Kubernetes is one of the most popular tools in cloud
computing and is becoming more and more popular every day.
All the projects are migrating to Kubernetes and it is
already becoming the standard in most companies as
a result. Of course, the need for IT professionals
who know Kubernetes is higher than ever and is increasing
every year. But the demand for Kubernetes professionals is way
higher than the number of people who actually know Kubernetes.
This means if you invest time in learning Kubernetes and
getting certified as a Kubernetes administrator,
you'll have an incredible advantage and a head start in
your IT career. Now, Kubernetes is
not the easiest tool to learn, set up and manage,
so if you want to become a Kubernetes administrator you will
need to learn a bunch of stuff. I have taught hundreds of
thousands of people Kubernetes through my videos and now I
have created this full course to teach you everything necessary
to get started with kubernetes from zero and become
an expert in it. You will be prepared to handle any
issues in the cluster. You will know exactly how Kubernetes
works and be able to support teams in your company to
use kubernetes properly after completing this course.
This course is mostly demo led projects where you work
hands on along with me, to practically apply all the concepts
you learn, but also understand the use cases of each
concept and really know why and how to use it.
And to make understanding the theoretical concepts easier. We have
animated videos and real world examples to understand
how it all applies in the real world projects.
Now you also know how important it is to prove your knowledge
in the it world and a certification is a great way to show
your skills and this course prepares you completely
for the CKA exam so that you can become
a certified Kubernetes administrator. So let's go
through the course contents and see what you will learn
from our Kubernetes administrator course. We will
start with the main Kubernetes concepts and understand
how Kubernetes architecture works, what Kubernetes resources
are, learn about Kubernetes configuration files
and generally how to work with Kubernetes. We will then install
a Kubernetes cluster from scratch on virtual
machines. For that we will use a Kubeadm tool
and learn and understand all the concepts about control plane
processes, how they work, how they get configured and
so on. You will also learn about container runtime interface
in Kubernetes and how is it possible to use different container
runtime technologies with Kubernetes. We will also look
at a very interesting topic which is networking in Kubernetes
and container networking interface. We will learn
about how pod networking works and how it is configured as well
as install a networking plugin to create a networking
layer in our Kubernetes cluster. We will also learn
how DNS works in Kubernetes and learn about
core DNS which is the DNS service in Kubernetes.
We will also take a look at how certificates work in Kubernetes,
what certificates get automatically created and
how you as a Kubernetes administrator can manage that.
In the same section we will also learn about very important Kubernetes
concepts like namespaces, how to work with Kubectl
which is a Kubernetes command line tool. You will learn about
Kubeconfig file and how to use that to connect to the
cluster, as well as how to configure and modify that and also
using Kubeadm tool you will learn how to join any worker nodes
to the cluster. Once you have installed and configured the
cluster, of course you want to start deploying your applications in
it and make it accessible externally. So we will learn
how to deploy applications inside the cluster using
deployments and how to make them accessible with
services. You will also learn about different types of services
in Kubernetes, how to use each one, and more importantly,
how they compare to each other. One of the common ways of
configuring external access to our applications running
in Kubernetes is ingress. So you will learn
what ingress controller is and how to create ingress resources
to configure routing in a cluster. And since
we will be installing the ingress controller application using helm,
you will also learn what helm is, how it works,
and how to use it to easily install different applications
in Kubernetes. Now of course you won't be the only one
working with the cluster because developer teams and other people
will also need access. But you can't just give everyone
admin access to the cluster. So we will
learn about the concept of users and permissions in Kubernetes. We will
learn about RBEC or role based access control.
We will also learn how client certificates work in Kubernetes
and we'll create a client certificate for a new cluster
user. Since DevOps is all about automation,
you will have to automate processes like deploying applications
from the CI CD pipeline to Kubernetes. For such
integrations you also need users and permissions.
So we will learn how to create non human users for different tools
that interact with Kubernetes. When working with Kubernetes
things will go wrong. So everyone using Kubernetes should
learn how to properly debug and troubleshoot the cluster.
So you will learn about different ways of troubleshooting and debugging
in Kubernetes using temporary pods,
Kubectl formatting and also how to debug and fix Kubelet
service issues, et cetera. A very common use case is running
multiple containers in a Kubernetes pod,
so you will learn about such use cases and how to implement that
using init containers and multicontainer pods.
When deploying databases or other stateful applications in
kubernetes, you need to take care of persisting the data.
For that we will learn about volumes, what different types
of volumes are available for different use cases, and how
to configure each one of them. We will also see how to
create external configuration for our applications with
config, map and secret components. Now when you have hundreds
or thousands of pods running in your cluster, you want to
make sure each pod has enough resources to
run and also that one pod doesn't take up all
the resources on the server. For that we will learn how
to configure resource requests and limits in pods.
Next we will learn about concepts of taints and tolerations
as well as node selectors, node affinity and
interpod affinity in kubernetes and what role they
play in scheduling pods in the cluster.
You will also learn how to configure health status
checks for containers inside the pods using
liveness and readiness probes. When deploying new application
releases in a cluster, it's important to understand how
the pods get upgraded to the new application version.
So for that we will learn about deployment strategies in kubernetes
such as rolling updates and how all this
works. One of the important tasks of the Kubernetes
administrator is to prepare for any disaster
scenarios and make it possible to easily recover cluster
in such cases. For that we will learn how to backup
and restore eTCD data and also learn the
theoretic concepts behind in many cases you may need
to automate your tasks with Kubernetes and for that it's
important to learn how Kubernetes rest API
works and how to use it to get information from the cluster
as well as make changes to it. Another very common task
for a Kubernetes administrator is making sure the cluster
is always up to date using the latest Kubernetes version
so you will learn step by step how to upgrade
Kubernetes cluster on control plane nodes as well as
worker nodes. As a cluster admin, you will often
have to manage multiple Kubernetes clusters, and for
that it's important to know the concept of contexts and
how to use contexts to switch between clusters when
administering them. As part of the Kubernetes
administrator job, you will also learn how to check expiration
of Kubernetes certificates and how to renew them. When configuring
Kubernetes clusters, you will have to also take care
of securing your cluster in different ways. One of the ways
of securing the cluster is by restricting the communication between
the applications within the cluster to minimize
the attack surface. And for that we will learn about the
network policies and how to configure them in Kubernetes.
And finally, if you want to take the CKA exam,
I prepared some useful tips that will help you totally
ace the exam. Now, equipped with all this
knowledge, you'll be prepared to pass the Kubernetes administrator
exam, but more importantly, be able to actually
set up and administer Kubernetes clusters in your projects.
The course is accompanied with a git repository including
all the relevant links, commands and examples I'm using
in the demos so you can easily work along.
I'm super excited to teach you all this, so let's
get started right into the definition. What is Kubernetes?
So Kubernetes is an open source container orchestration
framework which was originally developed by Google. So on the foundation
it manages containers, be docker containers, or from
some other technology, which basically means that Kubernetes
helps you manage applications that are made up
of hundreds or maybe thousands of containers,
and it helps you manage them in different environments
like physical machines, virtual machines or cloud
environments, or even hybrid deployment environments.
So what problems does Kubernetes solve and what are
the tasks of a container orchestration tool actually?
So to go through this chronologically, the rise of
microservices caused increased usage of container technologies
because the containers actually offered the perfect host for small
independent applications like microservices.
And the rise of containers and the microservice technology
actually resulted in applications. They're now
comprised of hundreds, or sometimes maybe even thousands of
containers. Managing those loads of containers across multiple
environments using scripts and self made tools can
be really complex and sometimes even impossible.
So that specific scenario actually caused the need
for having container orchestration technologies.
So what those orchestration tools like Kubernetes do
is actually guarantee following features. One is
high availability in simple words, high availability
means that the application has no downtime, so it's always
accessible by the users. A second one is scalability,
which means you can scale your applications fast when
you have more load on it and more users are trying to access it.
And the same way you can easily scale it down when the load
goes down. So it makes your application more flexible
to adjust to the increasing or decreasing load.
And the third one is disaster recovery, which basically means
that if an infrastructure has some problems like data
is lost, or the servers explode or something bad happens with the server center,
the infrastructure has to have some kind of mechanism to backup
the data and to restore it to the latest state so that
application doesn't actually lose any data and the containerized
application can run from the latest state after
the recovery. And all of these are functionalities that
container orchestration technologies like Kubernetes offer
that we as Kubernetes administrators or users
will be working with most of the time to make it easier to
understand all these components. I'm going to build a simple use case of
a web application with a simple database, and I'm
going to show you step by step how each component in Kubernetes
helps you deploy such an application setup and what is the
role of each of these components?
So let's start with the basic setup of a worker node,
or in Kubernetes terms a node which is a
simple server, a physical or virtual machine. And the basic
component, or the smallest unit of kubernetes is a
pod. So what pod is, is basically an abstraction over
a container. So if you're familiar with docker containers or
container images. So basically what pod does is
it creates this running environment or a
layer on top of the container. And the reason is because
kubernetes wants to abstract away the container
runtime or container technologies so that
you can replace them if you want to. And also because you
don't have to directly work with Docker
or whatever container technology you use in
a Kubernetes. So you only interact with a Kubernetes layer. So we have
an application pod which is our own application, and that
will maybe use a database pod with its own container.
And this is also an important concept here. Pod is
usually meant to run one application container
inside of it. You can run multiple containers inside one pod,
but usually it's only the case if you have one main application container
and a helper container or some side service
that has to run inside of that pod. And as you
see, this is nothing special, you just have one server and two containers
running on it with an abstraction layer on top of it. So now let's see
how they communicate with each other in Kubernetes world. So kubernetes
offers out of the box a virtual network, which means that each pod
gets its own IP address, not the container, the pod gets
the IP address and each pod can communicate
with each other using that IP address, which is an internal IP address.
Obviously it's not the public one. So my
application container can communicate with database using the IP address.
However, pod components in kubernetes also an
important concept, are ephemeral, which means that they can die
very easily. And when that happens, for example, if I
lose a database container because the container crashed,
because the application crashed inside, or because
the node, the server that I'm running them on ran
out resources, the pod will die and a new
one will get created in its place. And when that happens,
it will get assigned a new IP address, which obviously
is inconvenient if you are communicating with the database using
the IP address, because now you have to adjust it every time pod restarts.
And because of that, another component of kubernetes called service
is used.
So service is basically a static IP address or
permanent IP address that can be attached, so to say,
to each pod. So my app will have its own
service and database pod will have its own service.
And the good thing here is that the lifecycles
of service and the pod are not connected.
So even if the pod dies, the service and its
IP address will stay. So you don't have to
change that endpoint anymore. So now
obviously you would want your application to be accessible
through a browser, right? And for this you would have to create an external
service. So external service is a service that opens the
communication from external sources, but obviously you
wouldn't want your database to be open to the public requests
and for that you would create something called an internal service.
So this is a type of a service that you specify
when creating one. However, if you notice, the URL
of the external service is not
very practical. So basically what you have is an
HTP protocol with a node IP address,
so of the node, not the service, and the port number
of the service, which is good for test purposes if
you want to test something very fast, but not for the end product.
So usually you would want your URL to look like this if
you want to talk to your application with a secure protocol
and a domain name. And for that there is another
component of kubernetes called ingress. So instead
of service the request goes first to ingress and it does the forwarding,
then to the service. So now we saw some of the very basic
components of kubernetes. And as you see, this is a very simple
setup. We just have a one server and a couple of containers
running and some services, nothing really special where
Kubernetes advantages or the actual cool features really
come forward, but we're going to get there step by step. So let's
continue.
So as we said, pods communicate with each other using
a service. So my application will have a database
endpoint, let's say called MongoDB service that
it uses to communicate with the database. But where do
you configure usually this database URL or endpoint?
Usually you would do it in application properties file
or as some kind of external environmental variable,
but usually it's inside of the built image of the
application. So for example, if the endpoint of
the service or service name in this case changed to
MongoDB, you would have to adjust that URL in the application.
So usually you'd have to rebuild the application with
a new version and you have to push it to the repository and
now you'll have to pull that new image in your
pod and restart the whole thing. So a little bit tedious
for a small change like database URL. So for
that purpose, Kubernetes has a component called
config map. So what it does is it's basically your external
configuration to your application. So config map
would usually contain configuration data like
URLs of a database or some other services that you use.
And in Kubernetes you just connect it to the pod
so that pod actually gets the data that config map
contains. And now if you change the name of the
service, the endpoint of the service, you just adjust the
config map and that's it. You don't have to build a new image, you don't
have to go through this whole cycle. Now part
of the external configuration can also be database
username and password, right, which may also change
in the application deployment process. But putting a
password or other credentials in a config map in a plain
text format would be insecure, even though it's an external
configuration. So for this purpose, Kubernetes has
another component called secret.
So secret is just like config map, but the difference is that
it's used to store secret data credentials,
for example, and it's stored not in a plain text format of
course, but in base 64 encoded format.
But of course base 64 encoding a secret doesn't make it automatically
secure. The secret components are meant
to be encrypted using third party tools in
Kubernetes, because Kubernetes doesn't encrypt them out of the box.
And there are tools for that from cloud providers or
separate third party tools that you can deploy on Kubernetes
to encrypt your secrets and that will make secrets secure.
So secret would contain things like credentials and
of course I'm in database user. You could also put in config map,
but what's important is the passwords, certificates,
things that you don't want other people to have access to
would go in the secret. And just like config map, you just connect
it to your pod so that pod can actually see those data
and read from the secret. You can actually use the data
from configmap or secret inside of your application pod
using for example, environmental variables or even as a
properties file. So now let's see another very important
concept generally, which is data storage and
how it works in Kubernetes. So we have this database pod
that our application uses, and it has some data or it generates some data
with this setup that you see now if the database container
or the pod gets restarted, the data would
be gone. And that's problematic and inconvenient,
obviously, because you want your database data or
log data to be persisted reliably long term.
And the way you can do it in Kubernetes is using another
component of Kubernetes called volumes.
And how it works is that it basically attaches
a physical storage on a hard drive to your pod.
And that storage could be either on a local machine, meaning on the
same server node where the pod is running, or it could
be on a remote storage, meaning outside of the Kubernetes cluster.
It could be cloud storage, or it could be your own premise
storage, which is not part of the Kubernetes cluster,
so you just have an external reference on it. So now when the
database pod or container gets restarted, all the data will
be there, persisted. It's important to understand the distinction
between the Kubernetes cluster and all of its
components and the storage, regardless of whether
it's a local or remote storage. Think of a storage as
an external hard drive plugged in into the Kubernetes
cluster. Because the point is, Kubernetes cluster
explicitly doesn't manage any data persistence,
which means that you as a Kubernetes user or an administrator
are responsible for backing up the data, replicating and
managing it and making sure that it's kept on a proper hardware,
et cetera, because it's not taking care of kubernetes.
So now let's see, everything is running perfectly and a user can access
our application through a browser. Now with this
setup, what happens if my application pod
dies, right, crushes or I have to restart the
pod because I built a new container image.
Basically I would have a downtime where a user
can reach my application, which is obviously a very bad thing
if it happens in production. And this is exactly the
advantage of distributed systems and containers. So instead of
relying on just one application pod and one database
pod, et cetera, we are replicating everything
on multiple servers. So we would have
another node where a replica or clone of our
application would run, which will also be
connected to the service. So remember previously we said the service is like
an persistent static IP address with
a DNS name, so that you don't have to constantly
adjust the endpoint when a pod dies.
But service is also a load balancer, which means that the service will
actually catch the request and forward it to whichever pod is
list busy. So it has both of these functionalities.
But in order to create this second replica of the my application
pod, you wouldn't create a second pod, but instead
you would define a blueprint for a my application pod and
specify how many replicas of that pod you would
like to run. And that component, or that blueprint is
called deployment, which is another component of kubernetes.
And in practice you would not be working with pods
or you would not be creating pods, you would be creating deployments
because there you can specify how many replicas and you can
also scale up or scale down number of replicas
of pods that you need. So with pod, we said that pod is a
layer of abstraction on top of containers,
and deployment is another abstraction on top of
pods, which makes it more convenient to interact with the pods,
replicate them and do some other configuration.
So in practice you would mostly work with deployments
and not with pods. So now if one of the replicas
of your application pod would die, the service will forward the request
to another one. So your application would still be
accessible for the user. So now you're probably wondering, what about the database
pod? Because if the database pod died, your application
also wouldn't be accessible. So we need a database
replica as well. However, we can't replicate database
using a deployment. And the reason for that is because
database has a state, which is its data,
meaning that if we have clones or replicas of
the database, they would all need to access
the same shared data storage, and there
you would need some kind of mechanism that manages
which pods are currently writing to that storage or
which pods are reading from that storage in order to avoid
data inconsistencies. And that mechanism,
in addition to replicating feature is
offered by another Kubernetes component called stateful
set. So this component is meant specifically for
applications like databases. So MySQL,
MongoDB, Elasticsearch or any other stateful
applications or databases should be created using
stateful sets and not deployments. It's a
very important distinction. And stateful set,
just like deployment, would take care of replicating
the pods and scaling them up or scaling them down,
but making sure that database reads and writes are synchronized
so that no database inconsistencies are offered.
However, I must mention here that deploying database
applications using stateful set in Kubernetes cluster
can be somewhat tedious. So it's definitely more
difficult than working with deployments where you don't have all
these challenges. That's why it's also a common practice
to host database applications outside
of the Kubernetes cluster and just have the deployments or
stateless applications that replicate and scale
with no problem inside of the Kubernetes cluster and communicate
with the external database. So now that we have two replicas of
my application pod and two replicas of the database, and they're
both load balanced, our setup is more robust,
which means that now even if node one, the whole node server
was actually rebooted or crashed and
nothing could run on it, we would still have a second node with
application and database pods running on it,
and the application would still be accessible by the user until
these two replicas get recreated. So you can
avoid downtime.
Now let's say we want to collect logs in our cluster from each
pod. So we need an application that
will run on each node and collect all
the logs that pods are generating there.
Or think about kubeproxy, which as you learned,
needs to run on each and every cluster node.
So let's say for these two applications,
a log collector and kubeproxy, we create a deployment
and we set the replica count to the number
of nodes. Now what happens if after a
couple of days we add two new nodes to the cluster?
Now we need to adjust the replica number so that
qproxy or a log collector pod will also
run on those two new nodes. Now the next day let's
say we delete one of the nodes. Now we need to remove that one
replica again, because otherwise we're going to have two cube
proxies or log collector pods running on one of the
nodes. Also, we can't make sure that each node will
get just one pod of the application and
the pods will be equally distributed among the nodes.
So how can we solve all these issues for such
applications? Well, these are all the things that another
Kubernetes component automatically manages for you,
and that's a demon set component.
Demon set is basically a Kubernetes component, just like a
deployment or stateful set with the difference that
it automatically calculates how many
replicas of the application it should deploy, depending on
how many nodes you have in the cluster. And it also deploys
just one pod or one replica on each node
in the cluster. So when you add a new node to the cluster,
it will automatically start a pod replica there.
And when you remove a node, it will basically just remove that pod
replica. So you don't have to define replica count
with demon set component because it will automatically scale
down or scale up the replica count depending
on the number of nodes, and also guarantee only
one replica per pod.
So to summarize, we have looked at the
most used Kubernetes components. We started with the pods and the
services in order to communicate between the pods and the
ingress component, which is used to route traffic
into the cluster. We've also looked at external configuration
using config maps and secrets, and data persistence
using volumes. And finally, we've looked
at pod blueprints with replicating mechanisms
like deployments and stateful sets, where stateful
set is used specifically for stateful applications like
databases. Just using these core components,
you can actually build pretty powerful Kubernetes clusters worker
node, and we're going to see what is the difference between those and
which role each one of them has inside of the cluster.
And we're going to go through the basic concepts of how kubernetes
does what it does, and how the cluster is self managed and
self healing and automated, and how you as an
operator of the Kubernetes cluster should end up having much less
manual effort.
And we're going to start with this basic setup of one
node with two application pods running on it.
So one of the main components of a Kubernetes architecture
are its worker servers or nodes.
And each node will have multiple application pods with
containers running on that node. And the way
Kubernetes does it is using three processes that
must be installed on every node that are used to schedule
and manage those pods. So nodes are the cluster servers
that actually do the work. That's why sometimes also
called worker nodes. So the first process that
needs to run on every node is the container runtime.
Some of the container runtimes are docker, container D
and cryo. The most popular container runtime
today, used in most of the Kubernetes clusters and by
most major cloud providers, is container D,
which is much more lightweight than Docker, for example.
However, as you see in my pods, I have docker icons,
because you can run docker images on any container runtime.
So because application pods have containers running inside
a container, runtime needs to be installed on every
node. But the process that actually schedules those pods
and the containers then underneath is Kubelet,
which is a process of Kubernetes itself.
Unlike container runtime that has interface with
both container runtime and the machine, the node
itself. Because at the end of the day, Kubelet is responsible for
taking that configuration and actually running a pod,
or starting a pod with a container inside, and then assigning
resources from that node to that container like
cpu, ram and storage resources. So usually
Kubernetes cluster is made up of multiple nodes which
also must have container runtime and Kubelet services
installed. And you can have hundreds of those worker nodes which
will run other pods and containers and replicas of the
existing pods, like my app and database pods in
this example. And the way that communication between them works is
using services, which is sort of a load balancer
that basically catches the request directed to the pod
or the application like database, for example, and then forwards it
to the respective pod. And the third process that
is responsible for forwarding requests from services
to pods is actually Kubeproxy that also
must be installed on every node. And Kubeproxy
has actually intelligent forwarding logic inside that
makes sure that the communication also works in
a performant way with low overhead. For example,
if an application my app replica is making
a request to the database, instead of service just randomly
forwarding the request to any replica, it will actually
forward it to the replica that is running on the same
node as the pod that initiated the request,
this way avoiding the network overhead of sending
the request to another machine. So to summarize,
two Kubernetes processes, Kubelet and kubeproxy
must be installed on every Kubernetes worker node along
with an independent container runtime in order for
Kubernetes cluster to function properly. But now the question is
how do you interact with this cluster? Or do you decide on
which node a new application pod or database pod
should be scheduled? Or if a replica pod
dies, what process actually monitors it and then reschedules it
or restarts it again? Or when we add another server,
how does it join the cluster to become another node and get
pods and other components created on it? And the answer is all
these managing processes are done by master nodes.
So master servers or master nodes have completely different
processes running inside, and these are four processes
that run on every master node that control the cluster state
and the worker nodes as well. So the first service
is API server. So when you as a user want
to deploy a new application in a Kubernetes cluster,
you interact with the API server using some client.
It could be a UI like Kubernetes dashboard, could be command
line tool like kubelet or a Kubernetes API.
So API server is like a cluster gateway
which gets the initial requests of any
updates into the cluster or even the queries from
the cluster. And it also acts as a gatekeeper
for authentication to make sure that only authenticated
and authorized requests get through to the cluster.
That means whenever you want to schedule new pods, deploy new
applications, create new service, or any other components,
you have to talk to the API server on the master node
and the API server, then validate your request.
And if everything is fine, then it will forward your request to
other processes in order to schedule
the pod or create this component that you requested. And also if
you want to query the status of your deployment or
the cluster health, et cetera, you make a request to the API server
and it gives you the response, which is good for security because
you just have one entry point into the cluster. Another master
process is a scheduler. So as I mentioned, if you send
an API server a request to schedule a new
pod, API server after it validates your request
will actually hand it over to the scheduler in order to start
that application pod on one of the worker nodes. And of
course, instead of just randomly assigning it to any node,
schedule has this whole intelligent way
of deciding on which specific worker node the
next pod will be scheduled or next component will
be scheduled. So first it will look at your request and see
how much resources the application that you want to schedule
will need, how much cpu, how much ram, and it's going to go
through the worker nodes and see the available resources
on each one of them. And if it sees that one
node is the least busy
or has the most resources available, it will schedule the
new pod on that node. An important point here is that
scheduler just decides on which node
a new pod will be scheduled. The process that actually does.
The scheduling that actually starts that pod with a container
is the kubelet. So it gets the request from the scheduler
and executes that request on that
node. The next component is controller manager, which is
another crucial component, because what happens when pods
die on any node, there must be a way to detect
that the nodes died and then reschedule those pods
as soon as possible. So what controller manager does is
detect state changes, like crashing
of pods for example. So when pods die,
controller manager detects that and tries to recover
the cluster state as soon as possible. And for that
it makes a request to the scheduler to reschedule those dead pods.
And the same cycle happens here where the scheduler decides,
based on the resource calculation, which worker
nodes should restart those pods again, and makes
requests to the corresponding kubelets on those worker
nodes to actually restart the pods. And finally,
the last master process is Etsy,
which is a key value store of a cluster state.
You can think of it as a cluster brain actually,
which means that every change in the cluster, for example
when a new pod gets scheduled, when a pod dies,
all of these changes get saved or updated into
this key value store of etCD. And the reason why ETCD
store is a cluster brain is because all of
this mechanism with scheduler, controller manager, et cetera,
works because of its data. So for example,
how does scheduler know what resources are available
on each worker node? Or how does controller manager
know that a cluster state changed in some way? For example pods
died? Or that Kubelet restarted new pods upon the request
of a scheduler? Or when you make a query request
to API server about the cluster health, or for example
your application deployment state, where does API server get
all this state information from? So all of this information
is stored in ETCD cluster. What is not stored in
the ETCD key value store is the actual application
data. For example, if you have a database application running
inside of the cluster, the data will
be stored somewhere else, not in the eTCD. This is just cluster
state information which is used for master processes
to communicate with the work processes and vice
versa. So now you probably already see that master
processes are absolutely crucial for the cluster operation.
Especially the ETCD store which contains some data
must be reliably stored or replicated. So in practice,
Kubernetes cluster is usually made up of multiple masters
where each master node runs its master processes,
where of course the API server is load balanced and
the ETCD store forms a distributed storage across
all the master nodes.
So now that we saw what processes run
on worker nodes and master nodes. Let's actually have a look
at a realistic example of a cluster setup.
So in a very small cluster you'd probably have two master nodes
and three worker nodes. Also to note here, the hardware
resources of master and node servers actually differ.
The master processes are more important, but they actually have less
load of work, so they need less resources like cpu,
ram and storage, whereas the worker nodes do the actual job of
running those pods with containers inside. Therefore they
need more resources. And as your application complexity
and its demand of resources increases, you may actually
add more master and node servers to your
cluster and thus forming a more powerful
and robust cluster to meet your application resource
requirements. So in an existing Kubernetes cluster
you can actually add new master or node servers pretty easily.
So if you want to add a master server, you just get a new bare
server, you install all the master processes on it and add
it to the Kubernetes cluster. Same way if you need two worker
nodes, you get bare servers, you install all the worker
node processes like container runtime, kubelet and Kubeproxy
on it and add it to the Kubernetes cluster. That's it.
And this way you can infinitely increase the power
and resources of your Kubernetes cluster as your
application complexity and its resource demand increases.
And what is a use case for each of
these components? Now how do you create
all these components in Kubernetes? There are two
options for that. The first and simple option
is using a Kubernetes command line tool
called Kubectl. Some people also call it kubecontrol
or kubectl. I prefer to call it kubectl.
With Kubectl we can create a deployment,
stateful set service or any other
Kubernetes component as well as delete
or update them. Later we will see how to install Kubectl
and connect it to the cluster and use it to create,
update and delete components. It is a very powerful
command line tool that lets you work with the Kubernetes
cluster, get information from the cluster about any resource
as well as create resources inside. However,
there is a limitation with this approach when
creating different resources, and that
is if we want to configure a more complex
stuff for our Kubernetes resources. For example,
if we want to configure multiple ports in a service or maybe multiple
containers in a deployment and so on. And this can become
very difficult and impractical to do with Kubectl
because you would have to pass in a bunch of parameters,
and sometimes it's not even possible to fully configure what
you want. So we need an alternative to Kubectl
where we can define more complex configurations for
deployments, services or any other components.
And that's where Kubernetes configuration files are used.
With Kubernetes configuration files you just
write the whole configuration of a component in a file.
In a nice editor you have a nice overview of
all the containers you are creating, all the configuration of ports,
et cetera. And once your configuration file is
done, you can simply apply what's in that file using
Kubectl apply command. You can even have multiple
components configured in one Kubernetes
configuration file and create them all with one apply
comment. If you want to update a component,
you can simply edit your configuration file and apply those
changes as well. And same way using a configuration
file, you can delete all the components
configured there using Kubectl delete command.
And just to get our technical terms right, note that
Kubernetes configuration files are also called Kubernetes
manifests.
So you saw two approaches of how to create,
update and delete components in Kubernetes cluster.
These two approaches also have their names. The first way
of creating, updating and deleting components using
Kubectl commands is called an imperative way
because we're telling Kubernetes what to do, create this
component, delete this resource,
update this attribute of an existing component,
et cetera. The approach with Kubernetes configuration files
is called a declarative way, which means we
simply declare what we want as a result
in the configuration file and we let Kubernetes
figure out what it needs to do to get us
that desired state. Which one is the
right one? You may be wondering. Well, to have a proper history of
what has been created, deleted and updated in the
cluster, it's better to use the Kubernetes configuration
files for any changes. This also ties into
the infrastructure as code practice, where you will put
all your config files as code in a code repository where
everyone in the team can access it and make changes that
are more transparent to the whole team, rather than everyone just
executing some commands from their laptops.
To make changes in a cluster. But imperative way
can be practical and useful when testing things
and making quick changes. So this could be
a use case for imperative approach. And as
I said, we're going to see both of these in practice in
the upcoming lectures. Now let's see examples
of how Kubernetes manifest files actually
look like for different components and
the contents of Kubernetes configuration file, which is the
main tool for creating and configuring components in
Kubernetes cluster. If you've seen large configuration files,
it might seem overwhelming, but in reality it's pretty simple
and intuitive and also very logically structured.
So let's go through it step by step.
So here I have examples of a deployment and service
configuration files side by side. So the
first thing is that every configuration file in
Kubernetes has three parts. The first part is
where the metadata of that component that you're creating resides.
And one of the metadata is obviously name of the component itself.
The second part in the configuration file is specification.
So each component's configuration file will have a
specification where you basically put every kind of
configuration that you want to apply for that component.
The first two lines here as you see is just declaring
what you want to create. Here we are creating deployment and
here we're creating a service. And this is basically you
have to look up for each component, there's a different API version.
So now inside of the specification part, obviously the
attributes will be specific to
the kind of a component that you're creating. So deployment
will have its own attributes that only apply
for deployment and the service will have its own stuff. But I
said there are three parts of a configuration file and
we just see metadata and the specification. So where's
the third part? So the third part will be a status,
but it's going to be automatically generated and edit
by Kubernetes. So the way it works is that
kubernetes will always compare what is the desired state
and what is the actual state or the status of that component.
And if the status and desired state do not match,
then kubernetes knows there's something to be fixed there, so it's going
to try to fix it. And this is the basis of
the self healing feature that Kubernetes provides.
For example, here you specify you want two replicas
of Nginx deployment. So when you apply this,
when you actually create the deployment using this configuration file, that's what
apply means. Kubernetes will add here the status of
your deployment and it will update that state continuously.
So for example, if a status at some point will say just
one replica is running, then Kubernetes will compare that
status with the specification and will know there is
a problem there. Another replica needs to be created. SAP.
Now another interesting question here is where does Kubernetes
actually get the status data to automatically add
here or update continuously. That information comes
from the itsyd. Remember the cluster brain,
one of the master processes that actually stores the
cluster data. So itsyd holds at any time
the current status of any Kubernetes component,
and that's where the status information comes from.
So as you see, the format of the configuration files is
Yaml. That's why the extension here,
and generally it's pretty straightforward to understand.
It's a very simple format, but YaML is very strict
about the indentations. So for example, if you have
something wrongly indented here, your file will be
invalid. So what I do, especially if I have a configuration
file that has 200 lines, it's pretty long.
I usually use some YAML online validator
to see where I need to fix that, but other than
that it's pretty simple. Another thing is where do you
actually store those configuration files? A usual practice
is to store them with your code, because since
the deployment and service is going to be applied to
your application, it's a good practice to store these
configuration files in your application code. So usually it
will be part of the whole infrastructure as a code
concept, or you can also have its own git repository
just for the configuration files.
Explain all about YAMl. We will see what YAML
is used for, and we'll go through the syntax of how to
write a valid YAML file. Generally speaking,
YAML is a serialization language, just like XML
and JSON. Serialization language basically means that applications
written with different technologies, languages,
et cetera, which have different data structures, can transfer
data to each other using a common agreed on or
standard format. And the most popular such formats are YAML,
JSON and XML. And the name YaML actually
stands for Yaml ain't markup language. And you can
create YAML file with one of those two extensions.
They're the same. One of the main reasons of why
YAmL's popularity has increased so much over the past years
is that it's super human, readable and intuitive,
which makes it a great fit for writing configuration files
for all those recent DevOps tools, like I
mentioned, Docker, kubernetes, etc. So to show
you an example, and also comparison between YAML,
XML and JSON formats, let's consider
this example. So this is how Yaml file would
look like. It's very straightforward, it's pretty clean. This is
the same data in XML format where
you have these so called tags, and then you have the
JSON format. And as you see, in XML and JSON,
data structures are defined using special characters in
XML. You have so called text with angle brackets. In JSon
you have curly brackets, and in Yaml you don't have those special
characters. So how data structure is defined in YAML
is through line separations and spaces
with indentations. That's why you can indent
and space in XML and JSOn as you wish. But in Yaml
you get a validation error if you have one single space and data
structure wrong, which may be a little bit annoying, but it
makes YAmL format the cleanest, most human readable
format of all three. So what are some of Yaml's use
cases to count a few? Yaml format is used for docker compose
files, for Ansible, Prometheus,
kubernetes, and many more tools.
Okay, so now that you know what Yaml is and where it's used,
let's dive into its syntax. So let's start with
the basic syntax, which is simple key value
pairs. So let's take an example that I just showed you,
and let's write key value pairs like app,
and let's call it user authentication.
And we have a port, let's put it
at 9000 and version of the app at
1.7. Just an example. So these are
simple key value pairs. This is how YaMl file is written,
and you have different data types. Here we have a string which notes
that we don't have to enclose it with quotes.
You can if you want to. So you can use either double quotes
or single quotes or no quotes at all.
And you have the number representations as well. If you need
to use some special character like line carriage
for example, then you have to enclose it in strings,
otherwise Yaml cannot recognize it. But other than that
you don't need quotes. So I'm going to mention here that in Yaml
you also have comments. So everything that starts with this sign
or with this character, basically YAml interprets as a comment.
So I can write comment here,
and basically I can use this comment between the
attributes anywhere in Yaml file where I want to make my file even
more readable and understandable. So this is a simple list
of key value pairs. What you can do is you can group them inside of
an object, so you can create an object in YAml, and you can do that
by indenting this individual key value pairs
and enclosing it in an object. And let's
call it a microservice like this.
And this becomes an object with microservice
with its attributes. And note that the space has
to be exactly same for each attribute
within the object. And also note that because YAML is so
sensitive about the spaces and indentation it's always a good idea
to use a YAML validator before you for example execute
a configuration file in Kubernetes or you apply that
or use that file to be sure that your
indentations are right and there are online tools for that.
One of them which I use is this one here but there are some other
online tools as well. I can link them in description. So what you
can do is you can just copy that and it tells you that it's
valid. If I for example did this it's going to
scream bad indentation. So you can check your validity here.
So let's go back in Yaml. You can also have lists.
So for example if I have multiple microservices like
this I can create a list of those microservices
simply by using dash. So like this.
And again important thing that those attributes
stay at the same level and the dash is right
here and you can also have boolean.