We'll save it into an ingress configuration file. So let's see what options
we have here. We have ingress name,
let's call it nginx, or let's call it Myapp
ingress. And I'm just going to
copy this and we're going to do the
actual configuration in the file. So dry run client
Yaml and let's save it into my ingress
Yaml file.
I'm going to clean up the unnecessary data here
and let's see what we have. And you see this is a
super basic ingress configuration file,
and you already learned the structure of ingress file
and these are basically the attributes. Now note one thing here,
which is some of the attribute names actually changed
in the recent version of Kubernetes. So you may
see ingress configuration files with attributes like
service name and service port, which doesn't work anymore
because this is the new attribute list.
So just to be aware, in case you see an ingress configuration
file which has service name and service port attribute
names. So what we need to configure here is that whenever a
request comes to the load balancer on
the load balancer's URL, which is the host,
and let's go see what is the host of the load balancer.
It is actually the DNS name. Now you could map it to
your own domain name, like myapp.com. In our
case, we just have load balancer's domain name.
Note that this cannot be an IP address, it actually has to be a
domain name. So we're going to use load balancer's domain
name, this long domain name that load balancer has
automatically assigned from AWS, and we're going to use
it as the host. That means again,
whenever a request comes to the
load balancer on the HTTP port, we want
to define what happens to that request.
And we're going to say that we want that request to be forwarded
to our internal service called
NgInX service,
on the port of NgInX service.
So some services have named ports.
In our case we can just specify a number of the port,
which is 80, 80. And finally
we have path, which basically adds to
the URL right here. So the combination of the
host and the path will basically mean that we want to configure an
ingress routing rule for this domain and
path like this for this URL. Basically in
our case, however, we want to create a rule for a
root path. So basically this domain name directly without
any edit path and path type is exact.
So this is going to match the path we defined here
exactly, which means with path type you can actually define prefix of
the path, for example. But let's leave our configuration at
this simple rule. Let's actually remove the
HTTP part here. And now let's
apply our ingress file. And here we have an error
that one of the services which is Ingress NginX
controller admission service with this IP address cannot
be connected with an internal error that a webhook
validation failed. And you may also have this error.
We're going to try to fix that with a simple workaround
because I don't want to go into too much detail here. So if
you do Kubectl get validating webhook
configuration, which is a
custom resource, basically this is not a Kubernetes
native resource, but rather part of the ingress Nginx
that we deployed. If we do Kubectl get validating webhook
configuration, we see this one resource.
Now we don't have to understand what this is and what it does. It is
in familiar kubernetes manifest file
format. All we have to do is change
one value here to
basically fix our problem. And if I scroll down here we
have an attribute called failure policy and we're
going to set it to ignore.
Save this. You see that webhook configuration was
edited and now let's actually try to apply ingress
again. So basically we just worked around the issue.
It's not fixed, which is a specific ingress issue.
And since we don't want to go too much into detail and fix that,
we're just going to disable it. And now we're able to create ingress
resource in the cluster. So how do we check ingress resources?
Kubectl get Ingress command
will list us all the available ingress configurations
basically in the cluster. And remember,
ingress is a namespaced resource.
So we're seeing ingresses in default namespace.
And also note that we created ingress component in the same
namespace as the service to which we are forwarding
the request to. So now if everything was configured properly
using this host address right here,
we should be able to access our NginX service. So I'm
going to copy that. And this is actually the same
load balancer name we used before and reload
again. And there you go, we have ingress
configuration that tells ingress controller
application that whenever this endpoint gets
hit in the browser, please forward that request
to the NgInX service. And we see the
NgInX welcome page here.
Now of course if you have multiple applications in the cluster
and you want all of them to be accessible through
the same host, but on different path. Then you
can make each application available on a certain path.
So let's see that configuration as well. Going back to the
cluster, I'm actually going to delete our existing
ingress,
and we are going to adjust the
ingress configuration.
And what we're going to do is we're going to say
whenever a request comes to this host on a path called
my app, on exactly this path,
forward that request to the NgInX service. So again,
let's save the change, apply the
ingress configuration, and let's
check our ingress again. Let's actually describe the ingress so
that we can see the configured
rules in a human readable way.
Right here we have the host, we have the path,
and we have the configured backend for that
URL. So now if we refresh the page on
the root destination without
any path, we're going to get bed gateway because nothing
or no backend is configured for a root
path. Right? Backend here is empty only
for myApp. Now let's try with MyApp URL.
And as you see, we actually get not found, which means we
were able to access NgInX. So the traffic routing actually
worked. We reached NgINX service and
the pods behind. But when Nginx got
the request, it actually got a request on MyEp.
And Nginx doesn't know what to do with that myapath
because it doesn't expect such a path. So what we
need to do here is we need to tell
Ingress to forward the request
coming to this host to this path.
But when it forwards that request to the service,
Nginx service, we want it to remove the myapp path.
So basically we just want the request to go directly
to the NgINX service without the myApp path, because NginX
does not expect such a path, it just expects a root path.
So how do we tell Ingress to remove the path when sending
the request further to the service? Well, there is
actually on configuration for that which goes into metadata
and looks like this, it's an annotations attribute and the configuration
is actually called rewrite target. So we are rewriting
the request before it reaches the
target service. And that's how the rewrite target configuration
looks like. So we're going to copy it into our configuration
file and
we're going to tell Ingress to rewrite
target to root path. So it's going
to rewrite the path from my
app to simply slash. So let's try this
out. I'm going to apply the configuration changes to
the existing ingress, and let's go
ahead and type Myapp in the browser again.
And this should actually show us
welcome to Nginx page. So that's how we can access applications
in the cluster on certain path. So we can have Nginx
service accessible on my app, we can have
maybe a database UI accessible at
my database and so on, and we can
configure all of that using simple ingress
configuration.
Now just a couple of notes here on Ingress and Ingress
controller manager before we wrap this up.
First of all, you notice that we have
just one single ingress controller pod running in
the cluster. Of course, in a production environment this is not very
optimal because you are dependent on one single replica.
So ideally you should have one replica
of Ingress controller pod per worker node,
so each worker node having its own ingress controller pod.
Another note on Ingress configuration itself is that
you can actually configure multiple different routes here.
So if you have ten applications and you want to
configure routes to all of them based on the path,
you can actually configure all of those right here
and have the same rewrite target annotation
for all of them, which basically removes the path that we just
came up with and sends a request to the service
on a normal standard endpoint there. And optionally
you can have a separate ingress component for each service.
And that's how you configure ingress for application
routing in your cluster and
set up for developers. It's time to give them access to
the cluster. But what kind of access do we want to give them? What kind
of permissions should they be able to do anything in the cluster?
What if they destroy some stuff? We don't want to just give
everyone an admin user access, right? So we need
to create users for the developers with limited
permissions. For that, let's first understand how users and
permissions work in Kubernetes.
Authentication and authorization works in Kubernetes,
how you can configure users groups and their
permissions in the cluster, and you will learn about
role based access control or RBEC concept
and which Kubernetes resources we use to define
permissions in the cluster. So let's start by
understanding why do we need to manage permissions in
the Kubernetes cluster in the first place. You have
a Kubernetes cluster that Kubernetes admins are
administering and developer teams are deploying resources
into now how do we manage permissions
for the cluster? Because administrators need different access
than developers, right? Developers should be limited to
what they can do in the cluster so that they don't break
stuff accidentally, while admins should be able
to administer the cluster. In security best practices,
we have the least privilege rule,
which means we give every user only the
permissions they need, not more. So let's
start with developers.
Let's say you have multiple namespaces in the cluster
and each developer team deploys their application in
the different namespace. How do you make sure
each team gets access to only their namespace and the
resources in that namespace so they don't accidentally
break something in the namespaces of other teams?
For this we have what's called RBEC in Kubernetes,
RBaC, which stands for role
based access control. So let's see how
that works. With RBEC you can define
access to each namespace using
roles. So role is bound to a specific
namespace and defines what resources in that
namespace you can access where resource is a pod,
deployment, service, secret, et cetera.
And what you can do with these resources,
like list, read these resources,
edit, delete, et cetera. So for each developer team,
you can create a role for their specific namespace
that they are managing and define what they can do inside
that namespace. Maybe they can only create stuff, but they
cannot delete any resources. But role only defines
the resources and access permission to those resources.
It doesn't include information about who gets that access
defined in the role. So how do we attach role
definition to a developer team for that? We have
another component in Kubernetes called role binding,
which is a very simple concept. Basically with role
binding we simply link a role to
a user or user group. So we can create
users and bind the role to each user using
role binding. But if you have ten developers
in a team that all need the same permission, you can instead
create dev team group with all the
users and then bind the role to that group instead
of binding that to each user separately. And with
role binding, all the members in this group will get
the permission in the cluster to do whatever is defined
in the role.
Now what about administrators? Kubernetes administrators
obviously are the ones that are administering the cluster.
They are managing all the namespaces,
configuring the volumes for the developer teams that are available
cluster wide, et cetera. So they are doing
cluster wide operations. So how do
we define their permissions? In Kubernetes, role doesn't
work here because role is limited to a namespace and
admins, as we just said, need cluster wide access.
Well, for that we have another component from RBEC
which is cluster role. Cluster role defines what
resources have what permissions,
but cluster wide instead of limited to a
specific namespace. So for the admins we
would create a cluster role, an admin group,
and then attach the cluster role to the admin group using a
cluster role binding.
Now there is one important question here, which is how
do we create users or groups in Kubernetes
that we can then assign role or cluster role to?
Well, Kubernetes itself doesn't actually provide any
resources or a specific way of creating and
managing users and groups. It just gives us an interface
and flexibility to do it in many different ways.
So basically, user or user group concept or
resource in Kubernetes doesn't exist. So it relies
on external sources for creating and managing users
and groups. And this external source could be a
static file with user details, username and
token. It could also be certificates that
are assigned by Kubernetes itself or a third party
identity service like LDEP for example. So a Kubernetes
administrator will usually configure one
of these external sources like static
file or certificate or third party identity service in
the cluster so that Kubernetes has access to this
information. And then API server, which is one of the control
plane components of Kubernetes and which is the one
handling authentication of all the requests coming
in. Kubernetes cluster will try to authenticate
any user that is trying to connect to the cluster using
one of these configured sources. So these
are examples of token files for defining users.
You can pass these files to API server so
that API server knows where to look up the user information
to authenticate users when they try to connect
to the cluster. If you want to define groups that
users belong to, you can simply add a group column
in this users file in this static file and
this will give you users and groups in the
cluster. For certificates. You as an admin
will have to manually create certificates for different users
in your team. This will be the users that will
be allowed to connect to the cluster. Or as I said
as a Kubernetes admin, you will have to configure LDAP
as an authentication source for the API server.
So as I mentioned at the beginning, Kubernetes allows you
to configure these external sources for authentication,
but it doesn't manage them itself. You have to
manage them yourself as a Kubernetes administrator.
Great, so we gave our admins privilege to
administer the cluster using cluster role and limited permissions
to our developer teams so that each can manage only
their namespace and resources inside using roles.
So these human user permissions are taken
care of. Now what about application users?
Not only people have access to the cluster,
applications and services also access
the cluster. These applications can be internal
inside the cluster or outside the cluster.
For example, inside the cluster we may have a monitoring application
like Prometheus that needs access to all other applications
to collect metrics from them. And we also may have
microservices applications that only need resources
and access to resources within their specific
namespace. These applications are running
inside the cluster and are talking to other applications
or using other resources in the cluster.
And we also have the external applications, for example
a CI CD tool that deploys applications to the cluster,
or maybe a terraform application that configures the
cluster itself. As I said at the beginning with
the least privileges security practice,
we want to make sure the application only has permissions
that it needs in the cluster and not more.
So how do we define permissions for application users
in Kubernetes cluster? For that we actually have
a Kubernetes resource that represents an
application user, and this Kubernetes component
is called service account. So instead of user or
a group for human users, you create a service
component for the application user. So your application
like metric server, Prometheus or external CI
CD tool like Jenkins will get a service account
component inside the cluster as a representation
of that application's user. And the same
way as for human users, you can link
service account to a role or cluster
role with role binding or cluster role binding
component, and with binding
service account. Or the application user that is behind that
service account will get permissions that are defined
in the role or cluster role.
Now let's see what the Kubernetes configuration files actually look
like for all these components. First of all,
this is an example of a role configuration file
where we define what resources have what kind of
access. So in each role we have three sections
API group. The default one is
the core API group. So when using the
core API group you can leave it empty for others. We have to specify
then within that API group we have resources like
pod deployment, et cetera,
which are part of the defined API group. And then we have
as a third part access verbs like list,
create, delete, update, etc. That applies to
the resources in the defined API group.
This role is for a default namespace,
but if you want to give access to the defined resources
for namespace Myapp, you will add a namespace myapp
in the metadata of role. That's how you
can scope the role to a specific namespace.
You can also set access to resources
even more granularly. For example, instead of giving access to
all the pods in that namespace, you can define access to
only certain pods in that namespace using resource
name attribute. For example, if in the same namespace you
have your own application and maybe a
database, and you want to basically define
separate roles in the same namespace, but for
your own application and for database basically separately as
different roles, you can target these specific
pods or applications using the resource name attribute
and then define different privileges on those resources,
and then you have a role binding for that role to
then attach it to a user group
or a service account. Here you define
a cluster role for node, which is
a cluster wide resource. So you can basically define for the
Kubernetes administrators what privileges they
have on worker nodes, right? Or you can also define cluster role
for namespace management, since namespace is also a
cluster wide resource. But in addition
to defining permissions for cluster wide resources
in cluster role, you can also define cluster role for namespaced
resources like pods services, deployments,
et cetera, just like in the role. And if you define a
cluster role with pod access, it will mean access
to pods in all namespaces, not just one specific one as in
the role and in cluster role binding. You will then link that cluster
role again to a user group or
a service account.
And since are defined as Kubernetes manifest
files, you can create these components in Kubernetes cluster
just like you create any other components like pods
services, config maps, et cetera, and you can
also view them using Kubectl get or describe
commands. Another interesting and useful
thing is that you can actually check the privileges
that your current user has using Kubectl
auth command. If you're an admin, you can also check access
or privileges of any other users in the
cluster to see who has what permissions
in any namespace. And this could be a very useful
and convenient way to look up permissions that you have
basically given to different users inside your cluster.
So to wrap this whole thing up in Kubernetes security,
we have two different levels.
For example, Jenkins sends a request
to the API server that it wants to create
a new service in a default namespace.
On the first level, API server will authenticate
the user, human or application user, in this case
Jenkins in the cluster, to see
whether this application Jenkins is allowed
to connect to the cluster. Can this user access the cluster
at all? Does it have access credentials like username, password or
certificate to talk to the cluster if
authenticated? As the second step, Kubernetes will check the
authorization of that authenticated user using
RBEC. So we check what role or cluster role that
user has and based on that permission defined
there, does user have permission to perform this
specific task that it's trying to perform? So that's
how authentication and authorization in
Kubernetes looks like and how Kubernetes uses RBEC
and its components to manage authorization of
who is allowed to do what inside the cluster.
Now I have to note here that RBEC is actually one of
four ways of authorizing users or applications in Kubernetes.
Kubernetes supports four different authorization modes
such as Node EREC or attribute based
access control, RBEC and Webhook.
You can check them out in the official documentation in detail
if you want to, but we actually only need to know about RBEC
mode. And since Kubernetes supports multiple modes,
somewhere there should be a configuration of which modes are
enabled, right? So where is that set? That is
actually set in the API server configuration.
So if we check the pod configuration for
API server in manifests
and Kube API server,
among those many parameters that we pass to the
Kube API server application when we started there is a
parameter called authorization mode and
by default when we bootstrap the cluster with
Kubeadm you have node and RBEC authorization
modes enabled. And that means if you're maintaining
a cluster and it doesn't have RBEC enabled by
default, that's where you can edit.
We will look at how client certificates work in
Kubernetes so that you understand the concepts before we
actually create a Kubernetes client certificate for a new
user. Also this will be a refresher of Kubernetes certificates in
general that you already learned in this course. When we execute
Kubeadm init for bootstrapping the cluster,
Kubeadm generates all the needed certificates for
Kubernetes components as we already saw in the auto
generated folder.
EtCPKI,
which you learned stands for public key infrastructure.
We saw server certificates for API server
with private key, API server key and certificate
with public key APiserver CRT
and we also saw server certificates for Etsy
in ECD folder.
Kubeadm init also generated client certificates
for other services that talk to the API server
and we saw the private and public key certificates for clients
in the Kubeconfig files for Kubelet,
scheduler, controller, manager, et cetera.
So now the question is who signed all those certificates
which CA was used here? Well,
Kubeadm actually also generated own
CA for Kubernetes cluster. In fact it
generated a CA for API server and one
for itsty server. But Kubernetes own
generated cas are not globally trusted and recognized
ones, right? So why does it work? Why do all these client
components talking to API server, for example,
acknowledge a server certificate signed
by an auto generated Kubernetes CA?
Because all the clients got a copy of
the Kubernetes CA that signed the API
server certificate in the Kubeconfig files. In addition
to the client's key pair, we also see
CA certificate defined. This way the clients can
verify whether the service certificate was signed by it
and if yes, they know it can be trusted. So just
like your operating system has a list of CAS packaged
in, we just add a new CA to the list of the
client and the client will see the CA as one of the trusted
ones. This means the Kubernetes CAs are actually trusted
within Kubernetes by all components who have a copy
of it. As I
mentioned, Kubernetes allows configuring external credentials
for authentication like tokens, file certificates
or third party services. And I mentioned that these
are all managed externally by you. Kubernetes does
not manage them. In our demo we will actually configure
user authentication using one of these methods,
which is certificates. So we will configure a user
access for one of the developers in the team through a
client certificate. So let's see how this works in Kubernetes for
this it definitely helps to understand how certificates work
in general, regardless of Kubernetes. So if you don't
know anything about certificates, watch the prerequisite
video first and then continue from here. It will be much easier
to understand.
So you as a Kubernetes administrator or the user itself
will generate a client key for the user. Now user
will use this to authenticate with Kubernetes,
so you need this key signed by Kubernetes certificate
authority. For that you will generate a certificate
signing request. Till this point Kubernetes doesn't know anything
about this certificate. So how do we get this
request signed by Kubernetes? Well, Kubernetes has
something called a certificate API which allows
you to send it the csrs or
certificate signing requests and Kubernetes will then sign
it for you using its certificate authority.
Now any user or program can request Kubernetes
to sign a certificate through this programmatic certificate
API. So once requested, it gets in a pending
state so it doesn't automatically get approved for security
reasons and you as a Kubernetes administrator can
make the final decision whether a request can be approved or
denied. Once you approve the request, you will get the
signed certificate from Kubernetes CA, which you can
give to the client to use to authenticate with the cluster.
It may sound a bit complex, but it's actually pretty easy and
straightforward and we're going to see all that in a hands on demo.
A user in Kubernetes for a developer
tom by generating certificates for
Tom and getting it signed by Kubernetes certificate
authority using Kubernetes certificate
API. For that, first we will create a client
key for developer Tom using OpenSSL
command line tool, and then we will ask Kubernetes
certificate API to sign that certificate
signing request for us by creating a Kubernetes
resource called certificate signing request.
Once that's done, we're going to be able to approve the certificate signing request
as a Kubernetes administrator for developer Tom.
And finally we can get the signed certificate for
our user developer Tom from Kubernetes.
And with the resulting files we're going to see how to provide
user Tom with all the certificate files and
all the credentials to be able to access the cluster with
Kubectl command using his own dev Tom
user certificate. So this whole process can
actually be considered similar to creating a user
in Kubernetes, even though Kubernetes doesn't have user objects.
However, once we have the user, it also needs certain permissions
so it is able to authenticate with the cluster,
but it has to be able to do something inside the cluster.
So as a next step, we're going to give this new user dev Tom
certain permissions to create,
delete, update Kubernetes resources like pods,
deployments, services, et cetera, so that he can deploy his
own applications. And finally, we're going to see how to validate
the user permissions by checking what authorization
a user has and what permissions he does not
have. So that's going to be a human user like
a developer tom that will get access to the cluster.
As in the second part, we're going to create a non
human user for a CI CD tool like Jenkins to
be able to access the cluster with its own user.
And for that we're gonna create a service account for Jenkins.
Again, this will create a non human user in Kubernetes
which will need some permissions. So we're going to give the service account certain
permissions in Kubernetes cluster to create,
delete, update Kubernetes resources in only
MyApp namespace. And finally we're going to see
how you would access the cluster from Jenkins
using Kubectl and service account credentials.
We have a lot to do, so let's get right into it.
Great. So first, as I said, we need to generate
users client key and certificate
signing request, which is very easy to do using an OpenSSL
tool that you already learned in one of the previous lectures.
So let's go ahead and do that. OpenSSL command
should already be available on your server so we don't have to install it.
And a subcommand for OpenSSL is gen RSA
because we're generating an RSA key
and the name of the file that will contain the key will be
devtom key and we specify that as
out or output option. And finally we're going
to specify that we want a 2048
bit RSA key. That's it. That will create the
client key for dev Tom user.
And if I ls here, this is the
key and we can also check the contents of this file.
There you go. This is simply an RSA private
key file, so that one's done.
As a next step we're going to create a certificate signing request
for the key that we just generated. Again, open SSL
request because we're creating a new request and the
input for that request is going to be our key because
we want the key to be signed basically.
And again we need to save that request into an output
file and we're going to call that dev Tom
CSR certificate signing request.
And there is one more thing that we are going to do here, which is
adding a subject or setting a subject
inside the certificate that will be then generated where
we set the certificate name to be Tom. And this
basically will indicate that the certificate is
for user Tom and this is going to be the
name which Kubernetes will use when validating
the request using this client key
and certificate. So we're just going to call it Tom
and that's the command. This will actually give us
dev Tom CSR file
right here. Again, let's check how it
looks. And there
you go, you see certificate request and
the contents here.
So we have those two files here. Now as a next step we
need to send this certificate signing request
to Kubernetes itself so that Kubernetes can sign it
for us using the certificate authority of Kubernetes.
And we do that again by creating components in
Kubernetes in a Kubernetes native way, as you already know,
using configuration files. So I'm going to go
to Kubernetes documentation and search for certificate
signing request.
And here we have an example of how a certificate signing
request resource in Kubernetes will look like.
So I'm simply going to copy this example. So I'll take the yaml
part from here and we're going to create file
called Dev Tom CSR
Yaml and let's paste the contents.
So again certificate signing request,
that's a Kubernetes object coming from this API group
with this version and a couple of attributes here in the
specification. First let's change the name. Let's call it
Dev Tom. And the main part in the specification
is the request itself. So what is this
value? You can also check that in documentation. Actually the request
value that we set here is base 64
encoded value of the CSR
file that we generated. And you also see an example of
how to get that value from the CSR file.
So let's copy that. I'm going to save this changes
and we need the base 64 encoded value
of the CSR file contents. So the command that
I copied, of course we have to adjust the name
like this. So what we are doing is we are printing out
the contents of Dev Tom CSR
file. Then we are base 64 encoding
those contents by piping it to base 64
program. And then we're removing all the new
lines because we want the contents in one line.
Basically we don't need new lines, so we're trimming
all the new lines. So let's execute.
So that's the value, the basics before
encoded value of this file.
So back to our Kubernetes configuration file,
Dev Tomcsr Yaml. And what
I'm going to do is I'm going to push the existing value to a new
line and then I'm going to just delete it by clicking d
twice and paste in
the new value. And there you go. And note that this is one
string basically without any new lines
here, which is exactly what we need. The signer name will stay the same,
usages will stay the same. This is a client certificate
and we can actually extend the expiration date to
longer than one day. So this would be around 100 days.
So basically we set an expiration date on the certificate
and we renew it regularly before it gets expired.
And I'm going to save this and we have our
certificate signing request configuration for kubernetes.
And just like any other Kubernetes configuration file we
need to apply it using
Qctl apply command. So Dev Tom CSR
Yaml and when we apply the file we should get this error
that says that expiration seconds attribute or
field is unknown. And the reason for
that is because that field was actually added in the latest
Kubernetes version 1.22.
And we have installed Kubernetes
version 1.21 so
that's why it's not supported. What we can do is
basically just comment out or simply
remove the field and maybe use it when we upgrade the
cluster version. So I'm going to save the changes
and let's try to apply again. And there you go. So by creating
this CSR or certificate signing
request resource in Kubernetes, we basically sent the
Kubernetes certificate API a request
to sign our dev tom users
certificate. So let's see the state
Kubectl get. CSR will
actually list us all the signing requests that
are in the cluster and their conditions,
which this one is in a pending state. And we
as Kubernetes administrators also have to have
the ability to approve this. So that's the name
of the requester which is Kubernetes admin user.
That's the user we are connecting to the
cluster right now and executing the Kubectl commands. And the
user is basically defined in Kubeconfig
file that our Kubectl command is using.
So I'm going to do grep Kubernetes
admin and let's print out two
lines or so. And there you go. In the Kubeconfig
file we have the user which is Kubernetes admin
and that's the user we are executing those Kubectl commands with.
So that's the requester and we as an admin also
have the permission to approve any
certificate signing requests and
that's what we're going to do.
We're going to approve this request and for that there is a subcommand
called Kubectl certificate.
We can also see the help information on that. And this command
is used to modify any certificate resources
in the cluster. And we have proof or deny commands
for approving or denying csrs.
So Kubectl certificate approve and we
need the name of the CSR which is Dev Tom
approve. And now let's check again. We should have
CSR in an approved and issued state.
And this means we actually just got
our CSR signed by Kubernetes
CA and that signed certificate is what
we need for dev Tom user to
connect to the cluster. So we're going to extract that information using
Kubectl, get CSR dev
Tom and then printing it out in a yaml format.
So we're getting the details of this CSR and
as you see here we have a bunch of attributes like
the request that we set signer name et cetera,
and a new field in the status called certificate.
So as you know, status section is automatically
generated by Kubernetes. And this section
was basically automatically edited with all
these values. And one of them is the signed certificate
for our user which is again base 64 encoded.
So we would have to decode it to see the actual certificate.
So I'm going to copy that. And since we
have devtom key which is the private
key, we can also create devtom CRT
certificate which is going to be the public key of that pair.
And that's very easy to do.
We're going to basically echo the
base 64 encoded contents of the certificate.
Then we're going to decode it like
this. Let's see that first of all. And as you see we get
an actual certificate and
we could actually save this into a
file called Dev Tom CRT.
Let's clear this Ls and that's our
file. Let's check the contents. And there
you go. So now we have a key pair for our user which
is private key and public key with
the certificate which is signed by Kubernetes certificate
authority.
Now we have all the files that we need for devtom
user, but how do we actually connect to the cluster
now with this user's client
certificate? So as a next step, let's see how that
works. So basically when we give all these files to Tom,
the developer, how does he connect to the cluster using
his client certificate? So that's what we're going to see as a next step.
Right now when we execute Kubectl commands,
Kubectl actually uses the admin certificate because
that's what we have configured in the default
cube config file.
So we need to actually execute the Kubectl command
using the dev tom user.
So one way of doing that is to pass all the options
to the Kubectl command to override this default admin
configuration and to see what options we have
available. We can actually execute Kubectl options
command which will show us all the global configuration options that
apply to any Kubectl command. And there are
a bunch of them here, but the ones that we are interested in are client
certificate, client key, certificate authority
and server which is the address and port of Kubernetes
API server. And with these we're basically overriding
the default values coming from cubeconfig
file. So let's try to configure that. First of
all, where do we find the API server address?
We can look it up in the Kubeconfig file or we can
just do cluster info and
that's the address of API server.
So Kubectl server
the address, let's go to a new line and
specify certificate authority
which is located in EtcPKI
folder. That's where
all the Kubernetes certificates are located on the master node as you
already learned. So that's the certificate authority. Then we need
client certificate which
is Dev Tom certificate,
that's the file that we generated, that's signed by
the certificate authority of kubernetes.
Then we have client key which is again
what we generated at the beginning
and that's it. So we're telling Kubectl go to this server,
use this certificate authority to authenticate
the server, use this client certificate and key
to authenticate yourself with the API
server. And finally we need the actual Kubectl
command like get pod and let's execute. And when
we execute this we're going to have a couple of issues here. The first one
is that when we execute this command,
Kubectl takes all those configuration options,
plus it will also check the configuration from
the default cube config file.
And it says that in this default cube config
file, client cert data and client
key data are defined. And this one
has the precedence over client certificate
and client certificate data. And client key data
options have precedence or they override
basically client certificate and client key options. So again
to check that kubeconfig,
we see that in the default kubeconfig file,
the client certificate and client key values are defined
directly in the kubeconfig file. So we have the file contents
inside instead of link to the file. So this attribute
name, client certificate data takes precedence over
attribute called client certificate which references the
file. So to test our
command let's actually move this default file
temporarily from
cube folder to current folder so
it's not in the cube cube folder anymore.
And let's execute our Kubectl command again with
dev Tom users client certificate
and key and execute. And there you go. This actually
worked because we were able to connect to the cluster
and request to list the pods.
The error that you see here is because we haven't given our dev
Tom user any permissions for the cluster yet.
So what we get is basically forbidden.
So we have been authenticated with kubernetes, but Devtom
user is not authorized to do anything and we're going to
authorize him later in this lecture. So that's basically
one way of specifying credentials of a
specific user with Kubectl commands.
However, passing those values to every Kubectl
command as you can imagine will be very annoying.
So how can we avoid this and instead
go back to using our kubeconfig file? Well, just like we use
the admin user's kubeconfig file,
we can actually create our own kubeconfig file
for devtom user. So let's do that as a next
step. And for that I'm going to take the admin
user's kubeconfig file which we just copied
and we have it here and I'm going to create
a duplicate of it and call it devtom
conf. And now let's
actually change all the values from admin to
devtom user. So first of all we are reusing
what kubernetes already generated for us or for the admin
user. We have the certificate authority data already inside.
We have the server API, server address here, so everything's going
to stay the same. But there are a couple of things that we need to
adjust. One of them is the name of the
user. So we are not using Kubernetes admin anymore.
We have dev Tom user in the user section.
And do not forget to also change the
user in the contexts because that's the reference to
the name of the user and change it here as
well like this.
So we replaced the user everywhere. Now it's time to replace
the client certificate data for Tom.
These are client certificate and key for admin.
Now we have two options here. We can either reference
the client certificate and client key files just
like we did in our Kubectl command, or we can
base 64 encode the contents of the file
and then paste those contents right here
as value in order to reference the files.
If we don't want to have the contents of certificate and key files
here, we can use client certificate and
client key attributes.
And again I'm going to delete the line here
and here
as well. And this will be referencing dev
Tom cert crt
dev tom key. And this makes our kubeconfig
file a little cleaner and it's a little less work for
us because we're simply referencing the files. Now know that the location
of the file has to be obviously correct and we're going to specify
absolute path for both files so
that it works no matter where you put your kubeconfig file.
So let's save it. And now we can execute the Kubectl
command with the kubeconfig file of
Tom's user. And let's execute again. We have
connected to the server, we have authenticated with kubernetes,
but we're not allowed to list any pods or user.
Tom is not allowed to list anything in the cluster.
So now as a kube admin what you basically do
is you take the kubeconfig file that we just generated
for Dev Tom user. You take the certificate
file and the key file and you basically give all those
three files to Tom and he can use
that to execute Kubectl commands against the cluster. So on
his own laptop, Tom can basically take this
kubeconfig file and put it in his own home
directory, kube config
location.