Called items. So that's basically the top of the hierarchy.
Inside the items is an array and inside that array
we have objects for each pod and in that
object we have attributes like API version
kind and metadata. And metadata is the one
that contains the name of the pod.
So basically this way we can work through
the whole hierarchy to find the attribute that
we're looking for. So we have to chain all this together.
So again going back here we first
start with dot items and this will give us
all the items which is an array. From that array we
can get the first element like this. This will
be just one pod. So as you see this is
a very ugly output of JSON
configuration of one single pod.
And from that pod we want the metadata attribute.
Let's see that first getting a little bit smaller.
And in the metadata we have bunch of this stuff
but we only want to know the name.
And metadata name will give us
the name of the pod. So this basically ended
up being our first expression that gives us
the name of the first pod in the list.
But we want to print out names of all the pods. For that
we just do star which means for every
item in the array give me metadata
name value and execute.
And this is a list of all the pod names.
Now as you see we have the output in one single line which
is not very nice. So using JSON path expression
we can also print the values on a new
line and let's see how that works.
Json path we also have a couple of built in functions.
One of them is range which basically lets us iterate
through the items. And for each item print out
the metadata name and add
a new line here and then end
the whole expression. Again, this is probably not very
intuitive and you'll have to learn how to iterate through
arrays for example. But it will help you get specific output
that you're interested in. So let's execute this and as you
see you get the values in a nice list. Now let's
say we want multiple values, not just pod
names but also pod ips next to the names.
So how can we do that? Well, it's pretty simple actually.
After their metadata name we can create
a space or a tab like this and
then extract the IP address from status
pod IP of each item.
So here we have the name from the metadata section
and the pod IP is actually defined in the status section
of the item. So status and metadata are on the same
level. And this will actually give us pod
name and its IP address next
to each other. And this way you can specify any other attribute
you want to extract from this configuration. And let's do one
more again,
separated by tab.
And let's get the start time or when the pod
was started, which is also in the status section and
called start time. And there you go. So now
we have a list of all the pods with their
names, IP address, and when it was started.
Now as I said, the JSON path expressions
are not very easy and you may not want to type
that often. So one useful thing could be
to write custom scripts with JSON path expressions
for Kubectl to print out some of the most common data that
developers or you as an admin may need when
working with the cluster. So you can have these pre configured
and ready to go expressions whenever you need
them. So for example, we could save the above in a script
called pod name ip
created et sh
like this and make it executable.
And whenever you execute it, you basically have
the same output. So this could be a
useful way to use the JSON path expressions
without having to type them all the time. And you can distribute
the scripts to your developers as well.
Now if you have such scripts that give you an output of different
data, it may not always be clear what this data actually
represent. So could be a name of the pod, or it
could be a name of the service, or what these IP addresses
belong to or what this date is about. So it
will be actually useful to have some kind of column names
for all these data, right? So can we add column names
to these values? We can actually do that using
another output format type called custom columns,
which is simpler to use than the JSON path actually.
And this may also be very useful in debugging.
So let's see how that works. We have, let's use same Kubectl
get pod command, and instead of JSON path
we're going to have custom columns
output type. And the syntax is actually pretty
straightforward. We have the name of the column, let's call it
pod name. And this can be uppercase,
lowercase doesn't matter, I'm just going to use uppercase
and underscore separation after the name you
have column, and then you have to define which values
will be grouped under this column name. And in our
case that's going to be metadata name. Note here that
I don't have to use items, I can just grab the
metadata name directly. And we separate the rest of the
columns with their values using comma. So the
second column will be pod iP,
column status,
pod ip as we saw.
And finally, let's call the third
column created at and
the value is going to be dot status start time.
And note that you shouldn't have spaces between the comma here.
It should look exactly like this. And if I execute, you have
a super nice output with column name with
the values under it. So it's much more descriptive
and obvious what these values actually represent. So these were
some of the useful ways of debugging
in a cluster and maybe working a little bit more efficiently when
trying to find information about different cluster components
developers. Some issues happen to the control plane components
and worker processes. And since we are managing the
cluster ourselves, we need to take care of this.
Let's say one of the issues is that when we do Kubectl
get node, see, is that worker one
is in a not ready status. So obviously there is something wrong
with this node. The question is how can we debug this
and how can we identify what the issue is? The not
ready status of a node most probably indicates
that something is wrong with the Kubelet process running
on that node. So we can start by entering that node or
sshing into it and debugging and troubleshooting the Kubelet process.
And that's what we're going to do. We're going to ssh into worker one
and we're going to troubleshoot Kubelet. Now, Kubelet is not running as a
pod, but rather a Linux process, as we already learned.
So we're going to use Linux commands to troubleshoot it.
So first we're going to see whether Kubelet is running and which
state it is in. So we can do service
Kubelet status.
And this shows us that Kubelet is running.
However it is in activating status
so it's not running. And we also see a failure here.
Kubelet service failed and this seems like an error.
And we also see some of the logs of the Kubelet process that
says user localbean Kubelet. No such
directory. If we need more context or more logs,
we can also use journal control command to
check the complete logs of the Kubelet
service like this. So in our case, because we
see the error in the logs, we can try to identify
where this issue is coming from. So first of all, it says that
this path cannot be found. So we can validate
that by checking whether this
is accessible. And you see there is no file or
directory like this. So Kubelet executable is
not at this location. We can see where Kubelet
executable binary is located using which Kubelet
command. And this will show us the correct location
of Kubelet binary. Now where is
Kubelet configuration coming from? So where is this
binary executable defined so that we can fix it?
Well, in this output we actually see the location
of Kubelet configuration,
which is this one right here. So if we check this
location, and again we need
pseudo, you will see the
configuration which starts Kubelet.
And let's actually open it with Vim editor so we
can see some syntax highlighting as well.
And as you see, we have a couple of commands
here, just basic Linux commands that
basically configure and then start Kubelet service.
And all the way down here we have the exec start.
So basically where the start command of
Kubelet is defined with all the environment variables
as parameters. And right here we see that
wrong path is configured. So by updating it
to the right location which was
user,
Binkubelet should
fix the issue. So let's save this.
So we fix the configuration by providing
the correct location of Kubelet's executable.
However, we now have to restart Kubelet service so that
it can read the changed configuration.
And for that we need to first execute
demon reload. And then we are going to restart the
Kubelet service using system control. Restart Kubelet.
And again, let's check the status using
service Kubelet status command.
And as you see, Kubelet is now in an active
running state and we don't have the error message anymore.
And now of course we need to validate that node is
back to the ready state. It may take a couple of
seconds, but after that we should see that
worker one is back to ready. So that's how
you can troubleshoot and fix any issues with
Kubelet on the cluster nodes.
Now let's say we have a second issue where suddenly your
Kubectl commands stop working and we get
this error whenever we execute the Kubectl
command.
So whenever we try to execute Kubectl commands,
either we get an error that it cannot connect to the server or
the API server, or our Kubectl command, just hanks.
And we don't get any output like this for example.
So let's see how we can debug this issue. First of
all, we know that Kubectl configuration is defined in
a kubeconfig file. So if Kubectl is
not able to connect to the server, the first place we're
going to look at is the Kubectl configuration where the location
of the API server or the cluster is defined
as well as its credentials. So let's print out
the Kubeconfig contents and
validate that everything is configured properly.
First let's check the cluster configuration. We have certificate
data and the server address, so let's validate these two.
First of all, let's see that we are using the correct certificate
or that it hasn't been updated. So I'm going to
copy the certificate authority data
which is base 64 encoded. So we're going
to decode this.
So that's the CA certificate defined in the kubeconfig.
Now let's check that it is the same one
as what the cluster is using,
which is PKI
CA certificate.
And if we compare we see that this is the same
exact certificate, so the contents are the same. So the CA certificate
for the cluster is correct. The second thing we
want to check about the cluster is that the server endpoint is still
correct and it hasn't changed. We know that API server
is running on the master node on port six
four, three, so it's accessible on the master
node's ip address on this port, so the port is correct.
Now let's validate that the masternode's ip address is
also correct. And you can check that on the masternode itself
or in host file,
or we can also simply check it in the AWS console.
So this is our master node and that's the IP address
of the master node in the cluster. So I'm going to copy this
and compare it to what we have defined
here. And as you see this is a different IP address,
not the one that master node has, so that one needs
to be fixed. So this IP address needs to be an
IP address of the master, which is this
one right here, which we just copied. So we need to fix that.
So we're going to open the kubeconfig in an edit
mode and just going to paste in the correct IP
address of master Node and let's save it.
And now let's check that Kubectl commands work again.
And as you see we are able to
connect to the cluster again at this endpoint.
So these are some of the ways of debugging issues
in the cluster, either connectivity to your cluster or issues
on the nodes themselves.
Great developers have now access to the cluster and
they know how to debug stuff in there too. But at some
point they have a use case where they need to deploy
a small script next to the main application that
updates the cache of the application, or that talks
to the authentication service to authenticate users,
or an application that sends logs from the
application to a log service. So it's not part of the application,
but rather a small helper application for
the main application. In addition to that, they also want to deploy a script
that needs to run before each startup of the application.
The script prepares and configures the environment before application
startup, so they ask you, what is the best way to deploy
both of these scripts in Kubernetes cluster?
Do they create own pods for them, own deployment
files, or how will that work? So you go ahead and research
how this is done in practice.
As you learned in Kubernetes, Pod is like a virtual operating
system environment with its own IP address,
ports, access rules, its own network namespace,
et cetera. And you also learned that you can start multiple containers
inside the pod, one main application and a
small helper applications on the side. And that helper
application has a technical term called a sidecar
container. So if your MySQL database needs a script that runs
in parallel and synchronizes the data every five
minutes or so, that script will run in a sidecar
container inside the same pod. Same way, if you want to
collect logs regularly from your web application using
a separate application, you can deploy it as a sidecar
container in the same pod. The containers in the
same pod are able to talk to each other using localhost
without needing a service name or the IP
address of the pod or service, and they can share the
data among themselves as well. So having them
in the same pod makes the interaction between them much
easier. And note that you can have multiple sidecar
containers in a pod.
Now what about the script that is supposed to prepare the environment before
the main application runs? For example, it may need to
set some environment variables or do some system check
to make sure the environment is ready. Or as another example,
wait for a certain service to be available before the
main application can start. Do we run such scripts as
sidecar containers as well? Well, sidecar containers are
applications that run the whole time as the main application
is running and do some work regularly. In comparison,
this script would run just once at the beginning,
and that's it. Its job will be done. Also,
sidecar containers start at the same time as the
main container, so we can't be sure that environment
will be ready and prepared when the main application
starts. Well, for that we have a different type of container
called init container. You define them in its
own init container section of the pod.
Configuration and kubernetes will know to start it
first. Again, it will start in the same pod as the main application,
but as a first container it will do its job,
exit or complete, and only after that the main
and sidecar containers will be started. Now that you know how
such scripts or small applications need to be deployed
and learn about multicontainer pods with
init and sidecar containers, you want to test that
in practice and add the containers to the existing
deployment.
So we're going to open our NginX deployment configuration and
make the changes right here. First of all, let's add a sitecare
container that will be responsible for collecting
the logs of the application and sending it to a log service.
Now, in our case, we're just going to simulate it with a simple echo command,
but that could be a purpose of a sidecar container and
we're going to define that in the containers section. As you
see from the name as well, containers means it is a list
of containers. So in a YAmL format, the items
in a list always start with the dash. So we're going to have
another container here next to the NginX main container
and we're going to call this log sidecar.
And since we're just simulating using an echo
command, I'm just going to use a busy box image. You can also specify
a version and I'm going to pass in a
command to execute. And as I said,
the sitecar containers run the whole time
in parallel to the main application. So a log sidecar will
basically be a program that regularly collects the logs of the application,
sends it to a log service. So it's not going to be a
one time command. So to simulate that,
I'm just going to execute,
I'm just going to do shell executable.
And then we're just going to do a while loop here that basically
echoes something. Let's do sync application
logs and then it waits for 20 seconds
and logs again.
And we're going to need double quotes here. And this
is going to be executed in an endless loop.
So the log sidecar container will run
as long as the pod is alive. And you learned in one of
the previous lectures how to use the command attribute, right?
This is basically just overriding whatever is
defined in the image docker file as executable will
be ignored. And instead we're overriding it with
this command. And you also learned that you can use a combination
of command and arcs and basically pass this
as arguments. So this will be our sidecar container
and I'm going to save this, let's actually
delete the deployment, existing deployment
to create the new one kubectl
apply and let's create a new deployment
with two container pod and let's check
get pod. And as you see, three replicas
of the pod are being created, each with
two containers. And now in
order to check the logs of the container, we're going to do Kubectl
logs and the pod name.
However, when I execute this, you will see an error that
says the container name must be specified. So whenever we
have a pod with multiple containers, we always have to
specify explicitly which container we want to log
or which container we want to attach terminal to, et cetera.
And we can do that using c
for container and name of the container.
In this case, let's choose lock sidecar.
And as you see we already have the
echo commands, so it is running and executing
these commands every 20 seconds like
this. So that's our sidecar container.
Now let's go ahead and add the init container.
Again I'm going to open the deployment yaml.
And in addition to the containers attribute, we're going
to add init containers, which has
to be on the same level as containers here and
will be exactly the same type of list as
containers. The difference will be of course for kubernetes
to know that these containers should run first
and complete before this can start.
And again, init containers is a list. So you can have multiple
containers here as well. And let's say this init container will check
whether a certain service is available before the
main NginX application can run. So for example,
if the web application depends on a database, we can check here
MyDB available.
And again, let's use the busybox image and
the command will check whether a MyDB
service is available in the cluster or not. So what
we can do is execute until Nslookup,
let's call it MyDB service. So we're going to
do nslookup on MyDB service and
Echo waiting for database and
then we do that every 4 seconds.
So basically every 4 seconds this is going to check whether MyDB
service is available or not. And it will wait until
the service is available before letting the application start.
So let's actually save this.
And again, I'm going to delete the existing
deployment and
recreate it. And if I do Kubectl get pod.
Now you see that the old pods
are getting terminated and the new ones are getting started.
And let's check again. There you go.
And here we have a different status. Now we have zero
out of two containers ready. So these are actually
the main containers, not including the init container.
However here we see that init container hasn't completed
its job yet, right? So again the status
is that init container is being executed. Now we don't have
a MyDB service in the cluster, so this is going to basically keep
trying to access that service before the main
insidecar containers can start. However we
can also log the init containers just
like we do the regular ones. So I'm going to do get
kubectl logs. Again I will
get an error, but this time it says choose one of
Nginx or log sidecar or one of the
init containers. And this is my init container name,
so I can also specify this as an option.
And as you see here we have nslookup
output which tries to resolve the MyDB service,
but it cannot find one because we don't have it in the cluster. So to
fix that and basically let the init container
exit, let's actually create a service with
MyDB name. So cluster IP
is going to be my DB service, that's what
we called it. And we have one required attribute
which is port and let's have it at 80 80
and it is actually called tcp.
And now that we have the
service, MyDB service,
our init container should be
able to resolve that. So let's lock
the container and as you see
it was able to resolve it my DB
service to the IP address of the service.
And as a result you
see that the init container status is gone and both pods
have two containers running inside. So that's how you
can use init and sidecar containers in
your pod.
Data about the pod or Kubernetes environment
in your application. This could be a pod IP address or
pod namespace, a service account that the pod uses,
et cetera. For example in the sidecar logging application
you may want to add these values as metadata to each
application log. So how do you access information about pods
and cluster generally in the container running
inside the pod? Well actually the whole pod configuration
is available for all of its containers to access.
So if I do kubectl get pod with Yaml
output, that's the entire configuration
with all the data about the pod. And all of this is actually accessible
inside each container, including the generated
data like the status section. However in order to access
them we have to explicitly pass them. How can
we do that? We can define environment variables for the container
and pass the different pod configuration attributes
as the environment variable values.
Let's see an example again.
I'm going to bring up our NgInx deployment and
let's actually clean this up a little and remove the init
containers. We don't need them anymore. And let's say we want to
expose some of the values inside the log
sidecar container. To do that we're going to define
an attribute here called Env that stands for
environment variables. And this is a list of
environment variables that we can pass to
a container. And environment variables are basically just
key value pairs. And for each environment variable
we have the key, which is name the name of the
environment variable. Again this could be lowercase,
but as a standard you define the names of the environment variables
using all caps and underscore
separation. And you have the value of
that variable which can be a hard coded value
like my value. Or it could be a reference
to a data that actually contains that
value. And in that case we're going to define value
from and point to the reference.
Now in our case we want to reference different
data from the pod configuration. And let's start
with the name of the pod where this container is running.
Let's call it pod name. Now how do we reference
the pod configuration data in environment variable,
the syntax for that is field reference.
And under that we have field path.
So this basically points to the path to
the attribute that holds that value. In our case that's the pod
name which is in metadata section name.
And that's how we get values
defined in different sections of the pod configuration.
And you can also see this syntax in Kubernetes official
documentation about exposing pod information to containers
through environment variables, which is very descriptive.
And you have the examples right here.
And as I said, you can also get the values
of auto generated configuration like pod
service account.
Again, we have value from field
reference field path
in the specification with service
account name attribute. Let's also expose
the pod IP address and I'm simply going to copy this
status pod IP and all these
three values will be available inside the container. Now we can use
those environment variables in the application running
of the container as we wish, right in our case to just validate
that the values have been passed, let's just print them
out in the container. So after sync logs
we're going to do print env and
basically just print all of these,
all these values one by one to make sure they have been passed
correctly. Now if you have a large command that you want to pass
into a command, you can also as a multiline command,
we can also do that using arcs
attribute here. So instead of having all that defined
on one line, let's actually remove
that here. And we can define that in the arcs or
arguments as a multiline command. So let's
copy like
this.
And there you go. Now this can be a little bit easier to read
and maintain as well as adjust some values here
if you have a whole script that you're executing in a container.
So as you see, there are many different syntax variations with
the command and arguments and how you can define scripts
here, but you can always reference the documentation to see
whether you have a right syntax or not. So again,
let's save this and delete
the old deployment and
apply the changes. And let's check the logs
of our container.
And it's called lock sidecar. And you see
the values printed out here. So first we have sync app logs.
This is the pod name that we passed in as a
parameter. That's the service account name and the pod
IP address. And because we have a while loop, this gets printed
out multiple times. So again, as a use
case, if we had a log sidecar container that synchronized
the locks, it could append all this metadata information
to the application logs every time it collects them.
So that's how you can access any
pod configuration information inside the containers in
a cluster. However, after a couple of days of running
the application, the database pod died and
all the data inside got lost. And that's really bad because the
developers had created test data inside the database and now
the database is empty so they have to now recreate
the application state again. But generally if you had production
environment, you would not want to lose your database
data, right? So developers ask you to support them.
Configure data persistence in Kubernetes so that
even after the database pods or any other pods that have
data die, the data will still stay and
attach to the new pods. So to be able
to help developers configure persistent storage for
their applications in the cluster, we first have to understand how
data persistence actually works in Kubernetes and
what different components and resources we have available to
configure that show
you how you can persist data in Kubernetes using volumes.
We will cover three components of Kubernetes storage,
persistent volume, persistent volume claim and storage class,
and see what each component does and how it's created and
used for data persistence.
Consider a case where you have a MySQL database pod
which your application uses. Data gets added,
updated in the database. Maybe you create a new
database with a new user, et cetera. By default,
when you restart the pod, all those changes will be gone,
because Kubernetes doesn't give you data persistence out
of the box. That's something that you have to explicitly
configure for each application that needs saving data between
pod restarts. So basically you need
a storage that doesn't depend on the pod lifecycle,
so it will still be there when pod dies and new one gets
created. So the new pod can pick up where the previous
one left off, so it will read the existing data from
that storage to get up to date data.
However, you don't know on which node the new pod
restarts. So your storage must also be available on all
nodes, not just one specific one, so that when the
new pod tries to read the existing data, the up to date data
is there on any node in the cluster.
And also you need a highly available storage
that will survive even if the whole cluster crashed.
So these are the criteria or the requirements that
your storage, for example your database storage,
will need to have to be reliable. Another use case for
persistent storage which is not for database, is a directory.
Maybe you have an application that writes and reads files from
pre configured directory. This could be session files
for application or configuration files, et cetera.
And you can configure any of this type of storage
using Kubernetes component called persistent volume
think of a persistent volume as a cluster resource, just like
ram or cpu that is used to store data.
Persistent volume, just like any other component, gets created
using Kubernetes YaMl file where you can specify
the kind which is persistent volume. And in the specification
section you have to define different parameters like how
much storage should be created for the volume.
But since persistent volume is just an abstract component,
it must take the storage from the actual physical
storage, right? Like local hard drive from
the cluster nodes, or your external NFS servers
outside of the cluster. Or maybe cloud storage like AWS
block storage, or from Google Cloud storage, et cetera.
So the question is, where does this storage backend come
from? Local or remote or on cloud? Who configures
it? Who makes it available to the cluster? And that's
the tricky part of data persistence in Kubernetes.
Because Kubernetes doesn't care about your actual storage,
it gives you persistent volume component as an interface to
the actual storage that you as a maintainer or
administrator have to take care of. So you have to decide
what type of storage your cluster services or
applications would need and create and manage them
by yourself. Managing meaning do backups
and make sure they don't get corrupt, et cetera. So think
of storage in Kubernetes as an external
plugin to your cluster. Whether it's a local
storage on the actual nodes where the cluster is running or a
remote storage doesn't matter, they're all plugins to the cluster,
and you can have multiple storages configured for your cluster.
Where one application in your cluster uses local
disk storage, another one uses the NFS server,
and another one uses some cloud storage, or one
application may also use multiple of those
storage types. And by creating
persistent volumes you can use these actual physical
storages. So in the persistent volume specification section
you can define which storage backend
you want to use to create that storage abstraction
or storage resource for your applications. So this is an
example where we use NFS storage backend.
So basically we define how much storage we need some
additional parameters to that storage, like should it be read, write or read
only, et cetera, and the storage backend
with its parameters. And this is another
example where we use Google Cloud as a storage backend,
again with the storage backend specified here and capacity
and access modes here. Now obviously, depending on the storage type
on the storage backend, some of the attributes in the specification
will be different because they're specific to the storage
type. This is another example of a local storage which
is on the node itself, which has additional node affinity attributes.
In the official Kubernetes documentation, you can actually see the complete
list of more than 25 storage backends
that Kubernetes supports. Note here that persistent volumes
are not namespaced, meaning they're
accessible to the whole cluster. And unlike other
components that we saw, like pods and services,
they're not in any namespace. They're just available to
the whole cluster, to all the namespaces.
Now, it's important to differentiate here between two categories
of the volumes, local and remote. Each volume type
in these two categories has its own use case,
otherwise they won't exist, and we will see some of these use
cases later in this video. However, the local volume
types violate the second and third requirements of data
persistence for databases that I mentioned at
the beginning, which is one not being
tied to one specific node, but rather to
each node equally because you don't know where the
new pod will start and the second surviving
in cluster crash scenarios. Because of these reasons
for database persistence, you should almost always
use remote storage.
So who creates these persistent volumes and when?
As I said, persistent volumes are resources like CPU
or RAM, so they have to be already there in the
cluster when the pod that depends on it or that
uses it is created. So a side note here is
that there are two main roles in Kubernetes. There's an administrator
who sets up the cluster and maintains it and also
makes sure the cluster has enough resources. These are
usually system administrators or DevOps engineers in
a company, and the second role is Kubernetes
user that deploys the applications in the cluster,
either directly or through CI pipeline. These are developer
DevOps teams who create the applications and deploy
them. So in this case, the Kubernetes administrator
would be the one to configure the actual storage,
meaning to make sure that the NFS server
storage is there and configured, or maybe
create and configure a cloud storage that will be available for
the cluster. And second, create persistent
volume components from these storage backends
based on the information from developer team of what types of storage
their applications would need. And the developers then
will know that storage is there and can be used by their
applications. But for that, developers have to
explicitly configure the application YaML file to
use those persistent volume components. In other words,
application has to claim that volume storage,
and you do that using another component of Kubernetes called
persistent volume claim. Persistent volume
claims also pvcs are also created
with YAML configuration. Here's an example claim.
Again, don't worry about understanding each and every attribute that
is defined here. But on the higher level, the way it
works is that PVC claims a volume
with certain storage size or capacity, which is defined
in the persistent volume claim, and some additional characteristics
like access type. Should it be read only or read write,
or the type, et cetera. And whatever persistent
volume matches this criteria, or in other
words satisfies this claim, will be used for the
application. But that's not all. You have to now use that
claim in your pods configuration like this.
So in the pod specification here, you have the volumes
attribute that references the persistent
volume claim with its name. So now the
pod and all the containers inside the pod will have
access to that persistent volume storage.
So to go through those levels of abstraction step
by step, pods access storage by using
the claim as a volume, right? So they request the volume
through claim. The claim then will go and try to
find a volume persistent volume in the cluster that satisfies
the claim and the volume will have a storage,
the actual storage backend that it
will create that storage resource from.
And this way the pod will now be able to use that actual storage
backend. Note here that claims must
exist in the same namespace as the pod using the
claim. While as I mentioned before, persistent volumes
are not namespaced. So once the pod finds
the matching persistent volume through the volume claim,
through the persistent volume claim, the volume is then mounted
into the pod like this here. This is a
pod level, and then that volume can be mounted
into the container inside the pod, which is
this level right here. And if you have multiple containers here in
the pod, you can decide to mount this
volume in all the containers or just some of those.
So now the container and the application inside the
container can read and write to that storage, and when the pod
dies, a new one gets created. It will have access
to the same storage and see all the changes the previous pod or
the previous containers made. Again, the attributes here like
volumes and volume, miles, et cetera, and how they're used. I will show you
more specifically and explain in a later demo
video. Now you may be wondering why so many
abstractions for using volume where admin
role has to create persistent volume and user role creates a
claim on that persistent volume and that isn't used in pod.
Can I just use one component and configure everything there?
Well, this actually has a benefit because as a user,
meaning a developer who just wants to deploy their application in the cluster,
you don't care about where the actual storage is.
You know you want your database to have persistence,
and whether the data will leave on a cluster,
FS or AWS, EBS or local
storage doesn't matter for you as long as the data is safely
stored. Or if you need a directory storage for files.
You don't care where the directory actually leaves as long as it has enough
space and works properly. And you sure don't
want to care about setting up these actual storages
yourself. You just want 50 gigabyte storage
for your elastic or ten gigabyte for your application. That's it.
So you make a claim for storage using PVC and assume that
cluster has storage resources already
there. And this makes deploying the applications
easier for developers because they don't have to take care of the
stuff beyond deploying the applications.
Now there are two volume types that I think needs to be mentioned separately
because they're a bit different from the rest and these are config,
map and secret. Both of them are local volumes,
but unlike the rest, these two aren't created via PV
and PVC, but are rather own components and managed by
Kubernetes itself. Consider a case where you need a configuration
file for your Prometheus pod, or maybe a message broker
service like mosquito or consider when you need a certificate
file mounted inside your application.
In both cases you need a file available
to your pod. So how this works is that you create config
map or secret component and you can mount that into your
pod and into your container the same way as you would mount
persistent volume claim. So instead you would have a
config map or secret here. So to quickly summarize what we've
covered so far, as you see, at its core, a volume is
just a directory, possibly with some data in it which
is accessible to the containers in a pod, how that
directory is made available, or what storage medium actually
backs that, and the contents of that directory are
defined by a specific volume type you use.
So to use a volume, a pod specifies what volumes to
provide for the pod in the specification volumes
attribute and inside the pod. Then you can decide where to
mount that storage into using volume mounts
attribute inside the container section and
this is a path inside the container where
application can access whatever storage we mounted
into the container. And as I said, if you have
multiple containers, you can decide which containers should
get access to that storage. Interesting note
for you is that a pod can actually use multiple volumes
of different types simultaneously. Let's say you have an elasticsearch
application or pod running in your cluster that
needs a configuration file mounted through config
map, needs a certificate, let's say client certificate
mounted as a secret and it needs database storage,
let's say which is backed with AWS
elastic block storage. So in this case you can configure
all three inside your pod or deployment.
So this is the pod specification that we saw before.
And here on the volumes level you will just list all
the volumes that you want to mount into your pod.
So let's say you have a persistent volume claim that in the background
claims persistent volume from AWS block storage.
And here you have the config map, and here you have a secret.
And here in the volume mounts you can list all those
storage mounts using the names, right? So you
have the persistent storage, then you have the config
map and the secret and each one of them is mounted to a
certain path inside the container.
Now we saw that to persist data in kubernetes,
admins need to configure storage for the cluster, create persistent
volumes, and developers then can claim them using pvcs.
But consider a cluster with hundreds of applications
where things get deployed daily and storage is needed for these applications.
So developers need to ask admins to create persistent
volumes they need for applications before deploying them.
And admins then may have to manually request storage from cloud
or storage provider and create hundreds of
persistent volumes for all the applications that
need storage manually, and that can be
tedious, time consuming, and can get messy
very quickly. So to make this process more efficient,
there is a third component of Kubernetes persistence
called storage class. Storage class basically
creates or provisions persistent volumes dynamically
whenever PVC claims it. And this way
creating or provisioning volumes in a cluster may be automated.
Storage class also gets created using YAML
configuration file. So this is an example file where we have the
kind storage class. Storage class
creates persistent volumes dynamically in the background.
So remember we define storage backend in the persistent
volume component. Now we have to define it in the storage class
component. And we do that using the provisioner attribute which
is the main part of the storage class configuration because it
tells kubernetes which provisioner to be used for a
specific storage platform or cloud provider
to create the persistent volume component out of
it. So each storage backend has its own provisioner
that Kubernetes offers internally which are prefixed
with Kubernetes IO like this one here.
And these are internal provisioners. And for others
or other storage types they are external provisioners
that you have to then explicitly go and find and
use that in your storage class. And in
addition to provisioner attribute, we configure parameters of
the storage we want to request for our persistent volume, like this
one here. So storage class is basically another abstraction
level that abstracts the underlying storage provider
as well as parameters for that storage or characteristics
for that storage like what disk type or
etc. So how does it work or how do we use storage
class in the pod configuration? Same as persistent
volume, it is requested or claimed by PVC.
So in the PVC configuration here we add
additional attribute that is called storage class
name that references the storage
class to be used to create a persistent volume
that satisfies the claims of
this PVC. So now when a pod claims
storage through PVC, the PVC will request that
storage from storage class, which then will provision
or create persistent volume that meets the
needs of that claim using provisioner from the actual
storage backend. Now this should help you understand the concepts
of how data is persisted in Kubernetes.
As a high level overview,
figure different types of volumes for applications
in Kubernetes and the types of volumes actually depend on
where the data ends up persisted. So for example,
if you use cloud storage for your volumes or some remote
storage, then you'll be working with remote storage volumes,
and remote volumes are actually the ones that you
should be mostly using for databases and
any important application data,
especially in a production environment. However, it may be
a little bit tricky and difficult to configure.
So for test purposes, or if you have data that is not
so important to keep, you can actually use
local volume. So data will still be persisted, but not on
a remote storage where it can be backed up and replicated,
but rather on the cluster nodes itself,
and that's why they're called local volumes.