And now he can execute Kubectl commands without specifying
any options just like this. So this
is one way of configuring the Kubeconfig file for
new users in the Kubernetes cluster. And probably
the more optimized and easier way for the team members
to use it is if you as a Kubernetes administrator also
put these certificate and key file contents inside
the kubeconfig. So let's see how to do that as well.
As I said, right now we're just pointing to
those two files as locations, so we need
them to be available on the machine as well.
Or we can just paste them directly inside here.
So we just have one file to move around and give developers and team members
instead of three files. So to do
that, first we're going to change these to data and
let's remove those two and
get the base 64 encoded values of
both files, which is actually not very difficult to do.
We simply do base 64, we pass in the file.
Let's do the certificate file first.
And again, let's trim all those new lines
so we can paste the output into the file.
And there you go, I'm going to copy this and
this is going to be the value right here.
So that's our certificate data.
Let's now base 64 encode the
key itself. Let's copy and
paste it right here, save it and there you go.
Now we just have one Kubeconfig file which
includes both certificate and the key of the client.
And let's try again, make sure it works. There you go.
As a Kubernetes administrator you just have to distribute
and give any Kubernetes users in your team
this Kubeconfig file. So that's probably the most optimized and
effective way of sharing those credentials.
Awesome. So we have a user in the cluster,
we have its certificate signed by Kubernetes
CA, and we have a kubeconfig file with all the data
inside that we can share with the team members to use when
connecting to the cluster. But as we saw,
the new user doesn't have any permissions so they can authenticate
with the cluster but they're not authorized to do anything.
So that's going to be our next step where we give this user some permissions.
As you already learned, the way we give permissions to users is
using cluster roles or roles. In this
case we want to give user Tom permission to
create, update and delete common resources
like pods, deployments, services,
etc. In all the namespaces so to give
Tom this permission, we're going to create a cluster role with
all the permissions specified. And after that we're going
to create a cluster role binding to bind that cluster
role to Tom's user.
Now how do we create a cluster role? We're going to use the
Kubectl imperative command for that.
Because using Kubectl create command,
we can actually create roles,
role bindings, cluster roles and cluster bindings.
To make our work easier, we're going to generate a cluster role
configuration file using Kubectl create cluster
role command cluster role let's
get help again. Let's give us some space.
Let's call it dev cluster role. And as you
see, we have a couple of required attributes here
which we have to set. One of them is
verb, which basically means what
actions do we allow with this cluster role? And verb option
is a list. So we can specify different options. Let's do
get, list,
create, update and delete.
Then we have the resource where we specify
again a list of resources where we have the resource
name and the API group that this resource belongs
to. For default API group which is core,
we don't have to specify the group, but for other resources we
have to specify that. So for example, I'm going to specify deployment
here which is not from a core API
group, but rather from API group called EPS.
And then let's specify pods which is in core
API group. But as I said, for core we don't have to
specify the group name and this actually should be
plural. So let's actually go ahead and
use this configuration. Do not forget the dry
run option because we're not executing
this directly, just getting a preview in YamL format.
And let's save this into dev cluster
role Yaml file and let's
open it. And that's basically our generated
YamL file. Now this makes working with Kubernetes
configuration files easier because we have the main structure created
and some of the configuration already set.
Plus we have now a visual way to see and reconfigure
some of the stuff. First of all, you see that we have
name Devcr and a list of rules.
And because we are using two different API groups,
one of them which is core or empty,
the default one and one of them apps, we have two
API group sections here. So for each API group
we have a separate section. Second, we see that for each API
group we have a list of resources, in this case pods
from the core group, and a list of actions
that we can perform on these resources. And the
same structure here. Now we can go ahead and
adjust our configuration. Let's say we want to give
any user with this cluster role access
to pods, deployments,
services and stateful sets. So let's list
all those resources first. Now you may be asking,
how do I know which API group each of these resources
actually belong to? Well, you can't know this by heart, so you
will have to look it up in the documentation. So let's see which API
groups, services and stateful sets actually belong to.
So going to Kubernetes documentation, you have the Kubernetes
API reference. So this is one way
where you can easily find which resources belong to which API groups.
So you can use this as a reference for creating your
cluster role or role configurations.
So first of all, pod is in a core group, which we already
have defined. Deployment is in apps API group.
Now let's check service and stateful set. So stateful
set is in apps. So let's set
that one. In API groups apps we
have another one, stateful sets.
Also note that resources are always referenced in plural.
And now let's find service which is
in core API group. So we're going to list it
right here under the pods like
this. And for example, if we wanted to
give user permission to create ingress components,
you see that ingress component will be in an
API group called Networking Kubernetes IO.
So you would have another API group section right
here with the name of networking
Kubernetes IO in addition to the apps and the
core. So that's how it works. And finally,
let's configure the verbs. So what
do we allow on these resources? And here you
see that I have basically allowed almost any of the actions,
and in order to avoid just typing out all of them one
by one, if you want to allow any action on the resources,
you could also just use a star.
Again, this is an array, so you
could say all the actions or all the verbs are
allowed for the resources defined here. This way
you don't have to type out all the verbs. And again,
you may be wondering where can you actually check the
list of all the verbs for the resources. You can also see
that in a documentation. For example, here in the
Arbec authorization documentation you have a bunch
of examples. And this for example is a list of
all the available verbs. So you can check the
list here and use it in your configuration file. And let's
say we allow everything on pods and services, but we only allow
to get list and create deployments and stateful
sets. We do not allow updating or deleting those
resources. Let's just say that's the permission we have decided on and that's
our cluster role configuration and we can use it for
all the developers in the team. Again, if we want to add new permissions,
we can update the cluster role itself later after we
create it and basically add more permissions like
creating persistent volumes or ingress
components, et cetera. So that's how we define cluster roles.
Let's save it and
let's apply Kubectl apply.
There you go. And of course we cannot apply
these because we're using Tom users kubeconfig file.
So let's actually change that
by specifying kubeconfig file to be their
admin users config. And there you go again,
let's do get
cluster role and we have a bunch of them
which have been generated by different services,
but one of them is Devcr that
we just created. So it's there and we can also
describe it,
describe cluster role Devcr.
And here we see a human readable form
of cluster role which says which resources
from which API groups, which shows what
actions you can take on which resources
from which API groups.
Now let's create a cluster role binding to actually connect
or assign this cluster role to Tom's
user, again using create command
cluster role binding. This is going to be an easier one.
You see that we have to specify cluster role itself and
one of those three either user
which is what we have for Tom, a group or
service account. So cluster role binding,
let's call it dev cluster role binding.
Cluster role is what we
created, which is cluster role which already exists in
the cluster. And then we have user which is Tom.
And you can also check that in the error messages here
where kubernetes says user Tom cannot
get resources. So that's the name of the user. And again
do dry run equals client yaml
format output and save
this into cluster role binding yaml
file.
And let's check the configuration file here.
It is super straightforward actually we have
the name here and we have two main parts
here. So basically we're binding an existing
role to an existing user.
And for cluster role and user we're just providing
the names. That's basically the whole configuration, which is
very straightforward. We can save this
and apply and
let's not forget to execute this as admin.
And there you go, let's describe cluster
role binding devcrb
with the admin user. And there you go,
user Tom bound to cluster
role dev CR.
Now let's validate that our binding
and our cluster role actually works.
Before when we did kubectl get pod,
we were not allowed to execute this as a Tom user.
Now let's see what happens. And there you go. So get
pod works, get service should work too.
Now let's try get node.
We haven't given permission for node resource, so this
should not be allowed. As you see it is forbidden for
user Tom. So that's obviously one way
to validate that your permissions are set correctly.
Or you can also validate the permissions
for different users, not only your current user using
Kubectl Auth command. So if
you were an admin user kubeconfigconfig
admin users kubeconfig file and you wanted to
validate whether developer Tom now has correct
permissions, you can use Kubectl auth subcommand
to do that. And you can say Kubectl
Auth can I create pod
as user Tom?
And you get yes, now you can check can
I create service as
User Tom? Can I get
node? You get no as a response because we didn't
give this permission and also we didn't
give permission to delete deployments.
Let's check that. There you go. So this is a very efficient
way to check permissions of other users
in your cluster with admin users kubeconfig file.
Awesome. So we see that everything works. Now we authorized
user Tom to do a bunch of stuff in the cluster,
in all namespaces so that they can get started
and deploy their applications inside. Always know that whatever
you didn't explicitly specify in a cluster role is
not permitted. So for example, this user will not be able to create
new namespaces, for example because we didn't specify that in the cluster
role. And again, if you wanted to give permission for namespace
in the cluster role, you would find namespace resource
here and its API group and
edit to the permissions for the developers if you want to
human users covered, and we know how to give them access to the
cluster. Now what about application users or
non human users? For example, in a real project,
ideally you would set a CI CD pipeline that
deploys directly into Kubernetes cluster, which means
your CI CD tool like jenkins for example,
needs to have its own user and own access to
the cluster to deploy applications and make changes that
it needs to make. And as you learned for non human users,
we create service accounts in kubernetes. So in this
part we're going to create a service account for a CI CD tool.
This could be in our case jenkins, but this could be used for
any application you want. And then we're going to assign permission
to that service account. And this is all going to be actually
very easy because you already know all the necessary concepts for
this. So first,
let's create service count using our Kubectl create
service account commit. Again,
let's see the options we have. Service account, let's call it
Jenkins. We don't have any required attributes here. As you
see you can actually execute this directly right away
because we don't need to add any configuration or adjust
any configuration here. But again, as a best practice,
you should keep the configuration files of all the
components that you created in the cluster for a history of changes.
So I'm going to do dry run client
Yaml and save this into a
configuration file. Let's actually check that configuration
file. It's actually super simple. We just have
service account and its name. And for
that let's actually switch back to our admin user
because right now the Kubeconfig file
actually holds the kubeconfig of Tom
user. So let's reset this back to admin
and let's see that it works. There you go.
And let's apply the
service account configuration. And now if I do
describe service account and
Jenkins, you see that the service account was
created and automatically assigned
a token. So whenever you create a service account in Kubernetes,
a token gets automatically generated for that service account,
which is basically like a user password or user
token to access the cluster.
And this token, since it's a credential, is actually created as a
Kubernetes secret. So if I do
Kubectl get secret with
a name, as you see that this is actually
the name of the secret that holds the
token and the type of that secret is service account token.
So it has a own dedicated type for service
account tokens. And again, as I said, this is the name of
the secret containing the token. It's not the token itself.
And in order to extract the token we're simply going to
print the whole secret contents as YAmL file.
And right here, this is our token. Also note that service
account token contains the CA certificate data as
well, in addition to the token credential.
So now again, the question is how do we access
the cluster using a service account? So basically,
how do we execute Kubectl commands from Jenkins
using Jenkins own service account?
For that I'm going to copy a token. Remember this is
base 64 encoded so we need to decode it first.
So let's do base 64
decode. And that's a decoded token. It may
look the same, but this is actually a different string here.
And what we can do is actually save this
token into a variable here in Linux
so we can reference it later. So let's do token
equals and we grab the decoded value
of course. And now we can access
the token like this and again using
Kubectl options so we have this token that we
can use instead of client certificate so the command will look
like this.
So let's remove the config
file temporarily. We already have this in the current location
so we can safely remove it because
we have it here already. And let's execute the
Kubectl command again. And there you go again. We were
able to access the cluster, but Jenkins
service account is not allowed to do anything because we haven't
given it any permission yet. So we get forbidden response
from the cluster for user. And this is actually the
name of the user with service account which is system service
account, the namespace in which we
are executing the command and the name of the service account.
So you could actually execute Kubectl commands like this from
Jenkins for example. However, again, because these
are a lot of options on the command, you may actually want to
spare yourself setting all these options on Kubectl
command. So the question is, can we create a kubeconfig
file for a service account just like we
did for human users? Well, the answer is yes,
we can have a kubeconfig file for service account
users. So let's see how that's going to work. Let's actually duplicate
our existing dev Tom confile
into Jenkins confile
and let's open again.
We have certificate authority, data API server.
Let's change the user in
all the relevant places like
this of course the name and
the users list.
And we're going to get rid of client key and client certificate.
So the only change we need to make here is actually to
specify a token instead
of client key and client certificate. And the token is
again the decoded token for service account.
So let's leave a placeholder here and
let's get our token that I saved in the variable
and set it as a value right here.
So now you have a kubeconfig file for the
service account for Jenkins. And this means you could just
take this file and copy it onto a Jenkins server and use
it when you execute Kubectl commands.
So Kubeconfig is
going to be the Jenkins config file and let's do get pod
for example. And again we have accessed the cluster
and we get forbidden because we're not authorized to get the pods.
So that's how you can use service account for your
applications like CI CD tools such as
Jenkins or any other application that would
need access to the cluster.
However, we still need to give the service account permission
to do something in the cluster. And let's say in Jenkins case
we don't want to give Jenkins access to the whole
cluster, to all the namespaces, but only to a
specific namespace. And as a security best practice, we should always try
to give only the necessary permissions to users
and applications accessing the cluster because otherwise we're just
going to be increasing the security risk by giving too many
permissions. And as you learned, in order to give a user permission
to a specific namespace instead of the whole cluster,
we have roles instead of cluster roles. So we're
going to create a role for default namespace. So Jenkins
will only be able to access resources in
the default namespace. And again we're going to create
the role using the create command.
And let's call these CI CD role.
And again we have some required attributes here
which are same as you learned for cluster role.
So we have the verb let's do create and list, we'll add
the rest later and in
the configuration file and then we have the resource and group name.
And let's say Jenkins is not allowed to interact
with the pods directly, but only create
maybe updates and list deployment
components which are as we learned part of
the API group called Apps and services
which are part of the core group. And we're
going to do dry run and
save this into CI CD role
YaML file and
we're going to error because we need our admin
users kubeconfig file. So let's actually copy
that back to the default
location so we don't have to specify it all the time.
And let's rerun the command. There you go. So CI
CD roll YamL file and
let's check the configuration here. So we are
allowing Jenkins to create updates and
least services and we are allowing it to create update and
least deployments. And since deployments and services are
from two different API groups, we have two different
rule sections here. And finally, as we know, role is
bound to a namespace. So these
rules actually apply for one specific namespace.
And since we haven't specified a namespace, here it is a
default one. So it means if you wanted to give Jenkins
access to namespace, MyApp for
example, you would have to specify it right here.
In our case that's the default,
which is the default namespace. So we don't have to
explicitly specify it here. So that's
the role that we can apply right away.
And let's describe our
role. Note that when checking the cluster roles,
you don't have to specify a namespace. But for example,
if we had a role in MyApp namespace,
then you would have to actually specify the namespace in
the Kubectl command. Again, we're working with the default
namespace, so we don't have to do that. And we have services deployments
in apps API group with these actions.
Let's now bind the role
to Jenkins service account, which is super
easy. We do kubectl create role
binding and
again CI CD binding and we have
our role which is CICD role
and one of these three options,
user group or service account, in our case
the service account. And as you see here with the service account you
also have to specify the name only service account name will
not be enough. So we have to do default and
name of the service account, which is Jenkins.
And again we could execute this right away. We don't have to change
any configuration here. But again, to be consistent
I'm going to save this into a configuration file and
then apply that CI CD binding
YAML and let's check it.
So again, super simple CI CD role which
is in the default namespace. That's why we don't
have a namespace attribute defined here,
is bound to Jenkins service account
in default namespace. And we
leave everything this and apply the
role binding.
Let's describe that's
like this, this and there you go. And now as
an admin user,
because I'm using the Kubeconfig of admin user,
we can actually validate that the permissions have been applied
by doing check with Kubectl
Auth subcommand. So Kubectl Auth can I
create service?
And as you learned, the username of service account is not
just the service account name, but it is system service
account, the namespace where
the service account is and then finally the name of the
service account. And we want to check whether the
Jenkins service account can create services in
namespace default. And we should get yes,
now let's try another namespace like Kube system
for example, and we should get no. And in the default namespace
we can also try create
deployment again, we get yes
and let's try get pod
which we did not give permission for. So we get no.
And that's how you can check service account permissions
using your Kubernetes administrator user.
And as a last step, as a Kubernetes administrator
you would take this Jenkins configuration file that holds
everything necessary to connect to the cluster, which is basically the
CA certificate of Kubernetes and the token
of the service account and hand it over to developers
who can then copy it to Jenkins server or whoever's responsible
for that. And using this config file they
can execute Kubectl commands from Jenkins.
Of course, for those actions, only that
service account with this token is permitted to do
the cluster, so they start deploying their applications
to it. But as they are still learning and figuring out stuff,
they would like to know how to troubleshoot things when pod
is not running or service is not accessible, et cetera.
So they ask you if you can give them any useful
tips on debugging in kubernetes. One use case
where you need to debug different components in the cluster
is when application running in the cluster is not accessible
for the end users. So what's the issue here? Is pod
not running? Is service not properly configured?
Is it not forwarding a request to the pod? Or is
service simply not accessible? Maybe you have a networking
issue in the cluster, so there could be many places where issues
may happen. So you check stuff step by step until you find
the problem and you need to know how to debug efficiently in
different ways. So in this part you will learn how to
troubleshoot different issues in Kubernetes and in that context
you will also learn a couple of interesting and useful
concepts like command and args attributes in Kubernetes manifest
files as well as how to format Kubectl
output and use it efficiently to cherry pick
the information you need about your Kubernetes resources.
Shooting the application we start by checking that the application
pods are running using Kubectl get pod commit.
Then we check that the pods are registered with
their respective service and that service is forwarding
the request to them. For that we can either do Kubectl get
ep or endpoint which will list the services and their endpoint
pods. Or you can also do kubectl describe service
with the service name that will give you all the details about
the service, including all the registered pods.
We can also check that the service is accessible by hitting its
endpoint. We can check it using a Netcat tool with
a combination of service IP address and
the service port. Or we can just ping the service name
and we can do both of these from one of the pods in
the cluster. If this is all working so the
service is accessible and it's forwarding the requests
to its endpoint pods, it means the requests
are reaching the pods. So now we can check the application logs
for any information or any errors with Kubectl
logs command sometimes it could be that the
container inside the pod is having some issues.
For example, it is crashing and it's failing
to start. In that case, you won't get the
container locks because there is no container running inside.
But we still want to see the status of the pod to understand
why the container is failing to start. We can get that information
using Kubectl describe pod command, which will
show us the events of the pod,
like fetching the container image, scheduling the pod,
et cetera. So one of the events can give us information about why
the container is not starting. So this would be a simple
path of troubleshooting an application in Kubernetes.
Now let's see some more advanced and more specific use cases.
One way to debug issues with applications and networking
issues in the cluster is using temporary pods
to execute commands from. Because as you learned,
pod network is different from the cluster node network.
All pods are in its private virtual network.
So executing troubleshooting commands from within a pod
may be needed in some cases instead of executing them
from the node. For that, there are some common
images that have tools needed for debugging
preinstalled. One such example is a busybox
image. This image actually includes tools like
if config, nslookup, Netstnet,
Ping, et cetera. You can also check all the commands
that busybox image has available in this list
here. Busybox does not however have curl
available, so for that you could use the official
curl image, for example. So let's create a
pod with busybox image. And because this is going
to be a temporary test pod, we're going to create it using
an imperative Kubectl run command. So kubectl
run name of the pod and let's call it debug
pod. And of course the image which is busybox.
So let's run this,
and if I do kubectl get pod, you will see that
debug pod was created. However it is not in
a running state. It says status completed
and we have zero containers out of one
actively running. Let's check again. As you
see, it actually got restarted,
but complete again. And that means the pod is there,
but there is no container or process running
inside. So we can't actually enter the pod.
We can't do kubectl exec and
attach a terminal because it will say container
not found. So what is this completed status?
And why did the debug pod
or busybox based pod just exit
after starting up while all those other pods
didn't have the same problem? So what's happening here?
Containers in general are meant to execute a specific task,
like run a MySQL database, or start
a web application or synchronize data, et cetera.
Once the task is completed, the container will
exit because it has completed its job and it's
done. In other words, the container only leaves as long as
the process inside leaves. So if the web application or
MySQL database process inside the container crashes,
the container will exit and you will have to restart
it. Now where is it defined, what task a
container will execute or what process it will
start? This is actually defined in the docker file of
the image. If we look at the docker file of the
Nginx image and for each image you can actually
see the docker file. If you go to tags,
these are basically all the built images or image
tags for that image and
just click in one of them. For each image
that was built, you will see a docker file that was used to build the
image. So you have this available for each image.
So in the Nginx image docker file,
you will see that there is a CMD or command instruction
that executes the Nginx command when
the container is created. Same way if I check a postgresql
image tag and one of the tags and its docker file, you see
that the same CMD instruction is
specified with postgres command. So CMD
in the docker file defines what program or process
will run in the container when it's created.
Now, compared to that, if we look at the busybox
image and its dockerfile, let's go to one of the
tags like
this one here.
You see that it simply runs an sh
or shell command. Shell command, however, is not a process
or a program like Postgresql or Nginx.
It is a shell that listens for inputs
from a terminal, and if it doesn't find a terminal to attach
to to get input from, it simply exits
and gets in a completed state because it doesn't have
any task to do. So how do we keep our
busybox pod alive? Can we add something
to this command or how does it actually work?
Well, we have two options here. The first one,
and a pretty easy one, is to attach
a terminal to the busybox image right away
when it gets created. So instead of just running
the pod like this and let's call it debug pod
two, we're going to attach it an interactive
terminal right away. And this will actually
create the pod from busybox and it will
automatically give us its terminal like
this. So now we are inside the busybox pods terminal
and we can execute commands from here. And if I exit and
do kubectl get pod, you see that the
debug pod two is actually in a running state and
we can exec into it just
like we do in other pods and
again get its terminal and execute any commands here.
So let's say we want to now debug the service
connectivity. As I said, we have bunch of utilities
already installed here. So we could do nslookup for the
service, or you can ping
the service in your cluster to see if it's accessible and so
on. That is one way of creating a PZ box pod
in a way that it doesn't exit right away when it starts.
So let's clean our cluster up by deleting
those two pods.
Now that's one easy option to fix
this using an imperative Kubectl run command.
But what if we wanted to create a configuration for
a busybox pod or maybe another pod that
also has a task that simply exits and we want
to keep it running? So how do we define or how do we create
a busybox or some other image pod
using kubernetes configuration file? Or in other words,
can we overwrite a command defined in
the docker file without having to modify the actual docker
file? You can overwrite that actually. So let's see how that works.
When we start the containers using Docker run commands,
we can override the CMD instruction by
just passing in an alternative command as a
parameter. So we can override the sh command
in busybox image. But what if we don't want to override
the command itself, but rather want to pass it a
parameter or append more commands to it, like execute
the shell program in busybox but pass in
Myscript sh file? Well, you can't
do that with CMD instruction, but for that there is another instruction
called entry point that allows you to append
parameters or additional commands on top of the entry
point commands. So CMD is an instruction that is best
to use if you need a default command that users
can easily override, while entry point is preferred.
When you want to define a specific executable that should
always run, and you allow users to just
append other commands or parameters in addition to it.
And there are even some cases where we have both
CMD and entry point instructions, and we
have a lot of examples for that. Again, taking our postgres image,
we have entry point which is a shell
script as well as a CMD command as well as
Redis, for example, that has a shell script as an entry
point and ready server command. In that case,
entry point defines the process that starts in container
and CMD defines parameters for that process.
Now how does this all work in Kubernetes pod definition?
Well, in a container definition of a pod, we can overwrite
both of these instructions using different attributes.
We can replace the entry point instruction defined in Dockerfile
with attribute called command in a pod
definition, and the CMD instruction with attribute called
arcs. Now this may be a little confusing because
CMD or command instruction in Dockerfile does not
map to command in pod. However,
as I said, when both of them are defined, the entry point
is the actual command and the CMD is the arguments
to that command. So when you think about this way,
then command and arcs attribute names in the pod definition actually
make sense. And you can also find that in Kubernetes
documentation we have different combinations of
using command and arcs, or just
one of the attributes in your pod definition and how the docker
field map to Kubernetes field names. So let's
see how this will work in the busybox image example.
So I'm going to create a simple pod.
Let's call this busybox pod definition
with a busybox image. So that's the basic Kubernetes
configuration file. And again, as we saw,
without having any parameters or defining
any parameters, busybox pod will run,
it will execute the shell command and it will exit
because it doesn't have any input from the terminal.
So let's actually pass it some argument
which is going to be a shell command to execute.
And as you learned, we can pass the arguments to the
defined command in an image, in a docker image using arcs
attribute. And arcs attribute is an array,
and in that array we can define the list of
arguments like this. So in
our case we're passing an actual Linux
command to the shell executable which busybox
image runs. So let's just do a simple echo
doing some debugging
and save. So note that I haven't
defined a command attribute. Here I'm only specifying
arguments for the already defined command.
So arcs attribute will actually override the CMD
instruction and it will execute echo doing some
debugging. As an alternative, we can also define
only the command which is also an array
like this. And let's define
print env that basically prints out all
the environment variables. Or we can define
command with arguments, basically specify which
environment variables they should print out. And let's do hostname
and Kubernetes port.
So instead of doing just print n, it will print
out those two environment variables. And since this is actually
overriding the main command inside the image,
we can also specify shell executable with
arguments like this. And this can be any
shell program that we want. For example an
expression like this which basically echoes something
every 5 seconds. In our case,
let's say we want a busy box to get created and
then run in the cluster in the shell process to basically
be alive and active in the container for an hour
or 2 hours so that we can use it to debug the cluster
and then we can get rid of it. And for that we can actually define
a simple sleep command here like this
for example, and the busybox container
will be alive for 1000 seconds. Now as you
see, command attribute is also an array and we
could define the arguments as well as the
main command all inside the command attribute. So I'm
going to copy this, paste it here and we
can get rid of the arguments. And if I execute
and do kubectl get pod, you see that busybox
pod is running and we can actually enter the pod
like this and execute
comments there if we want to. And the container inside will be alive
for thousand seconds after that container will exit and
the pod will have completed status and zero
out of one containers in a ready state. So that's
how you can overwrite commands and arguments
of the commands inside the images using
Kubernetes configuration itself, which is very powerful
because you don't have to actually adjust anything in the image.
You can either use the defaults that image has inside
already, or you can flexibly overwrite them in your pod
configuration. So this gives you a lot of flexibility to work with
images in Kubernetes.
Now you have already learned how to execute commands from inside the pod
using kubectl exec command with interactive
terminal and passing shell sh or bash
command. The shell or bash command
at the end will start the shell program in the pod
so you can execute commands on it. But let's say you want to do a
simple ping inside the pod. For that you
don't want to enter a pod and then exit. Can we just execute
a command in the pod environment without attaching
an interactive terminal to it? Yes, we can do that as
well by passing the command we want to execute in the pod
to this shell executable directly. So basically,
instead of getting the bash or shell terminal
and running commands on it, we just pass the command directly to the
program and say hey, here is the command to execute inside
the pod. Now I want to note something about
the sh or bash executables
here, because you may be thinking, if I can do both,
which one should I be specifying here when executing commands
in the pod? Well, some images don't have bash,
they only have the classic shell, which is like a slimmed down
version of bash. So if Kubectl exec
command with Bash executable gives you an
error like this which says executable file bash not
found, it means that the image does not have Bash
executable inside. And in that case you have to fall
back to shell like this. So basically by
default you try to use Bash, and if it's not available in
the image, you fall back to the shell program. Now back to our
topic of executing commands without attaching a terminal
to the container in the pod. As I said, we can just pass
the command to the shell program, and we can do that
using an option minus c,
and the executable will be print n,
for example. Let's execute that. As you see, the command
got executed and we actually got the output here,
but we are still on the node. We didn't attach our
terminal to the container. You can also execute
whole expressions here, right? You can do, while true do
echo, hello, then sleep for
maybe 2 seconds and done, and let's
execute. And as you see, the expression is
actually now executing inside the container.
Let's stop the process. And of course you can use
this for more meaningful and useful commands,
like doing pings to the services,
for example, that you want to check whether they're
accessible, getting netstead
output from the container like
this, and so on. Now this may seem like a little improvement,
but this can save you some time and let you work a little more efficiently.
Of course, in addition to debugging from the pod,
you also want to debug the cluster components directly using
Kubectl, right? And Kubectl is a very powerful
tool, but when you have hundreds of services,
pods, deployments, config maps, and a bunch of other components,
it may be difficult to extract the information about the cluster
components in a digestible way. So basically in
a way that doesn't require you to scroll through endless
lines of output about different components.
For example, if you wanted to print out the node
IP addresses of the pods or service accounts that
pods are using, or maybe a creation time image
names, container names of the pod, you can't print all of
these for all the pods in your cluster directly
using Kubectl command. You will actually have to do Kubectl
describe for each pod separately to
see all this information. But there is a way to do this using
a JSON path output format of Kubectl.
Till now you have learned that if we do Kubectl get pod,
simply do Kubectl get pod. For example, you will get a
nice table view of the pod's most important data,
like the name, status, et cetera. You also learned
that with an output format of wide,
you get a little bit more data about the pod's
IP address, the node name, where it's scheduled on,
and so on. And finally, you also learned that we have
a YAmL output format for the pods that
basically gives you pod configuration in a Kubernetes native
way in YAML format. As an alternative,
we also have an output format in JSON.
So if we do Kubectlgetpod with outputs JSON,
you will see the same details as we saw with YAMl configuration,
but in a JSON format. And of course you can
do that on all the components like nodes,
services, et cetera.
But just like with YAML, this is actually a lot of
data to scroll through, especially if we have
hundred pods, this will be JSON data for hundred
pods. So how can we filter through all of
these? How can we basically pinpoint and say,
only give me the operating system image of
every pod running in the cluster, or how do you say
only show me the memory capacity of each pod
in this namespace. So basically, how do we extract only
specific attributes that we're interested in instead of having these
huge yaml objects for
each pod? And for that we can use something called JSON
Path, which basically is a query language for JSON.
And Kubectl happens to have support for
JSON path queries. So with JSON path expressions,
we can query any relevant specific data from
this whole huge output for each pod.
So let's see how that works. So first
of all, the output format here is
instead of JSON, it's going to be JSON path.
And the way we specify expressions of
JSON path is in quotes
and curly braces. Now, JSON path expressions
are not super easy and intuitive. They can actually
get pretty complex, so it may take some time to
get used to it, but you can do some very useful querying
with that. So let's start with the simplest example where we
just print out the names of all the pods
in the default namespace. And the way we put together the JSON path
expression is basically just finding the attribute names
and working our way all through this hierarchy.
So right here at the beginning of this huge JSON object that
contains the list of all the pods, we have these attributes.