IP address gets assigned to each node. Now,
on each of these nodes, we need to schedule pods,
but we said that pods are own isolated machines
in its own private network. So on each node, a private
network is created by the network plugin with a
different IP address range, which,
very important to note here, should not overlap
with the IP address range of the nodes.
Otherwise, the pod communication in your cluster will not work.
And this private network has a private switch or a bridge
on the host, which will let all the pods within that
network talk to each other, just like nodes
which are in the same VPC or same network can talk
to each other directly. So that's how the pods on the same node
can talk to each other directly, because they are part of the same virtual
network and have a virtual router. Now, how is
the IP address range for the virtual network
defined on each node? How do we make sure that
each node gets a different set of IP addresses so that pods
across the nodes will all have unique ips?
Well, as I mentioned, kubernetes does not care what range
you use. So it's up to the network plugin to define
that range. So network plugin will define a cider
block for the whole cluster, and from that range,
equal subsets of that IP address range
is given to each node. So now each node has
a unique set of ips it can give to its
pods. So we have virtual private networks on each node
with their own sets of IP addresses.
Now the question is, how does myApp
pod from node one talk to mydb
pod on node three using MyDB pod's
IP address? They're in their own private isolated networks,
so they can't access each other directly, so they have
to communicate using gateways. Let's see what that
means. So basically, route rules will be defined
in the route table of the servers that will
map each node's IP address as a gateway
to the pod network on that specific node.
So gateway is basically an IP address of the node,
and that maps to the virtual private network
cider block that was created for the pods
on that specific nodes. And that means now
when my app pod sends a request to
MyDB pod, route rule will be used to determine
which gateway should be used to access
MyDB pods network. And since MyDB
pod network is on node three, the IP address
of the node three, or gateway, will be used
to access the database pod here.
And this way we actually have one large
pod network that the network plugin creates across
all the nodes in the cluster. Again, why can they talk
through the gateway because the nodes, node one,
two and three are in the same network, so they can talk to each other
directly using each other's ip addresses.
Also, each node itself can access the virtual pod
network that was created on that node.
So if my app from node One's pod network wants
to talk to MyDB on node Three's
network, requests can be routed from my app
pod to node one. Then from the route table it will be determined
which node has my db pod. So node one
will send the request to node three, and node
three will then hand it over to myDB pod
on its pod network running inside the virtual
network on node three. And that's how pods
across nodes can communicate with each other.
However, there is one more thing here. In our example, we just
have three nodes, and therefore the route table
is actually pretty short and manageable. However,
imagine if we had thousands of nodes in the cluster.
Managing all these routes and keeping track of them will become very difficult,
so we would need a more automated and more scalable
solution for that. And network plugins actually solve this issue as
well. So the way it works is that networking application
or network plugin like weave for example,
is deployed on each node in the cluster as
a pod. These pods will find each other and
form a group so they can directly talk to each other and
quickly share information about which
pod is running on which node. So when my app
needs to send a request to MyDB pod, the network plugin on
that node will ask other network
plugin pods on other nodes. Hey, which node has
a pod miDb with this IP address
and quickly find out the answer from its peers. This makes
scaling the pod network in the cluster very easy,
even if you have tens of thousands of nodes.
Now, as I said, there are many CNI plugins that
implement networking in Kubernetes, and the
one that we will install is Weavenet.
It's very easy to deploy and it will run as a demon set
which will automatically schedule one wavenet
pod on each node in the cluster, which is exactly
what we need. So let's go ahead and install wavenet plugin to
create a pod network in our cluster.
Install it. I mentioned that pod network IP
address range or the cider block should not
overlap with the node IP address range. So how can
we check that? Well, our nodes get IP addresses
from the VPC, our private network
on AWS. So by checking the VPC service
we can see its IP address range, which is
172.310 00:16
in my case, it could be different for your network. So we have the node
IP range. Now what about the pod network? In the weavenet documentation
we see that default range that will be used is
ten point 32.0.00:12
which is about a million IP addresses between these two
ips. So that's going to be the start of the range
and that's going to be the final ip in the range. And this
means we can create around 1 million pods in
our cluster with this range. And this ip range
will be then evenly divided between the nodes
in the cluster. So as you see, the pod network cider block
and the node cider block do not overlap in our
case. So we can actually go ahead and use the
default IP range of WiPnet. And by the way,
if you want to calculate the range and to make sure
they don't overlap, you can use any cider block
calculator, you can specify the cider block and
you will see all the IP addresses in that range.
So that's actually very easy to validate. Now to install Wavenet,
let's actually check Kubernetes documentation again and I'm going
to search for network add ons.
And here you see the list of all the network solutions or network plugins
you can use in your cluster. And one of them on the list is
Wavenet. And if I click on it, it will take us
to their official documentation and the installation guide here which
is basically a one liner. And with this single
command you can install the weavenet plugin. Now if
you look at this one liner, it's basically taking a Kubernetes
manifest for weavenet application
and applying it using Kubectl apply
command. So if you wanted to see what's actually inside that
manifest that we are applying here, or keep it
locally as well to know which manifest version you
used for a later reference you can actually download this
locally and then apply it. So that's what we're going to do.
I'm going to copy this and on the master node I'm
going to download it with BgeT and save the
contents of this manifest into the Weave
yaml file. If we don't specify this option here,
it will by default try to create a file name with the URL
as the file name. So I'm going to execute this and if
I do. Ls. There you go. We have our weave Yaml
file and we
can see the contents of it, which basically shows us
that a bunch of kubernetes components get created, one of
them or the main one being the demon set as we said with the
Weavenet application itself running on port 6784.
Now we said that we've net defined a
default cider block of 10320 00:12
but what if we wanted to override it? We could
actually set a different cider block inside this with
yaml configuration and deploy the WNet plugin like this.
And again, in the documentation of wivnet
you see that we can do that by specifying this option
as a parameter for Weave launch command.
So we can modify the
weave yaml file going to the demon set component right
here and the main container of weave cube.
We see the launch command right here and we
can add the cider block
range as a parameter. So I'm just going to go ahead
and copy this from here and
instead of 10320 zero we can set it to,
which again should not overlap with our
node IP range. So this should be fine. And just a quick
note here on a command attribute within the container
in Yaml format. This is basically how you can specify
commands as a list of the
command itself and all of its options. So if I had a second and
third options here, I would just list them one by one in
a list like this. So let's save this and
now we can apply which
will install all these components including the demon set.
First, our master node should be in a ready state,
so let's check that kubectl get node.
And as you see we have status ready for master,
so that one's fixed. And the second one
was that core DNS pods were not starting,
they were in a pending state, so that should be fixed as well. And let's
see that get pod in kube system
namespace. And there you go. We have core DNS
pods both in a running status as well as we
have a new pod here. We've net on our master node,
and since we just have one node in the cluster, we have one
weave pod that basically manages the pod network in
our cluster.
And finally, we've talked about pod network and
pod ips. So how do we even see
the ip addresses of the pods in the cluster? Well,
one way of doing it is by getting detailed output
of the pod. So let's check the
core DNS pod and describe
that pod in detail with Kubectl.
Describe pod command and the pod name
as well as the namespace.
And this will give us a bunch of output of containers
creating and starting inside the pod,
as well as some metadata of the pod. And as you see,
we have an IP address for core DNS pod
which is in the range of the
cider block that we defined for wavenet,
which is 1320 three.
So that's one way to check the IP address of a pod.
However, doing this for every pod in the cluster
is too much work, and also you don't have a nice overview
of list of pods with their IP addresses.
To do that, we can display the pods using an output
option o, which stands for output option
wide. So this will basically give us an extended output
of the pods. So let's execute.
And there you go. We have additional columns with additional information,
and one of them is the IP address. And as
you see, the core DNS pods which started
after we've got deployed, have the
IP addresses both from the range of weavenet's
pod networks cider block. And you also notice that
all the other pods, the static pods as well as Kubeproxy
and the wivnet itself have a different
IP address, which is the IP address of the control
plane node they are running on. And that's
because these pods are not part of the regular pod
network like core DNS for example,
or any other pod application pods or database pods
that we're going to deploy later. And that's why they get
this static ip address of the node.
And to check that we can also do kubectl get node
with wide output and see the internal ip address
of the master node, which is same as right here.
So now we have our cluster completely set up, we have our control
plane processes running, and we have a
pod network deployed in the cluster. However, right now we just have
a one node cluster with only a master node.
So it's time to join the worker nodes and make them
part of the cluster. And installing the pod network
plugin was needed to add the worker nodes to
the cluster, otherwise we wouldn't be able to join them and create
pod networks on them. So now that we have everything prepared,
let's configure and join the worker nodes.
Worker nodes we already installed container
D, Kubeadm, Kubelet and Kubectl on
both worker nodes. Also, if you didn't already execute it,
run pseudo swap off a
command on both work nodes to
disable swap as described in the prerequisites.
So once all of this is installed and configured,
we can now actually join the work nodes to the cluster,
which is actually pretty easy.
Remember that we got an output after Kubeadm
init command with join subcommand,
which looked like this kubeadm join
and then some parameters. That's the command
with a generated token that you can execute
on a worker node to join it to the
cluster. So this command basically includes the address of
API server because the worker node needs to know which cluster
it is connecting to or joining to, as well as an automatically
generated secret token so that control plane components
can identify the worker and basically let it
join the cluster. However, if you don't have that command
anymore, don't worry, we can print out this command anytime
we need to join a new node to the cluster.
So let's see how it works. Now the token gets generated on
the master, so we need to create a new token and print
out the join command on the master so
that we can copy it and execute on workers later.
So going back to the master node, we're going to use Kubeadm
to do that. Now I want to give you a pro tip here which is
going to help you a lot when working with either Kubeadm
command line tool or kubectl tool.
Now both of these tools, just like any other command line tool,
also have a help option which shows
you pretty nicely all the subcommands you
have with them. This is the Inif command that we executed with
Kubeadm and some other subcommands with the descriptions
as well as possible options you can pass to those subcommands.
And one of the commands you see here is token,
which is a subcommand to manage the secret tokens
that we need to connect worker nodes to the cluster.
So I'm going to do Kubeadm token and I'm going
to do help again to see the
subcommands of Kubeadm token command
itself. Let's do that. And right here
you see with Kubeadm token we can create
new tokens, we can list existing
tokens and so on. Again, we want to generate
a new token for the worker nodes. So I'm going to do Kubeadm token
create and do help again to
see what other options I can pass onto
it and execute. Going back here usage
Kubeadm token create and one option
that I have here, one flag is print
join command. So in the description you see that instead
of just printing out the newly generated token,
this option will actually print us the
entire Kubeadm join command that we can
simply copy and execute on worker nodes. So I'm going to
copy that option, edit at the end
and let's execute. And there you go. This is
the command we are going to copy and execute
on worker nodes. Again, this is the API
server IP address this is the port
where API server is running on this machine,
right? We have the newly generated token and we have
the CA certificate hash so that worker node
can identify itself with the master node.
So that's our command. Let's copy this, go to
worker one. Now this command will actually require
pseudo privilege. So either you execute it with
a root user by switching to root, or we can just do pseudo
at the beginning. So with pseudo, let's execute the command.
And you see that Kubeadm is executing different
phases. We have the pre flight phase just like with Kubeadm in
it, and another simple phase that basically
configures Kubelet which is already installed and running on
worker node. And basically Kubeadm will tell them
and instruct Kubelet what to do. So in
the background, worker node just joined the cluster
and any pods that needed to be scheduled on
the worker node right here has been scheduled
automatically without our involvement. So to
check that, let's go back to the master and
let's do kubectl get node.
And we should see worker one in a ready status
which is now part of the cluster with the same Kubernetes version.
We can also check an extended output
with internal IP addresses. So this is the master,
this is the worker. And now if we do Kubectl
get pod in all the namespaces and
again a wide output or extended output.
You see that on the worker node with this internal
ip address right here we have two pods
that were automatically started on the worker node.
The first one is kubeproxy and another one is
we've. Net. Now kubeproxy and we've. Net are both
demon sets, if you remember, and demon sets
will automatically schedule a pod in each
single node in the cluster. So everything seems
great here.
Let's actually go ahead and execute
the same Kubeadm join command on worker
two. So we don't have to generate a new token for each
worker node. We can actually reuse the same one. So I'm
going to copy this and execute here
as well. And it's done. The worker node should be now joined
to the cluster as well as Kubelet was configured
and started. Let's actually check the Kubelet service
status and
we see that it's running in an active
state. And again let's
check the nodes. Master, worker one,
worker two, which is in the ready state with
this IP address. And again on
worker two we have the same two demon
set pods, Kubeproxy and Wivnet.
Here I'm going to remind you that joining
the worker nodes is actually possible because
we opened all these ports on master
nodes as
well as the worker nodes so that different processes
on master and worker can communicate with
each other in order to join the worker node to the existing
cluster.
Now as you already learned with Wimnet,
which is a pod networking layer inside
Kubernetes, the Wimnet pods on all the nodes
should now be talking to each other and forming this
network group so that we have a pod network in
the cluster and as we see they are running in
the cluster, but we don't know whether they are talking
to each other or not. Did they actually discover or find
each other and did they form a group? So let's
actually check that as a next step. So I'm going to clear
that and what I'm going to do is I'm
going to print only the weavenet pods
and their names. So we're just going to do a simple grab and
we're going to do weavenet here. So this will give us
the pod names of all the weavenet pods.
So I'm just going to take one of them, doesn't matter which
one, and I'm going to check the application logs
or weavenet application logs in the pod. And to do that
very simply, I'm just going to do Kubectl logs,
name of the pod, name of the namespace where
the pod is running and let's
execute. Now the logs actually don't belong to
a pod, but rather container that is running inside the
pod. And if we have two containers running inside the pod,
like in this case, then Kubernetes or Kubectl doesn't
know which container logs you want. So for that
we need to actually specify a container. So again,
copy that and specify container with
this is the first container, this is the second container. We want the
main application logs and execute again.
And there you go. And here you see the logs
of wivnet from start up till
now. And here you see a bunch of
error messages that says that it cannot connect
to this IP address which belongs to the master
node on this port where weavenet
is running. Now let's check the logs of another
pod, let's say this one for example.
And here you see the same exact error messages,
error during connection attempt. So it's trying to connect
to wavenet pods on
other two nodes, one of the work nodes
and the master node on the port 6783
where we've net is running, but it is failing
to do so. So what is the problem here? As I mentioned,
the networking plugin gets deployed on every node. So together
these individual networking pods deployed across
different nodes make one shared pod network.
In our case, this networking application is Wavenet
which listens on port 6783
on each node and for them to connect
to each other they need to be able to talk to
each other on this port. However, if we check
our firewall rules for the nodes,
you see that port is not open on the nodes,
right? So master node as well as the
work nodes do not allow talking on
port 6783.
So very simply we need to open that port
so that the weave net pods can talk to each other. So to
fix that, let's just open this port on master
and both worker nodes go to security group
edit inbound rules and we're going to add
another rule, custom tcp port 6783
and again, this port should be only open
for instances inside the VPC because we don't
need any outside or external connection to weavenet.
So that's going to be 172310
00:16 which is our
VPC cider block. Let's save the rule,
that's the security group of master nodes.
Let's also configure worker node
security group.
Again add a new rule, one seven
two,
our VPC cider block save rules
and that's it. This should have actually already
solved the problem. So if I go back and
print out logs of again one of the weavenet
pods and another option we have with
logs is to stream the logs so we can see actually output
in live is minus f. So we're going to tail
the logs and right here you see connection accepted. So we
have a successful connection with a master node connection edit
as well as with worker one. So now all the weavenet
pods should be actually talking to each other. And let's actually
check the other weavenet pod as well. Weavenet pod on
master node as well as worker two are connected
to the weavenet on worker one.
Once we install the network plugin and check
its logs, et cetera, we want to see the status and make
sure that all the network plugin pods have
discovered each other and we're able to actually connect to each other and
we can extract this information from the logs.
However, we have a way of seeing the status
in a clean nice output using weave command
itself. So let's see how that works. First of all, let's output
our weave pods,
including the IP addresses or the nodes where they are
running at and grab on weave.
So we have three wivnet pods on each
node, and let's actually check the wave net of
the master and its status. And we're going to do
this with this command. Now you will learn what this
command means and all these options and all these subcommands,
all these options, and how it gets executed step by step in
the later lectures. At this point you can just copy and paste
the command to check the status. So the only thing you will
have to change is the name of the pod. So we'll have to replace
it with your own pod name and execute.
And this will actually execute a weave command inside
the pod and give you a status that will
show you some important information, like how many targets it
was able to discover and how many connections it was able to
establish. So this is the important part here, which shows us
that this specific weavenet instance was able to find
two other peers, these two, and was able to
establish connection with them. So if it says two
failed connections or one established and one failed,
it means the weavenet pods were not able to find each
other. And probably you don't have three peers, but rather
one or three. So in this case everything looks
great. If you have any issues and you don't see
two connections here, you can reference the wivnet
troubleshooting documentation that will help you fix any
of these issues.
And this means now that the wivnet
pods on all the nodes are connected, we can actually
schedule pods on the worker nodes. And finally
to test our setup and that everything is working
as expected. As a final step, let's actually schedule a
test pod in the cluster and see that it's running on
one of the worker nodes. And to do that in the fastest way
and most efficient way, just to test basically
scheduling a pod, we can use Kubectl run
command, which basically needs pod name as a parameter.
So Kubectl run and let's call the pod test
and the image name because the pod needs to run
a container which is based on some image and simply
nginx image from the docker hub will do.
And if I execute this, this will schedule a pod
called test with Nginx image in a default
namespace. Let's execute Kubectl get
pod in a default namespace. Again you
see the container is creating. Let's add
a watch option. And there you go.
Test is running just to make sure that it is
running on one of the work nodes. Let's actually do
an extended output with.
And there you go. As you see it is running on worker
two. And if we want to test scheduling another
pod? Test two for example. And let's
do get pod again. As you see, test two was
scheduled on worker one, so the load was basically divided
between the two worker nodes. Each one is running a
test pod, and the IP address of the
pod itself, as you see, is also from the cider
block that we defined for Weavenet.
And as you see, worker two actually got
its own subset of the cider block
from the total IP range, since as I explained,
the network plugin will evenly distribute
its IP address range among the available
worker nodes, giving each one its own cider block
subset.
Actual application with a Kubernetes service inside
you as a Kubernetes administrator, want to test that application?
Deployment works fine in the cluster before
handing it over to the developers. So in this section we're
going to deploy a simple NGINx application to learn some
basic concepts of creating applications and making them
accessible for users in Kubernetes. For that,
we're going to create a simple configuration file for NGINX
deployment as well as its service to test that everything works.
We will deploy a test pod to connect to the
NgINX application through its service. This would mean
the NgInx is accessible internally for other pods
in the cluster, but we also want to make it accessible externally.
For that, we're going to first configure an external service
and then compare it to accessing the app with Ingress.
So we will deploy and configure ingress for our NgINX
application, and along the way we will learn several interesting
concepts such as labels and selectors, how service
networking works, and so on. So let's dive in for
NgInX. Now, what is a good way to put together a
deployment file? Well, we can write our own file from
scratch, or we can copy an example file from Kubernetes
documentation. So I'm going to go to Kubernetes documentation
and search for a deployment manifest example.
And there you go. We have a very simple example of a deployment
configuration, so we don't have to write this whole thing
from scratch. So I'm going to grab this and copy it
into my editor and save it as NgINx deployment
YaMl file now
a quick note on the editor.
For Kubernetes configuration files. I'm using a
visual studio code editor that supports YAML
format with proper highlighting, et cetera. You can
also install additional YAML plugins if you
want to, so make sure you have a proper editor that will make creating
and adjusting the configuration files easy for you now, you already know
what configuration file is and generally how it looks like,
but let's actually go through this deployment configuration
file step by step and let's see how a deployment
component is configured.
So here in the specification part of a deployment, you see
a template. Template also has its
own metadata and specification. So it's basically a configuration
file inside of a configuration file.
And the reason for it is that this configuration
applies to a pod. So pod should have its
own configuration inside of deployments configuration file
and that's how all the deployments will be defined. And this is
going to be the blueprint for a pod, like which image
it should be based on, which port it should open,
what is going to be the name of the container, et cetera.
So that's basically how deployment configuration
is created and how pod blueprint is configured.
So let's make final adjustments to our deployment file.
So I'm going to take the latest image of NginX. So I'm
going to remove the version tag as well as let's
set the replica count to two replicas. And now let's actually create
an NgINX deployment in our cluster using this deployment
manifest file. For that we have to do Kubectl apply
for this file. So first I'm going to create an NginX
deployment file on Masternode where I have Kubectl
configured.
And I'm just going to copy the contents
and put it here. Again, we have a nice highlighting in
vim editor. Let's save it.
And now we can actually apply it.
Apply f, which stands for file inputs and
Nginx deployment. And now let's see that two Nginx
pods are running in our cluster. Let's do Kubectl get
pod. And there you go. And let's actually
delete those two test pods
because we don't need them anymore.
And for that I'm going to do kubectl delete pod and
name of the pod and we can even provide a list instead of deleting
them one by one. And this will get rid of both
test and test two pods. Great.
So these are our two Nginx pod
replicas. And you see that the name of the pod
is always made up of the name of the deployment
as a prefix. And then you have the unique
hash for each pod. Let's also check that
a deployment was created in the cluster.
For that I'm going to do kubectlgeteployment.
And there you go. We have our NgINX deployment
two pods out of two configured pods
are ready and available. So now whenever
we want to change something in those pods,
like pod image or image version or container
specification, we will adjust the deployment component
and it will then propagate the changes to all of
its pods and restart them if necessary. So we are not going to
be working with pods directly, but rather with deployment.
Now that we have the pods running, we need a
service so that other pods in the cluster or even
external applications can access them. Because remember,
service makes pods accessible on a permanent ip address
using the service name as well as it
load balances the traffic among multiple replicas of
the pods. So let's go ahead and create a service which
again we can grab the specification actually
from the documentation. So let's do service. And here
we have a very simple service example. So I'm going
to copy that. You can of course create it directly on the master node,
but I'm going to first configure it in a visual studio code so that
we have a better overview. So going back to the visual studio code,
I'm going to create a new file, let's call
it NginX service Yaml,
and I'm going to create it next to the deployment
file. So first of all, again we have the same metadata
section in the service which
every Kubernetes component has. So let's call
this NgInX service here to
be consistent and then we have the same specification section.
However, as you already learned, every component specification
attributes or the configuration in the specification section
is different. In a specification of deployment we
have a template for a pod. In the service specification,
we have configuration for ports to access the pods
behind the service. As you see, service configuration is a
bit easier, bit simpler. The main part of the
service configuration is the ports section.
So how this is configured is basically service has
a port where the service itself
is accessible at. So if either service sends
a request to NgInX service here, it needs to send it
on port 80, but this service needs to know to
which pod it should forward the request, but also
at which port is that pod listening and that is
the target port. So this one should match
the container port. So you can have a list of
ports here where each port configuration
basically defines where on which port can
we access the service IP address and on
which port will service, then forward that request
to the pods that it's connected
to. So again, service is attached to a pod and
that pod is also accessible at a certain
port. In our case we want to use this service to
access Nginx pods, right? Here is configured
to be accessible at port 80. So when the
Nginx service gets the request to forward it
to Nginx pods, it should send that request to
port 80. So the target port always points to the container
port where service will send the request to.
And the port attribute itself defines the port where service
itself can be accessed. And these two actually can be
different. So let's configure this to be 80 80 and
the target port to point to the container port which
is 80. So basically when another pod
makes a request towards NgInX application, it will
send a request to this service using the
name of the service and the port number.
The service will take that request and it will then forward it
to one of the pods behind it on
the port where the applications inside the
pods are listening at, which is the target port.
And that's how the communication flow will look like.
Now you may be wondering, we have the target port of
the pods, but how does service know which pods
it should forward the request to? So basically, how do
we connect a service that we create in the cluster to
the pods? So how do we connect these two components
to each other? And that's where labels and selectors come in.
So the way the connection is established is using labels
and selectors. So as you see,
metadata part contains the labels and the
specification part contains selectors.
It's pretty simple. In a metadata, you give
components like deployment or pod a
key value pair and it could be any key value pair that you think of.
In this case, we have app Nginx and that
label just sticks to that component.
So we give pods created
using this blueprint label, app Nginx and
we tell the deployment to connect or to match
all the labels with app Nginx
to create that connection. So this way deployment will
know which pods belong to it. And these two labels
are used by the service selector.
So in the specification of a service, we define a selector which
basically makes a connection between the
service and the deployment or its pods,
because service must know which pods belong to that service
and that connection is made through the selector of
the label. So label is a key value pair
that we can assign to any component.
We can label deployments, pods,
services, et cetera. So label basically acts
like an identifier of the component, just like a name.
So for example, in case of the deployment, we have the name of the
component and in addition to that we have list
of labels that in addition to
the name can be used to identify the deployment.
In the case of pods, however, the label is a required attribute.
So we have to set labels on the pod.
Again, this is a list, so we can have multiple
labels on a component and the
label is any key value pair that you want,
but a standard and a common label key
is app and just the name of the application itself.
So even though you can have any key here,
app basically is kind of a standard.
So that's what you see in most of the examples. So labels
add key value, pair labels to the components and
selector lets you identify and
find all the components which have a certain label
on them. So here in the deployment specification, we have
a selector that finds all the
pods that have a label app nginx
on them. So if we change this to something different,
it will not be able to find pods with this
label. And it works the same way for a service.
If we go here on the specification of a service,
we also have a selector attribute that defines
label for the pods that it wants
to connect to. So in this case, the selector for the
label has to match what we have defined right
here. So it should be app Nginx and
this is basically how we tell a service which
pods it should connect to as its endpoints
and then forward all the requests that it gets on
this port. So now when a service gets a request
here, it will know to forward that request
to any of the pods that have this label
on the port 80 and
that basically configures our service. Now again, I'm going to
copy this service configuration, go back to
my master node and let's create Nginx service
yaml file here and
let's apply Kubectl apply
minus f Nginx service and
to get or to list all the services in the cluster
we have Kubectl get service or
we can also use a short version which is SVC.
And right here you see NgInx service and
the port which we configured for the service. This is where the
service will accept incoming requests, which is
port 80 80.
Now how do we make sure that our service was
connected to the pods? We actually have a subcommand
for Kubectl that will show you detailed
information of any component. And that's a Kubectl describe
command and describe commands. Takes the component type like service
or deployment as the first parameter and then
name of that component. So if we do Kubectl describe
service name of the service, this will give us
a detailed information about the service.
And this is obviously very useful for debugging Kubernetes resources.
So one we see the app Nginx selector. Right here
we see the port and the target port that we configured.
And this is a proof that our service was
able to connect to both NgInx
deployment replicas and registered them as
its endpoints. And these two are the IP
addresses of our NgINx deployment pods as
well as port number where Nginx inside
those pods is running. And to also be 100% sure,
we can do kubectl get pod white which will
show us the IP addresses of the pods.
And right here you see these two
are the IP addresses registered as endpoints
here. So this means if your service is not forwarding
requests to the pods as it's supposed to,
you can actually check its endpoints and see that
it has registered all the pod replicas.
Another component that gets created whenever we
connect a service to pods is an
endpoint component. And we can also get that endpoint component
using Kubectlgetep as
an endpoint. And this will actually give you a
nice list of all the services with the service names together
with a list of their endpoints. So that's another way
to check that all your services have right endpoints in the cluster.
Now the interesting question here is how does the service
forward the request to the IP address?
Or basically who manages these service endpoints?
As you already learned, service is not a process.
It's not an application or a process that is running
on one of the nodes. It's actually just a virtual
IP address that is accessible throughout the whole cluster.
So it's not bound to one specific cluster node.
And the requests to that virtual IP address then
get forwarded to the actual processes
which are the pods behind that service. And this
forwarding is done by Kubeproxy.
So Kubeproxy is responsible for maintaining
the list of all the service IP addresses and
the Pod IP addresses that belong to that service.
So Kubeproxy is the one that is managing service
and its endpoints. So when the request is sent
to the service IP address, Kubeproxy will intercept the
request. It will check in its list which
pod endpoints are registered for the service IP address,
and it will pick one of the pods to forward the request
to. So that's how the requests are forwarded
from services to their pod endpoints.
Now remember I said that the third part
of the configuration file is a section describing
status of the component. And since we created deployment
and service components, let's actually see that auto generated
part of the component. So how do we actually
check the complete configuration file
with the auto generated attributes and the status section
of the components that we created in the cluster. Well, first of all, let's print
out all the components we have in a default namespace in
the cluster right now, Kubectl get all.
So instead of get pod or service we are saying give
me all the resources I have in a default namespace
and this will give us the services pod deployment,
et cetera. And now let's actually check the configuration
file of NgINX service that kubernetes
edit some auto generated information to.
So one way to do that is using Kubectl edit command.
Again, we need type of the resource, it could be service
or the short version and name
of that component. If I click
this will open my default editor which is beam,
and show me a Kubernetes configuration file which
of course is based on the service manifest that we
created. But Kubernetes basically added bunch of
attributes and bunch of information to it
and that's what we're seeing. So all of these are automatically generated
information like unique id creation time,
et cetera. And right here we have a status
section here with some information. And to leave
the editor in vim I'm going to click on the escape
key colon and
quit without any changes.
And the same way we can also check the deployment
status. Again, bunch of auto generated
information,
obviously much more than what we configured. And here we
have a little bit longer status section which
has an information about the actual state of the deployment like
how many replicas are ready and available,
et cetera. Again, let's leave the editor and
you can use this edit command with all the components.
An alternative way of checking the YAMl
configuration file of the components in the cluster
without having to go in edit mode is
to do get and
instead of just printing out an output
like this, we can do give me an
output in YAMl format and this
will basically give you the same contents as we got with Kubectl
edit command.
One use case of using labels for components and
as you learned we need to give pods a label so
that sir vis can identify and select them
using that label selector. However there are other use cases
of labels as well. Now the question is what are other
use cases of labels.
IP address gets assigned to each node.
Now, on each of these nodes, we need to schedule pods,
but we said that pods are own isolated
machines in its own private network. So on
each node, a private network is created by
the network plugin with a different IP address range,
which, very important to note here,
should not overlap with the IP address range
of the nodes. Otherwise, the pod communication in your cluster
will not work. And this private network has a private switch
or a bridge on the host, which will let all
the pods within that network talk to each other, just like
nodes which are in the same VPC or same
network can talk to each other directly. So that's how the pods on
the same node can talk to each other directly, because they are part of
the same virtual network and have a virtual
router. Now, how is the IP address range
for the virtual network defined on
each node? How do we make sure that each node gets
a different set of IP addresses so that pods
across the nodes will all have unique ips?
Well, as I mentioned, kubernetes does not care what
range you use. So it's up to the network plugin to
define that range. So network plugin will define
a cider block for the whole cluster, and from that
range, equal subsets of that
IP address range is given to each node.
So now each node has a unique set of ips it can
give to its pods. So we have virtual
private networks on each node with their own
sets of IP addresses. Now the question is,
how does myApp pod from
node one talk to mydb pod on node
three using MyDB pod's IP
address? They're in their own private isolated networks,
so they can't access each other directly, so they have
to communicate using gateways. Let's see what
that means. So basically, route rules will be defined in
the route table of the servers that will map
each node's IP address as a gateway to
the pod network on that specific node.
So gateway is basically an IP address of the node,
and that maps to the virtual private
network cider block that was created for
the pods on that specific nodes. And that means
now when my app pod sends a request
to MyDB pod, route rule will be used
to determine which gateway should be used
to access MyDB pods network.
And since MyDB pod network is on node three,
the IP address of the node three, or gateway,
will be used to access the database pod
here. And this way we actually have one
large pod network that the network plugin
creates across all the nodes in the cluster.
Again, why can they talk through the gateway because
the nodes, node one, two and three are in the same network,
so they can talk to each other directly using each
other's ip addresses. Also, each node itself can
access the virtual pod network that was created
on that node. So if my app from node One's pod network
wants to talk to MyDB on node Three's network,
requests can be routed from my app pod to node
one. Then from the route table it will be determined which
node has my db pod. So node one will
send the request to node three, and node three will then
hand it over to myDB pod on
its pod network running inside the virtual network
on node three. And that's how pods across nodes
can communicate with each other.
However, there is one more thing here. In our example,
we just have three nodes, and therefore the route table
is actually pretty short and manageable. However,
imagine if we had thousands of nodes in the cluster.
Managing all these routes and keeping track of them will become very
difficult, so we would need a more automated and
more scalable solution for that. And network plugins actually solve
this issue as well. So the way it works is that networking
application or network plugin like weave for example,
is deployed on each node in the cluster as
a pod. These pods will find each other and form a group
so they can directly talk to each other and quickly share information
about which pod is running on which node.
So when my app needs to send a request to MyDB pod,
the network plugin on that node will ask
other network plugin pods on other nodes.
Hey, which node has a pod miDb
with this IP address and quickly
find out the answer from its peers. This makes
scaling the pod network in the cluster very easy,
even if you have tens of thousands of nodes.
Now, as I said, there are many CNI plugins
that implement networking in Kubernetes, and the
one that we will install is Weavenet.
It's very easy to deploy and it will run as a demon set
which will automatically schedule one
wavenet pod on each node in the cluster,
which is exactly what we need. So let's go ahead and install wavenet
plugin to create a pod network in our cluster.
Install it. I mentioned that pod network IP address range
or the cider block should not overlap with the node IP address
range. So how can we check that? Well, our nodes get
IP addresses from the VPC,
our private network on AWS. So by checking
the VPC service we can see its IP address
range, which is 172.310
00:16 in my case, it could be different for
your network. So we have the node IP range. Now what about
the pod network? In the weavenet documentation we
see that default range that will be used is
ten point 32.0.00:12
which is about a million IP addresses between these two
ips. So that's going to be the start of the range
and that's going to be the final ip in the range.
And this means we can create around 1 million
pods in our cluster with this range. And this ip range
will be then evenly divided between the nodes in the cluster.
So as you see, the pod network cider block and
the node cider block do not overlap in our case.
So we can actually go ahead and use the default IP
range of WiPnet. And by the way, if you want to
calculate the range and to make sure they
don't overlap, you can use any cider block
calculator, you can specify the cider block and
you will see all the IP addresses in that range.
So that's actually very easy to validate. Now to install Wavenet,
let's actually check Kubernetes documentation again and I'm going to search
for network add ons.
And here you see the list of all the network solutions or network
plugins you can use in your cluster. And one of
them on the list is Wavenet. And if I click on it,
it will take us to their official documentation and the installation
guide here which is basically a one liner. And with this
single command you can install the weavenet plugin.
Now if you look at this one liner, it's basically taking
a Kubernetes manifest for weavenet application
and applying it using Kubectl apply
command. So if you wanted to see what's actually inside
that manifest that we are applying here, or keep
it locally as well to know which manifest version
you used for a later reference you can actually
download this locally and then apply it.
So that's what we're going to do. I'm going to copy this and on
the master node I'm going to download it with BgeT and
save the contents of this manifest into the
Weave yaml file. If we don't specify this
option here, it will by default try to create
a file name with the URL as the file name. So I'm going
to execute this and if I do. Ls.
There you go. We have our weave Yaml file
and we can see the contents of it,
which basically shows us that a bunch of kubernetes components
get created, one of them or the main one being the demon set as
we said with the Weavenet application itself running on
port 6784. Now we said
that we've net defined a default cider block
of 10320 00:12
but what if we wanted to override it? We could actually
set a different cider block inside this
with yaml configuration and deploy the WNet plugin
like this. And again, in the documentation of
wivnet you see that we can do that by specifying this
option as a parameter for Weave launch
command. So we can modify
the weave yaml file going to
the demon set component right here and the
main container of weave cube. We see the launch command
right here and we can add the
cider block range as a parameter. So I'm just going to
go ahead and copy this from here and
instead of 10320 zero we can set it
to,
which again should not overlap with our node
IP range. So this should be fine. And just a
quick note here on a command attribute within the container
in Yaml format. This is basically how you can specify
commands as a list of the
command itself and all of its options. So if I had a second and
third options here, I would just list them one by one
in a list like this. So let's save this and
now we can apply which
will install all these components including the demon set.
First, our master node should be in a ready state,
so let's check that kubectl get node.
And as you see we have status ready for
master, so that one's fixed. And the
second one was that core DNS pods were not starting,
they were in a pending state, so that should be fixed as well.
And let's see that get pod in kube
system namespace. And there you go.
We have core DNS pods both in a running
status as well as we have a new pod here. We've net on
our master node, and since we just have one node in
the cluster, we have one weave pod that
basically manages the pod network in our cluster.
And finally, we've talked about pod network and
pod ips. So how do we even see the
ip addresses of the pods in the cluster? Well, one way of
doing it is by getting detailed output of
the pod. So let's check the core DNS pod
and describe that pod in detail
with Kubectl. Describe pod command and the
pod name as well as the namespace.
And this will give us a bunch of output of containers
creating and starting inside the pod,
as well as some metadata of the pod. And as you see,
we have an IP address for core DNS pod
which is in the range of
the cider block that we defined for wavenet,
which is 1320
three. So that's one way to check the IP address of a pod. However,
doing this for every pod in the cluster is
too much work, and also you don't have a nice overview of
list of pods with their IP addresses. To do that,
we can display the pods using an output
option o, which stands for output option
wide. So this will basically give us an extended output
of the pods. So let's execute. And there you
go. We have additional columns with additional information,
and one of them is the IP address.
And as you see, the core DNS pods which started
after we've got deployed,
have the IP addresses both from the range
of weavenet's pod networks cider block.
And you also notice that all the other pods,
the static pods as well as Kubeproxy and
the wivnet itself have a different
IP address, which is the IP address of the control plane
node they are running on. And that's because
these pods are not part of the regular pod network
like core DNS for example, or any other pod application
pods or database pods that we're going to deploy later.
And that's why they get this static ip
address of the node. And to check that we can
also do kubectl get node with wide output
and see the internal ip address of the master node,
which is same as right here. So now we have
our cluster completely set up, we have our control
plane processes running, and we have
a pod network deployed in the cluster. However, right now we just have
a one node cluster with only a master node.
So it's time to join the worker nodes and make them
part of the cluster. And installing the pod network plugin
was needed to add the worker nodes to the cluster,
otherwise we wouldn't be able to join them and create pod networks
on them. So now that we have everything prepared,
let's configure and join the worker nodes.
Worker nodes we already installed container
D, Kubeadm, Kubelet and Kubectl
on both worker nodes. Also, if you didn't already execute
it, run pseudo swap off a
command on both work nodes to
disable swap as described in the prerequisites. So once
all of this is installed and configured, we can now
actually join the work nodes to the cluster,
which is actually pretty easy.
Remember that we got an output after Kubeadm
init command with join subcommand,
which looked like this kubeadm join and then
some parameters. That's the command with a
generated token that you can execute on
a worker node to join it to the cluster.
So this command basically includes the address of API
server because the worker node needs to know which
cluster it is connecting to or joining to,
as well as an automatically generated secret token
so that control plane components can identify the worker
and basically let it join the cluster.
However, if you don't have that command anymore,
don't worry, we can print out this command anytime we need to
join a new node to the cluster. So let's see
how it works. Now the token gets generated on the master,
so we need to create a new token and print out
the join command on the master so that we can copy
it and execute on workers later. So going back to
the master node, we're going to use Kubeadm
to do that. Now I want to give you a pro tip here which
is going to help you a lot when working with either
Kubeadm command line tool or kubectl
tool. Now both of these tools, just like any other command line
tool, also have a help option which shows
you pretty nicely all the subcommands
you have with them. This is the Inif command that we executed
with Kubeadm and some other subcommands with
the descriptions as well as possible options
you can pass to those subcommands. And one of the commands
you see here is token, which is a
subcommand to manage the secret tokens that
we need to connect worker nodes to the cluster.
So I'm going to do Kubeadm token and I'm
going to do help again to see the
subcommands of Kubeadm token command itself.
Let's do that. And right here you see with Kubeadm
token we can create new tokens, we can
list existing tokens and so on.
Again, we want to generate a new token for the worker nodes.
So I'm going to do Kubeadm token create and do
help again to see what other options
I can pass onto it and execute.
Going back here usage Kubeadm token create
and one option that I have here,
one flag is print join command.
So in the description you see that instead of just printing
out the newly generated token, this option will
actually print us the entire Kubeadm
join command that we can simply copy and execute on
worker nodes. So I'm going to copy that option,
edit at the end and let's execute. And there
you go. This is the command we are
going to copy and execute on worker nodes. Again,
this is the API server
IP address this is the port where API server
is running on this machine, right? We have
the newly generated token and we have the CA
certificate hash so that worker node
can identify itself with the master node.
So that's our command. Let's copy this, go to worker
one. Now this command will actually require pseudo
privilege. So either you execute it with a
root user by switching to root, or we can just do
pseudo at the beginning. So with pseudo,
let's execute the command. And you see that
Kubeadm is executing different phases. We have the pre
flight phase just like with Kubeadm in it,
and another simple phase that basically configures
Kubelet which is already installed and running on worker
node. And basically Kubeadm will tell them and instruct
Kubelet what to do. So in the background,
worker node just joined the cluster and
any pods that needed to be scheduled on the worker
node right here has been scheduled
automatically without our involvement.
So to check that, let's go back to the master
and let's do kubectl get node.
And we should see worker one in a ready status
which is now part of the cluster with the same Kubernetes version.
We can also check an extended output
with internal IP addresses. So this is the master, this is
the worker. And now if we do Kubectl
get pod in all the namespaces and
again a wide output or extended output.
You see that on the worker node with this internal
ip address right here we have two
pods that were automatically started on the worker
node. The first one is kubeproxy and another one
is we've. Net. Now kubeproxy and we've. Net are
both demon sets, if you remember, and demon sets
will automatically schedule a pod in each
single node in the cluster. So everything seems
great here.
Let's actually go ahead and
execute the same Kubeadm join command on
worker two. So we don't have to generate a new token for
each worker node. We can actually reuse the same one.
So I'm going to copy this and execute here
as well. And it's done. The worker node should be now
joined to the cluster as well as Kubelet was
configured and started. Let's actually check the Kubelet service
status and
we see that it's running in an active state.
And again let's
check the nodes. Master, worker one, worker two,
which is in the ready state with this IP address.
And again on worker two we
have the same two demon set pods,
Kubeproxy and Wivnet. Here I'm going to remind you
that joining the worker nodes is
actually possible because we opened all these
ports on master nodes as
well as the worker nodes so that different processes
on master and worker can communicate with each
other in order to join the worker node to the existing cluster.
Now as you already learned with Wimnet,
which is a pod networking layer inside Kubernetes,
the Wimnet pods on all the nodes should now be
talking to each other and forming this network group
so that we have a pod network in the cluster and
as we see they are running in the cluster,
but we don't know whether they are talking to each other or not.
Did they actually discover or find each other and did they form
a group? So let's actually check that as
a next step. So I'm going to clear that and what I'm going to
do is I'm going to print only the
weavenet pods and their names. So we're just going to
do a simple grab and we're going to do weavenet
here. So this will give us the pod names of
all the weavenet pods. So I'm just going to take
one of them, doesn't matter which one, and I'm going to check
the application logs or weavenet application
logs in the pod. And to do that very simply,
I'm just going to do Kubectl logs,
name of the pod, name of the namespace where the
pod is running and let's execute.
Now the logs actually don't belong to a pod,
but rather container that is running inside the
pod. And if we have two containers running inside the pod,
like in this case, then Kubernetes or Kubectl doesn't
know which container logs you want. So for that
we need to actually specify a container.
So again, copy that and specify container
with this is the first container, this is the second container.
We want the main application logs and
execute again. And there you go. And here you see
the logs of wivnet from start up
till now. And here you see
a bunch of error messages that says that
it cannot connect to this IP address
which belongs to the master node on this port
where weavenet is running. Now let's check the logs of
another pod, let's say this one for example.
And here you see the same exact error messages,
error during connection attempt. So it's trying to connect
to wavenet pods on other
two nodes, one of the work nodes and
the master node on the port 6783
where we've net is running, but it is failing to
do so. So what is the problem here? As I mentioned,
the networking plugin gets deployed on every node. So together these
individual networking pods deployed across different
nodes make one shared pod network.
In our case, this networking application is Wavenet
which listens on port 6783
on each node and for them to connect to
each other they need to be able to talk to each
other on this port. However, if we check
our firewall rules for the nodes,
you see that port is not open on the nodes,
right? So master node as well as
the work nodes do not allow talking
on port 6783.
So very simply we need to open that
port so that the weave net pods can talk to each
other. So to fix that, let's just open this port
on master and both worker nodes go to security
group edit inbound rules and
we're going to add another rule,
custom tcp port 6783 and again,
this port should be only open for instances
inside the VPC because we don't need any outside
or external connection to weavenet. So that's going to be
172310 00:16
which is our VPC cider block. Let's save
the rule, that's the security group of master
nodes. Let's also configure
worker node security group.
Again add a new rule, one seven two,
our VPC cider block save rules
and that's it. This should have actually already solved the
problem. So if I go back and print
out logs of again one of the weavenet
pods and another option we
have with logs is to stream the logs so we can see
actually output in live is minus f.
So we're going to tail the logs and right here you see connection
accepted. So we have a successful connection with a master node connection
edit as well as with worker one. So now all
the weavenet pods should be actually talking to each
other. And let's actually check
the other weavenet pod as well. Weavenet pod
on master node as well as worker two are connected
to the weavenet on worker one.
Once we install the network plugin and check
its logs, et cetera, we want to see the status and
make sure that all the network plugin pods
have discovered each other and we're able to actually connect to
each other and we can extract this information from the
logs. However, we have a way of seeing the status
in a clean nice output using weave command itself.
So let's see how that works. First of all, let's output
our weave pods,
including the IP addresses or the nodes where they
are running at and grab on weave.
So we have three wivnet pods on
each node, and let's actually check the wave net
of the master and its status. And we're
going to do this with this command. Now you will learn
what this command means and all these options and all these
subcommands, all these options, and how it gets executed step
by step in the later lectures. At this point you can just
copy and paste the command to check the status. So the
only thing you will have to change is the name of the pod. So we'll
have to replace it with your own pod name and execute.
And this will actually execute a weave command inside the
pod and give you a status that will show you
some important information, like how many targets it was
able to discover and how many connections it was
able to establish. So this is the important part here,
which shows us that this specific weavenet instance was
able to find two other peers,
these two, and was able to establish connection with
them. So if it says two failed connections or one
established and one failed, it means the weavenet pods were not
able to find each other. And probably you don't have three peers,
but rather one or three. So in this
case everything looks great. If you have any issues
and you don't see two connections here, you can reference the
wivnet troubleshooting documentation that will help
you fix any of these issues.
And this means now that the wivnet
pods on all the nodes are connected, we can actually
schedule pods on the worker nodes. And finally to
test our setup and that everything is working
as expected. As a final step, let's actually schedule a
test pod in the cluster and see that it's running
on one of the worker nodes. And to do that in the fastest way
and most efficient way, just to test basically scheduling
a pod, we can use Kubectl run command,
which basically needs pod name as a parameter.
So Kubectl run and let's call the pod
test and the image name because
the pod needs to run a container which is based on some image and
simply nginx image from the docker hub
will do. And if I execute this, this will schedule
a pod called test with Nginx image in
a default namespace. Let's execute Kubectl
get pod in a default namespace. Again you
see the container is creating. Let's add a watch
option. And there you go. Test is running
just to make sure that it is running on one of the work nodes.
Let's actually do an extended output
with. And there you go.
As you see it is running on worker two. And if we
want to test scheduling another pod?
Test two for example. And let's do get pod
again. As you see, test two was scheduled
on worker one, so the load was basically divided between the
two worker nodes. Each one is running a test
pod, and the IP address of the pod
itself, as you see, is also from the cider
block that we defined for Weavenet.
And as you see, worker two actually got its
own subset of the cider block from
the total IP range, since as I explained,
the network plugin will evenly distribute
its IP address range among the available
worker nodes, giving each one its own cider
block subset.
Actual application with a Kubernetes service inside
you as a Kubernetes administrator, want to test that application?
Deployment works fine in the cluster before handing it
over to the developers. So in this section we're going to deploy
a simple NGINx application to learn some basic
concepts of creating applications and making them accessible
for users in Kubernetes. For that, we're going to
create a simple configuration file for NGINX deployment
as well as its service to test that everything works.
We will deploy a test pod to connect
to the NgINX application through its service.
This would mean the NgInx is accessible internally for
other pods in the cluster, but we also want to make it accessible
externally. For that, we're going to first configure an external
service and then compare it to accessing the app with
Ingress. So we will deploy and configure ingress
for our NgINX application, and along the way we will learn
several interesting concepts such as labels and selectors,
how service networking works, and so on. So let's
dive in for
NgInX. Now, what is a good way to put together a
deployment file? Well, we can write our own file from
scratch, or we can copy an example file from
Kubernetes documentation. So I'm going to go to Kubernetes documentation
and search for a deployment manifest example.
And there you go. We have a very simple example
of a deployment configuration, so we don't have to write
this whole thing from scratch. So I'm going to grab this
and copy it into my editor and save it
as NgINx deployment YaMl file
now a quick note on the editor. For Kubernetes
configuration files. I'm using a visual studio
code editor that supports YAML format
with proper highlighting, et cetera. You can also install additional YAML
plugins if you want to, so make sure you have a proper editor that will
make creating and adjusting the configuration files easy for you
now, you already know what configuration file is and generally
how it looks like, but let's actually go through this deployment
configuration file step by step and let's see how
a deployment component is configured.
So here in the specification part of a deployment, you see
a template. Template also has its
own metadata and specification. So it's basically a
configuration file inside of a configuration file.
And the reason for it is that this configuration
applies to a pod. So pod should have its own
configuration inside of deployments configuration
file and that's how all the deployments will be defined.
And this is going to be the blueprint for a pod,
like which image it should be based on, which port it should open,
what is going to be the name of the container, et cetera.
So that's basically how deployment configuration is
created and how pod blueprint is configured.
So let's make final adjustments to our deployment
file. So I'm going to take the latest image of NginX.
So I'm going to remove the version tag as well as
let's set the replica count to two replicas. And now let's actually create
an NgINX deployment in our cluster using this deployment
manifest file. For that we have to do Kubectl apply for
this file. So first I'm going to create an NginX
deployment file on Masternode where I have Kubectl
configured. And I'm
just going to copy the contents and put it here.
Again, we have a nice highlighting in vim editor.
Let's save it. And now we can actually apply it.
Apply f, which stands for file
inputs and Nginx deployment. And now
let's see that two Nginx pods are running in our
cluster. Let's do Kubectl get pod.
And there you go. And let's actually delete those
two test pods because we don't need them
anymore. And for that I'm going to do kubectl
delete pod and name of the pod and we
can even provide a list instead of deleting them one by one.
And this will get rid of both test and test two pods.
Great. So these are our two Nginx
pod replicas. And you see that the name of the pod is
always made up of the name of the deployment as
a prefix. And then you have the unique
hash for each pod. Let's also check that
a deployment was created in the cluster. For that
I'm going to do kubectlgeteployment.
And there you go. We have our NgINX deployment
two pods out of two configured pods are ready
and available. So now whenever we want to change
something in those pods, like pod image
or image version or container specification,
we will adjust the deployment component and it
will then propagate the changes to all of its pods
and restart them if necessary. So we are not going to be working
with pods directly, but rather with deployment.
Now that we have the pods running, we need a service
so that other pods in the cluster or even external
applications can access them. Because remember,
service makes pods accessible on a permanent ip
address using the service name as well as it
load balances the traffic among multiple replicas of
the pods. So let's go ahead and create a service which again
we can grab the specification actually from
the documentation. So let's do service. And here we
have a very simple service example. So I'm going to copy that.
You can of course create it directly on the master node, but I'm going to
first configure it in a visual studio code so that we have a
better overview. So going back to the visual studio code,
I'm going to create a new file, let's call it
NginX service Yaml,
and I'm going to create it next to the deployment
file. So first of all, again we have the same metadata
section in the service which
every Kubernetes component has. So let's call
this NgInX service here to
be consistent and then we have the same specification section.
However, as you already learned, every component specification
attributes or the configuration in the specification section is
different. In a specification of deployment we have a
template for a pod. In the service specification, we have configuration
for ports to access the pods behind the service.
As you see, service configuration is a bit easier,
bit simpler. The main part of the service configuration
is the ports section.
So how this is configured is basically service has
a port where the service itself
is accessible at. So if either
service sends a request to NgInX service here,
it needs to send it on port 80, but this service needs
to know to which pod it should forward the request,
but also at which port is that pod listening and
that is the target port. So this one should
match the container port. So you can have
a list of ports here where each
port configuration basically defines where
on which port can we access the service
IP address and on which port will
service, then forward that request to the pods
that it's connected to. So again, service is
attached to a pod and that pod is also
accessible at a certain port. In our case
we want to use this service to access Nginx pods,
right? Here is configured to be accessible at port
80. So when the Nginx service gets
the request to forward it to Nginx pods,
it should send that request to port 80.
So the target port always points to the container port where
service will send the request to.
And the port attribute itself defines the port
where service itself can be accessed. And these two actually can
be different. So let's configure this to be 80 80 and the target
port to point to the container port which is 80.
So basically when another pod makes a
request towards NgInX application, it will send
a request to this service using the
name of the service and the port number. The service
will take that request and it will then forward it to
one of the pods behind it on the
port where the applications inside the pods
are listening at, which is the target port.
And that's how the communication flow will look like.
Now you may be wondering, we have the target port of the
pods, but how does service know which pods it should
forward the request to? So basically, how do we connect a
service that we create in the cluster to the pods?
So how do we connect these two components to each other?
And that's where labels and selectors come in.
So the way the connection is established is using labels
and selectors. So as you see,
metadata part contains the labels and the
specification part contains selectors.
It's pretty simple. In a metadata,
you give components like deployment
or pod a key value pair and it could be any key value
pair that you think of. In this case, we have app Nginx
and that label just sticks to that component.
So we give pods created
using this blueprint label, app Nginx and
we tell the deployment to connect or
to match all the labels with app
Nginx to create that connection.
So this way deployment will know which pods belong to it.
And these two labels are used by the service
selector. So in the specification of a service,
we define a selector which basically makes a connection
between the service and the deployment or
its pods, because service must know which
pods belong to that service and that connection is
made through the selector of the label. So label
is a key value pair that we can assign to any
component. We can label deployments,
pods, services, et cetera. So label basically
acts like an identifier of the component,
just like a name. So for example, in case of the deployment,
we have the name of the component and in
addition to that we have list of labels
that in addition to the name can be
used to identify the deployment. In the case of
pods, however, the label is a required attribute.
So we have to set labels on the pod.
Again, this is a list, so we can have multiple
labels on a component and the
label is any key value pair that
you want, but a standard and a common label key
is app and just the name of the application itself.
So even though you can have any key here,
app basically is kind of a standard. So that's
what you see in most of the examples. So labels add
key value, pair labels to the components and selector
lets you identify and find all the
components which have a certain label on
them. So here in the deployment specification,
we have a selector that finds all the
pods that have a label app nginx
on them. So if we change this to something different, it will
not be able to find pods with this
label. And it works the same way for a service. If we
go here on the specification of a service, we also
have a selector attribute that defines label
for the pods that it wants to connect to.
So in this case, the selector for the label has to match
what we have defined right here. So it should be app
Nginx and this
is basically how we tell a service which pods
it should connect to as its endpoints
and then forward all the requests that it gets on
this port. So now when a service gets a request
here, it will know to forward that request
to any of the pods that have this label on
the port 80 and
that basically configures our service. Now again,
I'm going to copy this service configuration, go back
to my master node and let's create
Nginx service yaml
file here and
let's apply Kubectl apply
minus f Nginx service and
to get or to list all the services in the cluster we
have Kubectl get service or we can
also use a short version which is SVC.
And right here you see NgInx service and
the port which we configured for the service. This is where
the service will accept incoming requests, which is port
80 80.
Now how do we make sure that our service was connected
to the pods? We actually have a subcommand for Kubectl
that will show you detailed information of
any component. And that's a Kubectl describe command
and describe commands. Takes the component type like service or
deployment as the first parameter and then name
of that component. So if we do Kubectl describe service
name of the service, this will give us a detailed
information about the service. And this is
obviously very useful for debugging Kubernetes resources.
So one we see the app Nginx selector. Right here
we see the port and the target port that we configured.
And this is a proof that our service was able
to connect to both NgInx deployment
replicas and registered them as its endpoints.
And these two are the IP addresses of
our NgINx deployment pods as well as port number
where Nginx inside those pods is running.
And to also be 100% sure, we can do kubectl
get pod white which will show us the IP addresses of
the pods. And right here you see
these two are the IP addresses registered as
endpoints here. So this means if your service is not
forwarding requests to the pods as it's supposed
to, you can actually check its endpoints and see that
it has registered all the pod replicas. Another component
that gets created whenever we connect a service
to pods is an endpoint component.
And we can also get that endpoint component using
Kubectlgetep as an endpoint.
And this will actually give you a nice list of all the
services with the service names together with a
list of their endpoints. So that's another way to check
that all your services have right endpoints in the cluster.
Now the interesting question here is how does the service
forward the request to the IP address?
Or basically who manages these service endpoints?
As you already learned, service is not a process.
It's not an application or a process that is running
on one of the nodes. It's actually just a virtual
IP address that is accessible throughout the whole cluster.
So it's not bound to one specific cluster node.
And the requests to that virtual IP address
then get forwarded to the actual processes
which are the pods behind that service. And this forwarding
is done by Kubeproxy. So Kubeproxy
is responsible for maintaining the list
of all the service IP addresses and the Pod
IP addresses that belong to that service. So Kubeproxy
is the one that is managing service and its endpoints.
So when the request is sent to the service IP address,
Kubeproxy will intercept the request. It will
check in its list which pod endpoints are registered
for the service IP address, and it will pick one
of the pods to forward the request to.
So that's how the requests are forwarded from services to
their pod endpoints.
Now remember I said that the third part of the
configuration file is a section describing
status of the component. And since we created deployment
and service components, let's actually see that auto
generated part of the component. So how do we
actually check the complete configuration
file with the auto generated attributes and the status
section of the components that we created in the cluster.
Well, first of all, let's print out all the components we have
in a default namespace in the cluster right now,
Kubectl get all. So instead of get
pod or service we are saying give me all the resources
I have in a default namespace and this will give us the
services pod deployment, et cetera.
And now let's actually check the configuration file of NgINX
service that kubernetes edit some
auto generated information to. So one way to
do that is using Kubectl edit command. Again,
we need type of the resource, it could be service or the
short version and name of that
component. If I click this
will open my default editor which is beam,
and show me a Kubernetes configuration file
which of course is based on the service manifest that
we created. But Kubernetes basically added bunch of attributes
and bunch of information to it and that's what we're seeing.
So all of these are automatically generated information like
unique id creation time, et cetera. And right
here we have a status section here with some information.
And to leave the editor in vim
I'm going to click on the escape key colon
and quit without any changes.
And the same way we can also check the
deployment status.
Again, bunch of auto generated information,
obviously much more than what we configured. And here we
have a little bit longer status section
which has an information about the actual state of the deployment
like how many replicas are ready and available,
et cetera. Again, let's leave the editor and
you can use this edit command with all the components.
An alternative way of checking the
YAMl configuration file of the components in
the cluster without having to go
in edit mode is to do get
and instead of just printing out an output
like this, we can do give me an output in
YAMl format and this will basically give
you the same contents as we got with Kubectl edit
command.
One use case of using labels for components
and as you learned we need to give pods a label
so that sir vis can identify and select them using
that label selector. However there are other use cases
of labels as well. Now the question is what are other
use cases of labels.