And one of the local volumes you can use for data
persistence is called hostpath.
And as I said, this is very simple to configure because we
don't need to create storage on a remote platform,
like a cloud platform for example. And this is actually
one of the volume types that is tested in the CKA
exam. So in this lecture we're going to configure a host path volume
for our application. And this is actually very simple.
First, we're going to create a persistent volume component with
the host path as a storage backend. So again,
the data storage with host path is actually local machine.
So on the server's file system we're
going to choose a location which will persist all the data
for our application. Once we have the persistent volume
created in the cluster, we can then create a persistent volume
claim. The persistent volume claim resource is there to
claim storage through persistent volume
component. So again, if we have multiple persistent volumes in the cluster
and we create a volume claim, the claim will actually find the
persistent volume with the most fitting configuration
to claim its storage. And finally, because we want
to use this storage in our application, we are going to configure
our deployment or our pod actually to use
that storage through a persistent volume claim.
So let's see how all that works.
So first of all, how do we create persistent volume? Let's check
if we have option to
create it in an imperative way. And as you see, it's not
actually on the list of create subcommands.
However, you can always check the Kubernetes official documentation for
the example files for Kubernetes resources.
And this one actually documents creating a persistent volume,
a volume claim for it, as well as how to then
use that in a pod. So we're going to use this as a reference.
So I'm going to copy the first three lines and we're going to create
this step by step. And let's call this
Myapp persistent volume Yaml.
And as you see the kind is persistent volume and
let's call it data Pv.
And we have the specification. So what are the main attributes
to define in a persistent volume? The first and the
main configuration is what storage
backend we want to use to store the
data. Is it Amazon's elastic block storage?
Is it Google Cloud storage or some NFS
server, or in our case host path type?
And note that depending on which storage you
use, the attributes will be different. For host path,
the attribute is host path, and then it has its own
set of configuration options. And as I said, host path
configuration is super simple. We just need a path
or basically a location on local machine
which will store the data and we're going to set it to mount
data. And these two lines here will basically configure what
storage backend we're using to store the data when
we reference it using the persistent volume. So once the storage
backend is configured, now we want to know how much
storage do we actually need. So basically we need a storage
capacity that this persistent volume will
require from the type of storage defined
here. So on a local machine on host path,
we want a capacity for
storage of 10gb.
So we know where the data will be stored, we know how much storage
capacity we require for storing the data. And finally
we need to configure what kind of access do we give
the application for this storage. So we're
going to define access modes,
which is a list actually, and we're going to define,
read write once, or we
can define read write many. So depending on
what type of access your application needs to the storage,
whether it needs to write multiple times, whether it only needs a
read only access, et cetera, you can define the access modes right
here. And that will be actually the basic configuration of
a persistent volume and we can
save and apply.
So data PV was created and we can actually get
or list all the persistent volumes using get pv
command. And as you see, the status of this persistent
volume is available, meaning it is not being used
by any application yet, or in other words,
it hasn't been claimed yet.
So now let's go ahead and create a persistent volume claim
that will basically claim the storage that this persistent
volume defines. So I'm going to
create myappBC
YamL and again referencing
the documentation persistent
volume claim kind. And let's say we are configuring
this for a MySQL database pod. So let's
call it MySql data Pvc.
And then we have the specification for the volume claim. First of all,
we want to define how much storage do we want
to claim. Again, remember, persistent volumes and persistent volume
claims are created separately, so we don't know how
many volumes or what kind of volumes are available
in a cluster. Also, we don't care because we are creating a claim
that will automatically find the right storage
or right persistent volume with the right storage to
claim. So basically we define our wishes
for the storage in the volume claim specification
and let it find the matching volume available
in a cluster. The first thing we want to define is
how much storage do we actually need for the application? And we
can define that using resources requests.
So we are requesting storage
of let's say 5gb,
that's how much our application that will use
these volume claim will need. And we also define what type
of access our application needs, again using access
modes.
And let's say our application needs read
write many access, so let's save it.
And now when I apply this
volume claim,
I will expect that it will find a
matching persistent volume that is available in the cluster
and claim that. So let's apply.
And if I check get persistent volume claim
first, we see its details, and if I do
get pv, you see that status changed from
available to bound as well as the
PVC state is bound. And that means that PVC
was created and it was able to find a matching
persistent volume in the cluster. And once it
found it, those two were actually bound together.
And that means that this persistent volume is not available
for any other claim. Now until the persistent
volume claim releases it again. And note that the
persistent volume has a capacity of 10gb of
storage. However, our claim only required
5gb of storage, so the specification
doesn't have to 100% match the persistent volume
configuration. It has to be the best match among
many persistent volumes.
Now we have those two available, and that means we can actually
create our application with the volume claim so that
it can use the storage defined by the persistent volume.
So I'm going to create actually a MySQL deployment yaml
file and paste in a super simple
deployment configuration. Nothing crazy here.
And also we're creating a deployment, not a stateful set, even though it's an application,
because we're just running one replica of the database.
So that's fine. Now with this configuration there is no volume
configured, so let's actually do that. First of all,
you learn that volumes are configured for a pod.
So pod is basically taking the volume
from the volume claim, and that means we define this configuration
on a pod level. So in the specification of
the pod, under the containers, we're going to specify volumes
attribute, and volumes attribute is a list because we can
provide multiple volumes to a pod for different purposes.
So one of them could be for database data, another one
could be for configuration data, et cetera. And the volumes
configuration is pretty easy. We have the name of the volume which we decide
what it's going to be, let's call it DB data.
And here we're going to reference the persistent volume claim.
Again, you can check the syntax in the documentation for
how to reference it. So the attribute is persistent
volume claim,
and under that we have claim name
and this is going to be the name that we gave our persistent volume
claim component, and it's called MySQL
data PvC.
That's what we called it, and that's going to be enough to reference
the volume claim inside the pod. However, once we have
the volume attached to the pod, we actually need to use it
in our application. And the application is running in a container,
so we have to pass that volume to the container.
Again, if we have multiple containers in the pod, you can actually decide
which containers or which applications gets that
volume right. You may just want to give it to the main application,
but not share that volume with the sidecar or
init containers. So to pass the volume configuration to
the container, we have an attribute called volume mounts.
Let's actually give us a space here.
And volume mounts is also an array
because you may have multiple volumes in your pod
and you can pass multiple of those volumes to each container.
And this is also a pretty easy configuration. We have the name
which has to reference one of these volumes here and
the second attribute which is mount path.
And that basically means when we take that storage,
whatever and wherever it is configured, we want to
mount it into the container because the application inside the container
will be the one writing to that storage, right. So we
have to make a copy of that location inside
the container at a certain path, and that's
the mount path. Right. Where are we mounting it? Into the container's
file system. And this could be again any location
you want. In our case, let's define Varlebysql
because that's where the mySQl data is configured and
that's it. It's actually pretty easy to configure volumes in
a pod because you did all the configuration inside the volume
claim and persistent volume itself. So here
you're just referencing that storage.
And as you see, when you're creating pods
or when developers are creating pods and deployments,
they may not even know what kind of storage is configured
behind this volume claim. They may only be interested in the
capacity, so they want 10gb of storage for their database
data and that's it, and that's all they care about. So we have
to configure a root password here as
an environment variable. So let's add env
attribute name will be name of
the environment variable and
let's set it to some hard coded value like my password,
and let's save it.
I'm going to apply and let's see that the pod is
running. Let's check again. We can
also do describe and
make sure that the volumes configuration is correct
here. And we can also enter the pod
using exec command and
check that the mount path was actually created.
And as you see the path was created, it actually
has some data that MySQL application in the container
automatically generates. And this means whatever MySQL generated
right here will be also persisted in the storage backend that we
configured, which in our case is a local storage on the host path,
which we defined to be on the host at
Mount datapath.
Now where can we actually find that actual physical storage for
the host path or on which node is it
actually configured? If we do describe pod again,
we will see which worker node it is actually running on.
So our pod started on worker node one.
So if we ssh to worker one and
check mount data
location here, you will see that what MySQl application
generated inside the container has already been saved
right here. So now when the MySQL container and pod
get removed and all the data inside the container will be
gone, this data will still be persisted on worker one.
So when we restart the pod on worker one,
it will synchronize again the location from here,
from here to its mount path inside the container,
and we'll be able to read in all this data. So that's how
the persistence with host path actually works. However, you probably
already see the disadvantage, which is that the data is
specifically on one worker node. So if the pod
gets scheduled on worker two, for example, the data will not
be here, right? But as I
said, host path is actually great for testing volumes
or for configuring things that are not so important as the
database data. For example, and therefore as the
official Kubernetes documentation also says, you shouldn't
be using hostbeth for the database services,
especially in a production environment. And great thing about having
all these abstractions for volume, like persistent volume
and persistent volume claim and then referencing that claim
in the pod is that whenever you change a storage
type, for example, you change your database storage from host
path to a remote storage. The only thing you will need to update
is persistent volume resource. Everything else will
actually stay the same. The pod will reference the same persistent volume which will
now reference a different data storage in the background.
So you will not have to update your deployments or pods
that we deployed next to the main application needs to
access the log files that application creates in order to
be able to collect them and send them to an external
logging service. And right now it can't because the
main application container has its own file
system and the sidecar container has its
own file system and they cannot access each other's
file systems, so they need a shared location which
both containers can access. However, we don't really care
persisting this log data because the log sidecar
is anyways sending it to some remote log service.
And even if we lose some log data,
let's say we don't really care about that. So basically
in this case, we need to configure a storage that
these two containers can share, but it doesn't have
to be a persistent and permanent
storage. Another use case for this will be if the sidecar container
is updating the application cache, we would need to give
the main application and sidecar applications access
to the same shared storage where the application cache
is stored. And for that we actually have a volume type
called empty deer or empty directory.
And empty directory volume is perfect for multicontainer
pods. The empty Deere volume will only be accessible for
the pod and its containers, and can be shared among its containers.
And as the name suggests, the empty deer volume will be empty whenever
pod restarts. So it always starts from the
scratch, and then containers can update the data inside.
And configuring that is also very easy. Let's see how it works.
First of all, for empty deer volume type, we do not
need a persistent volume or persistent volume claim components.
We can define that directly into the pod, because again,
it's not a persistent volume, it's just used to share data
among the containers. However, defining them
in the pod is actually pretty much the same. Let's give us some
space here and on the same level as containers,
we're going to define volumes again and
let's give it a name, call it lock data.
And the last time when we referenced persistent
volume claim, we had a persistent volume claim attribute here.
For empty deer, we have an empty deer attribute,
and the only configuration we need for empty deer attribute
is empty curly braces. That's it.
So that configures a volume for the pod. And now we can
pass that volume to the containers. And the same way we're
going to define volume mounts,
the name will reference the volume name defined here,
and we have the same mount path attribute. And let's
say this is going to be on Varlock
path inside the container and we
can grab that exact configuration and configure
it for the sidecar container. So basically what
this does is it creates a shared volume for both containers
and then it mounts that shared volume into each
container at this path. So this path is actually inside
the container. And as I said, the other containers
cannot access file system of another container.
However, what can happen now is that whenever main application writes
something to this location, it will get propagated to this
shared volume of MTDR type. And then whatever gets written
here gets propagated back to another container
and will be visible inside here. So a sitecore
container can now read the data that main application
wrote to this location. And also note that the mount
path can be totally different on
each container. It doesn't have to be the same as long as they are
referencing the same empty deer volume. And let's
actually test that this works.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to simulate the NginX container
writing some data into that location
like this. So basically every 5 seconds
it writes this line into Varlog
myapp log file. And with these two greater than signs
it basically just appends every line to that log file.
And on the other hand, let's say we want to access whatever
main application has written here inside the sidecar
application.
So for that, let's actually delete this and
tail the file contents of MyApp log.
Now inside the sidecar container, this will be actually at this
path because that's where we're mounting it.
And the name of the file will be
Myapp log. So let's see that in action.
I'm going to save this. Okay, so the Internet's deployment
pod is running. Let's now actually check the logs to see that
the sitecar container was able to access the log file
that the main application has written into.
So logs
and we have to specify the container name, which is
log sitecar. And as you
see, we have the date of
the log. Then we have info and some app data, which is
exactly what the main application is logging every 5 seconds
and which the sidecar application was able
to access and then print out. That's how you
can use a shared storage location among containers
that is running in a cluster needs to connect to
a database and some other services. Now all of
these services need credentials to connect to like username
and password or secret token. So developers ask
you, what is the best way to create and pass an
external configuration with credentials to
the applications in Kubernetes? And that's where secret
and config map resources come in. So let's
see how this works. First, as you learned, secret is
for sensitive configuration data, while configmap is for
regular configuration data. Now this configuration data
from configmap or secret can be passed to
the applications in the pod in two different ways,
either as individual values using environment variables,
or as configuration files using volumes.
And we will see examples of both of these ways in the next
demo section.
Config map and secret components. And then
we're going to pass the data inside to the pod
using environment variables.
And for that I'm actually going to create a folder and I'm
going to call this external config.
And let's create my config map.
Yaml first and let's call it myappconfig.
And the specification is actually super simple. We define
data attribute, and under the data attribute we have
a list of key value pairs which can specify any
service endpoints that your application needs to connect to,
for example or any other type of configuration for your application.
And in our case, let's say we want to specify just a database
endpoint. Let's call it DB host,
which is the key. The syntax for the key can be anything,
it could be lowercase, uppercase, doesn't really matter, that's up to you to
decide and the actual value. And let's say in our case that's Mysql
service and that's our config map. As simple as that.
So let's save it.
And as a next step, let's create my secret.
So that's going to be my app secret.
And again, super simple configuration.
First we need a type because we have different types of
secrets in kubernetes. One of them we already saw
was service account type. And this one is basically
a general type that you can use for secret configuration.
So type opaque. And then we have the same
data attribute, which again
is a list of key value pairs with
arbitrary values. However,
note that the value has to be base 64 encoded.
We can't just put in plain text
here, right? So let's define
password and username. And I'm going to switch to another
terminal and let's create a base 64 encoded
text here, which is super simple. You just do echo
and then n, which is very important for
considering the end of the line and then your
text that you want to encode, right? So for example,
this could be my user and then
my base 64 encoded like this and
my password like this.
So that's the base 64 encoded value. So I'm going to copy that,
paste it in here, same for the password
and that's it. Let's save it. So we have our
config map and secret. Now we can actually apply that
to apply multiple files at once. You can actually just specify
the current directory so everything in that directory will be applied,
which in our case we just have two files in this directory.
So let's execute. And there you go.
So now that we have these two components,
let's create a deployment that uses values
from the secret and config map. Again,
I'm going to create MyApp deployment Yaml
and I'm going to paste in a base deployment
configuration. Alternatively, you can also generate
this from Kubectl create deployment command as you
already learned, and then basically just open it and
edit it. So this is a base configuration.
Now we need to use the values from secret
and config map in this application and
we're going to reference them using environment variables.
You already learned how to define environment variables on a
pod, so this is going to be the same concept. We have
the name of the environment variable, which we can decide what it's going to be.
Let's call this MysQl user and
the value either hard coded like my user,
or if we are referencing and using that value from a
secret, then we're going to do value from
and use a secret key
reference. So that's the attribute name.
And inside that secret key reference we have the name of
the secret my
app secret and the key of the value
that we want to get from the secret. And we called it
username. So whatever we defined as a value of
username inside my app secret will be substituted
right here as a value for MysQl user
environment variable. And let's do the same
for password.
Let's call the environment variable mysql pwd value
from and actually I can just copy this and
it's the same secret but key name is password.
And we have one more value want to use here
from config map. So again,
name of the environment variable, let's call this MySQl server
value from because
we are referencing another component instead of defining it
here directly and instead of secrets key ref it's
going to be config map key reference
and we have the same name attribute,
myapp config, that's what
we called it. And key inside the config map
which is Db underscore host. Now very
important to note here, you don't have to memorize the
syntax for each such configuration by heart
because you can always look them up in a documentation.
You will probably memorize and learn by heart the configuration
for the most common things that you do all the time.
But this kind of syntax you can always just check in the documentation. So this
configures our application with the environment variables
that reference data from secret and config map
components. Now let's also add a command here to make
sure that the values are actually being set and
let's just simply print them out. So I'm going to do command
sh shell and
I'm simply going to do print env and basically just
print the values of all these environment
variables. So this is going to simply print them out.
And as you already know, containers are
there to execute specific tasks and when the task is done,
container will exit and we don't want that. So let's add
a sleep command here so that container stays running for
a bit and let's save it and
apply. Note that the
secret and config map that you're referencing in your deployment
configuration need to already exist in the cluster
before you create the deployment. Otherwise you will get an error
that it can't find them.
And kubectl get pod and we should see our application
is running, which is this one right here.
And now let's actually log the
pod to see the environment variable values.
So we have my user, my PWD MySQl service.
So the values of secret and config map
components were successfully extracted
and passed over to our pod as
environment variables. And this will actually be a very
common use case for developers to configure
some external configuration using config map and secret and
then use that in the deployment configuration
configuration is actually not just a piece of data like
username or password or some secret token, but rather
a whole configuration file. For example, for a
MySQl application you may want to define
an external configuration file with lots of data inside,
right? Or you may want to pass in a configuration file
to your application that contains some credentials
as well. So passing those as individual values
like these will not be an option here. So the
question is how can we create configuration files for
applications and then pass them to the pod configuration?
Well, we can do that also using config map and secret.
Let's see how it works.
Using config map and secret we can actually
create files instead of just defining key value pairs.
So I'm going to create my config map file yaml
and again, same configuration
and same data attribute. Now instead of
defining key value pairs here, I'm going to define
name of the file, let's call it Mysql conf.
So that's going to be the key name, so to say.
And as a value I'm going to define the
whole file. And the syntax for that in Yaml is
the pipe. So basically pipe will let you
define a multiline string. So basically this
will give us the same key value pair but as a
file with the name of the file as key and the contents of the
file as the value. And here you can define the
MySQl configuration as you normally
would like this. And this is actually a valid MySQl
configuration. And also know that you can define
multiple such files. So you can have
another file conf and
again have another file contents. So you can have
a list of files here and let's save it.
And same way you can define secret
file, let's call it secret
file as well, the same data attribute,
secret file as
a name and the file contents.
And again the contents of the file has to
be base 64 encoded. So again I'm going to switch
here. And we actually have installation
files here. So you can actually base 64, encode the
whole file and then set its
value right here. And we can try to
do that. And let's trim all those new lines first
like this, so we can copy and
that's going to be the secret file content. Let's save
it. And now let's see how
we can reference those configuration files inside the
pod specification.
So I'm going to create a new pod definition, let's call this myapp
deployment file.
And again I'm going to copy in the file and this is
going to simulate a MySQL database pod because we created MySQL
configuration which we want to pass in as a configuration and we're
using just simple busybox image for that. So in order to
configure files defined in configmap
and secret as configuration files in your pod,
we're going to use volumes. So config map
and secret are actually types of volumes. They're not persistent
volume types, but they are actually one of the volume types
that lets you define inside config map or secret
into the containers. And we already learned
how volume configuration
is defined. So we have volumes in the pod
specification. We have name
of the volume, let's call this db config.
And the second attribute of the volume is always the
type of the volume, right? We already saw empty deer
and persistent volume claim. In our case we have config map
and of course we need name of that config
map, which we called MySQL config file.
And we also have to reference the secret,
let's call it db secret. And type
is secret and this one actually has secret
name as an attribute and
MySQL secret file.
Again, you can look up the syntax for this and you don't
have to remember exactly the attribute names,
but it's important to remember that when you define volumes,
you first define them on a pod level, and then for
each volume you create or you give it a name and the type
of the volume with its specification, and after that you
mount that volume into the container using
volume mounts attribute, referencing the
name of the volume and mount path.
And let's say the configuration file from
here goes to dbconfig
or whatever the default MySQL configuration
is. You can also define that instead. And we
have another volume
mount in the same container which
we can mount into another location,
Mysql dB secret.
So these two are the attributes always used in volume mounts.
And we have third attribute here which defines whether
the data that we mount here is read only or
not. By default it's not read only, so the application can
actually make changes to whatever we pass here.
However, let's say this is a secret file that is not supposed to
be changed or adjusted. So to make sure the
application doesn't accidentally, somehow rewrite the data,
we're going to set it to read only. True.
And finally, to make sure everything
was configured correctly, let's just print out
the file contents and
for that I'm simply going to cat
both of the file contents.
And again, let's sleep for 20 seconds.
So that's the configuration for creating
and then passing configuration files instead of configuration
values from config map and secret to the application.
Now there's one important thing here to understand
that the mount path is actually a folder name,
right? So we want to reference the files or we want
to actually print out the file contents inside
that folder name. The way it works is that any
files defined in a config map will
be actually mounted into this folder. So if
we had multiple files or key value attributes defined
in the config map, we would have all of those files actually
in this folder. And same goes for a secret.
And the files will be named the same as we name them in
the config map definition. And that means to
print the file we're going to do dbconfig
MySql conf and the secret file name is
secret file because that's how
we named it. So again, the files will be stored in this
directory in the mount path with a name that we define
as the key inside config map or secret configuration.
So let's save this. And now that we have all the
files ready, let's actually apply them one by one.
First let's create the my config file,
let's create the secret,
and finally let's apply the deployment.
So let's check that our pod is running. And there you go.
And let's log it to
see that files were configured correctly.
Execute. And there you go. So first of
all, we have the config map file contents, which was
these five lines here, and this is actually the secret
file install shell
script actually that we configured as a
value in the secret. So they were passed as
configuration files in the pod and we were able to
see the print out the contents.
And finally, another very important thing to
remember about external configuration with
config maps and secret in Kubernetes is that whenever we
update the contents of config map or a
secret, the pods that reference this config map
or secret data do not automatically get
the up to date information. They will still see the
old configuration. So in order to make the changes
effective, to basically reload the configuration in the pod, we will
have to restart the pod. So to see that, let's say
we changed our secret file
configuration and
let's say we defined it to be some other value,
right? This is a new secret
file database
and we basically updated the existing secret.
Now as you see, the pod doesn't get restarted as
well as it doesn't get the changes in the secret data automatically.
For that we would have to restart all the pods that reference that
secret or config map. Now one way to restart the pods
is basically doing Kubectl delete and the pod name. However,
if you have multiple pod replicas and if you want to restart all of
them, to get the new secret or config map configuration,
you can use command called Kubectl rollout
restart. So Kubectl rollout
restart allows you to restart
deployment or stateful set and all its pods.
So in our case, deployment name is MyDB and
if I execute this it will terminate the old pod
and start a new one again. If you had ten replicas
of MyDB deployment, all the pods will be
restarted one by one. And you can also check the
status of your rollout restart
using rollout status. In this case
you see that it was successfully rolled out, so it's completed.
And now let's check the logs
again.
It and as you see we got the new secret
data inside the pod.
As a Kubernetes administrator you check regularly whether
developers are adhering to the best practice
standards and configuring workloads correctly.
So as one of those best practices, you want to check
whether they have defined resource requests and limits for
their workloads. So first let's understand what resource
requests and limits are in Kubernetes, and then
let's see how to use them in the application configuration
so that when you see workloads configured without them,
you can send the developers a corrected YaML file example
to use as a sample and also explain
to them how they can define how much resources their
pods may require and explain to them how it all works.
Some applications may need more cpu and memory resources
than others, so to make sure that your application container has
enough resources when it starts inside the pod,
you should define resource requests for each of your
containers.
And with this defined, your containers will have enough resources
to consume. But what if while the container is
running, it actually needs more than what it
requested in resources? So what if it goes over
limits? So to say, for example, this can happen if one application gets
too much data that it needs to load into memory,
or application has a bug inside with some infinite loop
and starts consuming all the cpu available on that node.
In this case, one single container will actually start consuming
more than the requested resources,
and it can take all the cpu or memory of that node.
So other pods running on the same node will not
have enough resources, so they must be rescheduled.
Of course, you want to avoid such situations where one container
consumes all the resources on the node, and you can do
that by setting resource limits for each container
in addition to resource requests.
Understand how resource requests and limits work and
why you should use them in your pod configuration.
Let's actually see their usage in practice. And to showcase that,
let's actually reuse our NgINX deployment example
with the sidecar container, and I'm going to create a new definition
file for that. So we have the old copy unchanged,
and let's call it NgInx deployment with resources
Yaml. And we're going to define resource requests
and limits on both containers inside the pod.
So the first thing you need to decide is how much resources your applications
are going to need. In most cases, you may have applications that
just require an average amount of resources
for cpu and ram, but you may have applications that
are more cpu intensive. Or maybe you have a memory database
like redis that obviously needs more memory space, right? And for them
you would adjust the values and give them more cpu resources
or more memory resources. So the main thing to understand here
is that not all applications need the same amount of
resources. And when they need significantly more or
significantly less resources, it's always good to explicitly
define them. So in our case, let's say that my app, the main
web server application that runs with Nginx image
let's say just needs an average amount of resources
and we're going to define them in the container definition using
resources attribute. And then we have requests and limits.
Again, request is what you think your application will
need to fulfill its job. So let's say we
are expecting a memory usage of 64
mi and cpu of
250 m. So that's the expected
usage. However, some applications have spikes
and in that case they may actually require a little bit
more resources. And again, to limit that
maximum resource consumption, we are going to define
limits memory, and let's say we
allow twice as much resources
and maximum for both cpu and memory
like this. And the same way we're going to configure another container
and we can actually copy this whole thing. And our
logging sidecar application is much less cpu
intensive so it doesn't actually require too much processing power
to do its job. But let's say it stores a bunch of
logs in the memory first before it sends them to an
external logging service. So it requires more memory
resources. And if we know that about our application, we can
adjust it here so we can decide to give it 100
m of cpu and 120
mi for memory. And again, let's allow
twice as much resources as a maximum limit.
So this is going to be 256 and 200.
And let's also change the name because we already
have a MyApp deployment in the cluster.
And let's actually apply our configuration.
And there you go, we have MyApp resources pod
running with the resource requirements explicitly set.
Now if you had hundreds of deployments in the cluster and
you wanted to check which pods have resource requirements
explicitly defined, how would you actually list
all this data? So we need a command that basically gives us
a list of all the pods running in the cluster and next
to it show us whether they have resource limits defined or
not. And if they do, how much are those resource requirements?
And that's going to be a very useful command to check
that. Developers, for example, are deploying applications
with the correct configuration. So let's see how we
can get that output. And we're going
to get that output using a JSON path output
type, which as you remember, lets us pick
specific values from the whole configuration
using JSON path expressions. So let's do kubectl,
get pod and then JSON path with
an expression. So first of all,
we want to iterate through all the pods. So we're going to define a range
here of all the items like
this. You already learned that. And for each item we're going
to print out the name, and next to
the name of the pod we're going to print out the resources
configured, which is in spec
specification containers. And for pods
that have multiple containers, we want that resource definition for each container.
So we're going to do all containers resources,
and we want to separate each pod with a new line like
this. So that's an expression that will give us a list of pods with
the resource configurations. And there you
go. We have five pods in this namespace, and for each
pod we see whether they have a resource definition or not.
So for some of them it is empty. And if you see two
empty curly braces, it means this pod has two containers
and none of them have defined resources.
And then we have ingress Nginx controller that
has resource request defined and it's resource configuration for
both containers.
Now an interesting note here is that when a node
runs out of resources and has to evict
one of the pods, it will actually evict the pods first
that have no explicit resource definition.
So that's basically how resource requests and limits work
in Kubernetes, and why it is a good idea
to always define them for the containers in your
pods, as well as a command to inspect the whole cluster.
For pods with no resource definitions,
they have an application that runs some data and
cpu intensive process. So they want to
run pods belonging to this service on two dedicated
nodes in the cluster where no other pods will run.
So they will get all the resources. Plus they want
to make sure only one pod replica of the same application runs
on the same node. One of the developers also asks,
how is it that no pods get scheduled on the master node?
Because it's also part of the cluster nodes, right? And whether
is it possible to schedule a regular pod on a master node
as well? So you go ahead to find out all this
information.
Now, in Kubernetes we know that pods are automatically scheduled
on one of the available worker nodes.
Which node pod gets scheduled on is selected
by the scheduler. And that's great because the scheduler has an
intelligent way of deciding which node has the
most capacity and is least busy to run a
new pod process. But in some cases we may want to
decide ourselves where the pod gets scheduled.
So basically we can tell the scheduler, don't choose
just any worker node for this pod, schedule it
on this specific node, and we do that using an attribute
called node name, and the value will be.