Happens, Kubeadm generates a configuration for Kubelet
and puts it in this location as well as
generates environment file and then starts
the Kubelet service. So that means if we do
service Kubelet status
again. Now you see that Kubelet is
in an active running state and here you
see the logs of Kubelet starting up. So after
certificates get generated, the Kubeconfig files are ready to
make it possible for applications to talk to API server as well
as Kubelet starts. Kubeadm will create the
manifest files so that static pods can be created
which will be scheduled by Kubelet and they will use Kubeconfig
files with the certificate information to talk
to each other or talk to the API server.
So that is the next step. And those manifest files get
generated and put into this manifests folder.
And here you see the manifests of those components.
Now we will learn the syntax and how to write Kubernetes manifest
files in detail in the later section of this course.
So it's totally fine if you don't understand the contents and the syntax
of these manifest files right now, but we're going to take a
quick look at them to see some interesting information. And if
we check one of those manifest files,
for example for API server, I'll send
it to less and
we need pseudo because again this folder is accessible
for root user only. And there you go, you see
that it's actually just a regular Kubernetes
pod definition. We have kind pod here with the metadata
and labels and specification.
We're Kube API server. This is the image for Kube
API server with the version. So this application starts
with all of these configuration parameters.
And this is a very interesting and important thing
for Kubernetes administrators because this is a
way to know and check basically
how your API server is configured. So what
values are set for different parameters and also a place
where you can override or adjust some of these
values. Some of the parameters here are for
pointing to the certificate locations, right?
So this is the API server's server certificates
and these are passed in to the Kube API server
application using these parameters.
We also have pointer to the client certificates
for connecting to eTCD right here.
Right. And this is the location where we actually sew those certificates
as well as an endpoint of Etsyd server.
This is the port where ETCD server will run and be
accessible. We also have Kubelet certificate locations and
key file location and so on. So again,
for troubleshooting or changing different parameters for how
your API server runs. This is basically how you
can override them and change them. And what will happen is
if you change something or adjust something in this configuration
and then save that file, Kubelet will actually see
that a change has been made inside this manifests
folder because it watches for any changes inside that and
it will restart the pod with those changes.
Let's also check ETCD YamL, which is
again same thing, it's a pod kind and we are starting
an Etsyd application with bunch of parameters.
Again, the CA certificate, the service certificate of
Etsyd, as well as configuration for peers.
So basically if we had more than one eTCD in the cluster
for high availability on other master nodes, for example,
then we would have an ECD cluster and this will be configuration
for those ECD pods,
basically talking to each other and connecting to each other as
peers. And we also have a location where the
data is actually saved, which is varleep
etc inside the pod. And the same way you can check
the scheduler and controller manager manifest
files after the manifest creation. We also have some other
configuration setups here. And at the end of
all this configuration you also see a phase
called add ons. So basically two additional
applications get deployed inside the cluster,
not as static pods, but rather as add ons.
So basically these are added as regular
pods because the control plane pods are already running,
so they can actually already take over scheduling
the pods. One of them is Kubeproxy, which as
we know, again we need on each node. So Kubeproxy
needs to be on master node as well. And another one is core DNS,
which is an application that we're going to go into more
detail in one of the later lectures.
But as you see here, those two get also automatically
deployed in the cluster when we initiate it with Kubeadm.
So we saw what got created, what got generated. We saw
the Kubernetes folder
where the configuration files as well as manifest files and certificates
are located. And this is basically where you can check how
your control plane components are configured. And we also saw that
Kubelet has its own separate configuration location,
which is Kubelet.
We can also check that as well.
And again, it's a protected directory, so we need
pseudo. And this means that if you want to
check the configuration of Kubelet itself and
check Kubelet's certificates, et cetera,
this is basically where everything is
configured in a different directory,
right? Again, because Kubelet runs as a process directly,
not as a pod. So in the PKI folder
we have the server certificates of Kubelet because API server
will connect to it as a client as well as a
client certificate for connecting to the API server
and the main configuration which again gets generated
by the Kubeadm which is config Yaml
here and this is what's configured inside.
And one of the things I already mentioned is the static
pod path which by default is configured
for Kubelet at this location. So that's
basically the behind the scenes of cluster
initiation as well as how the master components
start and how they are configured and where you can
find and change all this configuration as a Kubernetes
administrator. Now we saw all these folders
that were created and all the configuration files,
but how do we actually see those pods
that are running in the cluster or how do we check the cluster
status and see what's running inside? How do we
connect to the cluster to get all this information? Because right now we
don't see anything about the cluster itself. And that's going to be our
topic for the next lecture.
How do we access the cluster once it's configured?
As we already saw, accessing the Kubernetes cluster,
which basically means accessing the Kube API server
which is the entry point to the cluster, we need certificates
and we saw that Kubeadm generated client
certificate that we can use to administer the cluster.
And we also saw that a Kubeconfig file was created that
has the information about the address of the API server.
So basically where we're connecting to the cluster as well as
that admin user's certificate and
private key. So that's the file we're going to use to
connect to the cluster. And you also learned that
Kubernetes has a client command line tool called Kubectl
which allows us to issue commands to the Kubernetes
cluster. So Kubectl tool will give us
commands to connect to the cluster and the kubeconfig for the
admin user will allow us to then authenticate
with the cluster. So let's see how that works.
So the Kubectl command to get information about
cluster nodes, for example, is Kubectl get node. Now if
I execute this, you see that we get no proper
output because it doesn't know where the cluster is,
right? Where is the API server of the cluster
that we want to get the nodes from. So that's one
thing that we need to specify. So that's the message we see here.
And also we need to pass those certificates to
authenticate with it. And to provide all that we're going to pass
in the Kubeconfig file we want to use. So Kubeconfig
and the location of the
admin conf file. However this
is only accessible to root user. So we're going to do
pseudo here. Now let's execute this command. And there
you go, you see that we connected to the cluster as
well as authenticated with it using this
configuration file. We're going to come back to the output of
this later. Now let's actually learn more
about this Kubeconfig file and let's see how the
contents of this file actually looks like.
So I'm going to copy that and we're going to simply see the contents
of this file. And again we
need pseudo permission. And there
you go, and I'm going to copy this contents.
So this is how the Kubeconfig file contents
actually look like. As you see, this is a Kubernetes
manifest file. We have kind
which is config and we have all this data here.
First of all we have list of clusters and this is
our cluster that we actually have created.
And this is the endpoint or address of
the Kube API server. And if we check this
IP address here 172 ending with 88,
go back. That's actually the private IP
address of our master node. So that's where the Kube API
server is accessible for other applications
within that VPC or private network.
And on that machine the API server is running
on this port. Then we have the certificate authority
data and this is actually the self signed CA
that Kubeadm generates for the cluster.
So this is the contents of the CA certificate
file. So client has to include that CA in the request.
So that's basically our cluster. And then we have
the users, again we have one user,
in this case it was called Kubernetes admin. That's our admin
user and it has client certificate
and client key. So these are basically the client
certificate that was created for the admin and it was
directly put in here because we don't need it anywhere
else. As well as the controller, manager and
scheduler and Kubelet, they have their client certificates
directly in those kubeconfig files. That's why you don't see them
actually here. So client certificate, the CA certificate and the
endpoint of the API server. This is everything that Kubectl
basically needs in order to connect to this cluster and
authenticate with it using these certificates. And finally
you also see an attribute called contexts here
with a current context for the Kubectl that says
connect to the cluster called kubernetes which is defined here.
So this cluster using a user called kubeadm
which is defined right here. So that's basically what a context
says. So if we had multiple clusters and multiple users
here that we connect to using the same Kubectl
tool, we could switch between those clusters and
users using those contexts. But we're going to see
context in practice in one of the later lectures
in detail. So here, just know that we're using context
to choose one of the clusters we want to connect to from the
clusters list using one of the users from
the user's list like this.
So that's basically how any other Kubeconfig
file will look like with just different client certificate
data and username here.
Now as I mentioned, as an administrator you're going to
be working with Kubectl a lot. So you're going to be basically
checking anything and creating and configuring anything in the
cluster using this Kubectl tool. So having
to specify a kubeconfig file on every
single Kubectl command, as well as having to execute
it with pseudo is kind of annoying and
very repetitive. So how can we actually
avoid that? Now there are two alternatives for that. The first one
is setting the Kubeconfig file location
as an environment variable. Now in our case, because this is
a protected folder only accessible for root,
let's switch to the root user like
this and set the environment variable
here which is called kubeconfig.
And this will be pointing to the admin
confile. And now I can execute the
Kubectl without specifying the kubeconfig file.
And this is a nice alternative. However this of
course will only work in the current session and also every time I
reconnect to the machine I'll have to
set this environment variable so it's not persistent. So as
a better alternative we can take that kubeconfig
file and put it in a default location where Kubectl
will actually look for it, and that is in the
user's home directory,
Kubefolder. So that's
the default folder where Kubectl will look for the configuration file.
However we don't have this folder, so let's actually
create it and
let's just copy the admin config file into cube
folder and it should be called config as
a default execute.
And now if I check this,
so I have my config file here. However it is
owned by the root user. So we have to actually make Ubuntu
make our own user an owner of this.
So let's see.
So if I do Idu, this will give
me the id of the current user. And if I
print the id of the group, the current
group, it's also 1000.
Using the root user or pseudo privilege we can actually
make our current user and current group
owner of that file.
Let's execute check again.
And there you go. Instead of root we now have Ubuntu user,
Ubuntu group owning that file. Now we don't have to
use pseudo anymore and we have our
Kubeconfig file in the default location. So if
I do Kubectl get node now with Ubuntu user,
there you go, we get the same result and now
it's persistent. So if we log out and log into the master node
we will still get the same result.
Concepts of kubernetes, which is namespaces,
which we will be using a lot in the upcoming lectures.
First of all, what is a namespace in Kubernetes? In Kubernetes
cluster you can organize resources in namespaces,
so you can have multiple namespaces in a cluster. You can think of
a namespace as a virtual cluster inside of a Kubernetes
cluster. Now when you create a cluster,
by default, Kubernetes gives you namespaces out
of the box. So in the command line if I type Kubectl get namespaces,
I see the list of those out of the box namespaces that Kubernetes
offers. But of course you can add and create new namespaces
and the way that you can do it is using Kubectl
create namespace command with the name of the namespace
so I can create my namespace.
And if I do Kubectl get namespaces, I see
that in my list. Now another way to create namespaces
is using a namespace configuration file,
which I think is a better way to create namespaces because
you also have a history in your configuration file repository
of what resources you created in a cluster.
Okay, so now we saw what namespaces are and that
you can create new ones and that Kubernetes offers some of them by default.
But the question is what is the need for namespaces?
When should you create them and how you should use them. The first
use case of using or creating your own namespaces is
the following. Imagine you have only default namespace
which is provided by Kubernetes and you create all your
resources in that default namespace. If you have a complex application
that has multiple deployments which create replicas of
many pods, and you have resources like services
and config maps, et cetera, very soon your default namespace
is going to be filled with different components and it will be
really difficult to have an overview of what's in there,
especially if you have multiple users creating stuff inside.
So a better way to use namespaces in this case
is to group resources into namespaces.
So for example, you can have a database namespace where you deploy your
database and all its required resources,
and you can have a monitoring namespace where you deploy
the prometheus and all the stuff that it needs. You can also
have elasticstack namespace where all the elasticsearch,
Kibana, etc. Resources go, and you
can have Nginx ingress resources. So just one way of
logically grouping your resources inside of
the cluster. Now, according to the official
documentation of Kubernetes, you shouldn't
use namespaces if you have smaller projects and
up to ten users. I personally think
that it's always good idea to group your resources
in namespaces because as I said, even if you
have a small project and ten users, you might still
need some additional resources for your application, like logging
system and monitoring system. And even with a
minimum setup, it can already get too much to just
throw everything in a default namespace. Another use case where
you will need to use namespace is if you have multiple teams.
So imagine this scenario. You have two teams that use the
same cluster, and one team deploys an
application which is called MyApp deployment. That's the name of
the deployment they create, and that deployment has its certain
configuration. Now if another team had a deployment
that accidentally had the same name but
a different configuration, and they created that deployment,
or they applied it, they would overwrite the first team's
deployment. And if they're using, for example a
Jenkins or some automated way to deploy that
application or to create that deployment, they wouldn't even know that
they overwrote or disrupted another team's deployment.
So to avoid such kind of conflicts, again, you can use namespaces
so that each team can work in their own namespace
without disrupting the other. Another use case for using
namespaces is let's say you have one cluster and you
want to host both staging and development environment
in the same cluster. And the reason for that is that, for example,
if you're using something like NgInX controller or
Elasticstack used for logging, for example,
you can deploy it in one cluster and use it for both
environments. In that way you don't have to deploy these common
resources twice in two different clusters.
So now the staging can use both resources as well
as the development environment. Another use case
for using namespaces is when you use blue green deployment
for application, which means that in the same cluster you
want to have two different versions of
production. So the one that is active, that is in production
now, and another one that is going to be the next production
version. The versions of the applications in those blue
and green production namespaces will be different,
however, the same as we saw before in staging and development.
These namespaces might need to use the same resources
like again NginX controller or Elasticstack,
and this way again they can both use the common shared
resources without having to set up a separate cluster.
So one more use case for using namespaces is to
limit the resources and access to
namespaces when you're working with multiple teams.
So again, we have a scenario where we have two teams working in the same
cluster and each one of them has their own namespace.
So what you can do in this scenario is that you can give the teams
access to only their namespace, so they can only be able
to create updates, delete resources in their own
namespace, but they can't do anything in the other namespaces.
In this way, you even restrict or even minimize the risk
of one team accidentally interfering with
another team's work. So each one has their own secured
isolated environment. Additional thing that you can do on
a namespace level is limit the resources that each namespace
consumes. Because if you have a cluster with limited resources,
you want to give each team a share of resources for
their application. So if one team, let's say,
consumes too much resources, then other teams will eventually
have much less and their applications may not schedule because the
cluster will run out of the resources. So what you can do is that per
namespace you can define resource quotas that limit how much
cpu ram storage resources one namespace
can use. So I hope walking through these scenarios helped you analyze
in which use cases and how you should use namespaces in your specific
project. There are several characteristics that you should consider before
deciding how to group and how to use namespaces. The first
one is that you can't access most of the resources from another
namespace. So for example, if you have a configuration
map in project a namespace that references the database
service, you can't use that config map in project
B namespace, but instead you will have to create the same config map
that also references the database service. So each
namespace will define, or must define its own
config map, even if it's the same reference. And the same
applies to secret. So for example, if you have credentials
of a shared service, you will have to create that secret in each
namespace where you are going to need that. However,
a resource that you can share across namespaces is
service, and that's what we saw in the previous slide.
So config map in project b namespace references
service that is going to be used eventually in a pod. And the way it
works is that in a config map definition, the database URL
in addition to its name, which is MySQl service, will have namespace
at the end. So using that URL you can actually access
services from other namespaces,
which is a very practical thing. And this is how you
can actually use shared resources like elasticsearch
or Nginx from other namespaces.
And one more characteristic is that we saw that most of the
components resources can be created within a namespace,
but there are some components in Kubernetes, they're not namespaced,
so to say. So basically they live just globally
in the cluster, and you can't isolate them or
put them in a certain namespace. And examples of such resources
are volume or persistent volume and node. So basically when
you create the volume, it's going to be accessible throughout the whole cluster,
because it's not in a namespace. And you can actually list
components, they're not bound to a namespace using
a command. Kubectl API resources namespace
false. And the same way you can also list all the resources
that are bound to a namespace using namespace.
True namespaces
are and how they are used. Let's actually check in our
cluster what namespaces we have and what pods are running in those
namespaces. So first of all, I'm back on my master node where I
have Kubeconfig file already configured in the default
location. So I'm going to execute Kubectl get
namespaces or short NS command,
and this will give me a list of the namespaces that have
been created in my cluster. This is the default namespace
that you can deploy your applications inside.
Then we have Kubenode, lease, Kubelic,
and Kube system namespaces. We're not going to need to
check or add something or do anything with those two namespaces
so we can ignore them and look at those two namespaces.
The default namespace, as I said, is where you can start deploying
your applications. So if I do Kubectl get
pod, which is a command for listing all the
pods running in the cluster, you will see that it
gives me zero results, no resources found in default namespaces.
And that means that by default this command
for listing pods and services, et cetera,
or kubernetes, resources that are living
in namespaces will always use the default namespace.
How do I see pods running in the Kube system namespace?
For that I can specify a namespace with my Kubectl
get Kubernetes resource name command and
name of the namespace. So this will basically
list all the pods running in this specific namespace.
And here are all the control plane pods that
were created as manifests and
deployed as static pods. We have Kube
API server, we have the Kubecontroller manager,
Kube scheduler and ECD. And you
notice that at the end of each of these pods we have
this suffix master. And this
is an indicator that these are static pods, because static pods,
as I mentioned, get a suffix at the end of the name
of the node where they're scheduled on. And also
you saw we had the static pod manifest for them, and as you
see they are in a running state and we have
one container out of one successfully running.
Everything seems great. Now, in addition to those
four control plane components,
we have another one called kubeproxy,
which is not a static pod, it doesn't have a
master suffix, and we also have core DNS
pod, two of them, right, two replicas. And remember,
in the output of Kubeadm init, we had
two atoms that were installed at the end of the
cluster setup. So once the master nodes were up and running,
those two pods were actually scheduled.
Qproxy runs as a regular pod,
as you see it is in the running state, and two replicas
of core DNS pods. And all these pods
are running on the master node. Because we
only have one node in the cluster which
is the master node.
You need to understand how networking works in Kubernetes,
which is a very interesting but also a complex topic.
However, in order to understand networking in kubernetes,
you need to have basic knowledge of networking in
general. So in this lecture we will cover the basic concepts
of networking. How does computer networks work?
How do computers connect to the Internet? What is an
IP address and a port? And so on. We will
learn all of this in this lecture where I will explain all the main
concepts step by step with examples.
So let's get started.
First of all, imagine your home network for your house where
different devices like your computer and laptop and phone are connected
to that network. Such a network is called a lEn
or local area network. So Len is a network
of a bunch of devices connected together in one physical
location. This can be as small as a private house,
len or len of a huge office building or a school
campus with hundreds of devices. And each device on this
network is identified by a unique IP
address where IP stands for Internet protocol.
So devices can talk to each other on the network
using this unique IP address. For example,
if your computer wants to send a printer something to
print, it must know the printer's IP address and send the
information there. This is an example of an IP
address 170 2160
zero. So IP address is basically
a 32 bit value.
One bit is essentially a value of one or zero.
Now we don't need to go into details here, but important to know
that an IP address or IPV four
address is composed of 32 bits.
So basically 32 ones or zeros
here. And what are those dots between them? Well,
every eight bits are grouped into an octet
and each octet can be represented as a decimal
number that we humans can read.
Like this octet here represents 172,
this one represents 16 and so on. So octet
with all zeros, so eight zeros is
just a zero and an octet with
all ones, so eight ones is a number.
255. That means that
IP address value can be any combination between zero,
zero and 255.
255 dot 255 255.
So that's how IP address is made up. But how do
devices know each other's IP addresses? Or how
can they send things to each other? Well, that is a task
of a special device on a local area network called a
switch. So switch sits within the lane and
knows all the IP addresses of all the devices and therefore
helps them communicate with each other within that local
area network. Great. So your laptop can talk to a phone or
a printer in Len using a switch. But what if
you want to talk to a server or some other device
which is not in your len? Like you want to open Facebook
website on your laptop. So you need to connect to and talk
to a Facebook server which is obviously
outside your len or essentially any website which is
hosted on a server outside your len. Does switch
help there too? No. For connecting to outside devices,
there is another special device in a lane called a
router. Router is a network device that
sits between the local area network and the outside network,
which is also called a wide area network or
win. So the router connects devices on local area
network and wide area network, which means the router connects
you to the Internet. Back to our Facebook example, if you
want to open Facebook app on your phone, your phone will send a
request to the router. Then router will send
that request to Facebook server over the Internet,
and the IP address of the router is called a
gateway. So when you hear the term router and network
gateway are basically the same thing.
Now the question is, when a device in LEN
sends a request to another device, how does
it know whether that other device is within the lane or it's
outside the lane in the wide area network?
Well, this is decided based on the IP address of the target
device. Remember, as I said, that every device on land has
a unique IP address? Well, these IP addresses
aren't random. They all belong to the same
range of IP addresses to identify
devices in the same network. And that IP address range
is represented by a concept called subnet
or subnetwork. This is how an IP
address range for a lan can look like.
So the first part here is the IP address,
and that's the starting point of the IP address range.
So that's the first IP address in the range. And the
second one is what's called a subnet mask.
So subnet basically sets the range and
it defines that whatever IP address of a
device starts with 192.1680.
So whenever an IP address starts with this, it belongs
to the lan. If we change the subnet mask value
from 255 dot 255
dot 2550 to
255 dot 2550 zero,
then this will define an IP address range that
starts with 192 168.
So all the IP addresses that starts with these two numbers
belong to the same len. So as you see, the value 255
fixates the IP block or
octet, and the value of zero means
a free range. Why 255 and zero?
Because as you learned, each IP decimal block can
have values from zero to 255,
so anything within that range. So basically,
subnet defines how many bits in the IP
address are fixed, making the rest of them
flexible. So 255 dot 2550
zero means that half of it or 16
bits are fixed in the IP address. This, on the other hand,
means that third of all the bits or 24
bits are fixed in the IP address. So again,
when we're using this as a subnet mask,
it means that those first three octets
or decimal values cannot change. Right? So the
IP addresses of this land here will be
between 192 dot 168
dot zero. So the first three cannot change,
they are fixated and the last one
can change and it could be all the way up to 255.
So your IP addresses will be within those ranges.
And right here we have only half of it fixated.
So your IP addresses of this len will be from
this IP address to 255
255. So within this range.
That's how it works. And as we said, this subnet
mask number basically dictates how many bits
in this 32 bit IP address are fixed. So based
on this logic, there is actually a shorthand way of writing
this, which is also called a cider block and is written
like this. So the same IP address as we have here,
16 or 24, where 16
and 24 represent the number of bits
in the IP address range that are fixed.
Just to recap, with subnet and a starting IP
address, we have a range of IP addresses
that are available in the lane. So every device in
that local area network will get an IP address
from that range. So when we send a request to
an IP address within our lan, the request will
go to the switch and it will forward it to the device within the
land. If the IP address is external, it will go to the
Internet through the router. And that means any
device on your network will need three pieces of data
to communicate with other devices, both within its own network
and to the outside network's devices.
And this is the IP address subnet and
gateway.
Now we said that internally in a lan, we have an IP
address range that a network administrator of a
company or school or in case of
your own house, your Internet provider
chooses, and that each device will get a unique IP
address from that range? And suppose a device
in our land is talking to a device in another land.
Now how do we make sure not every network
administrator selects the same range and that the
IP addresses in our land don't overlap
or aren't the same as someone else's land?
Well, the way it works is that the IP addresses of devices
that belong to a land are not visible to
the outside network or Internet. So when you send a request to
Facebook from your laptop, your laptop's IP address from
the lan range does not arrive at Facebook server.
Instead it's replaced by the IP address of the router.
And this functionality of router is called a network
address translation or net. So basically when a
laptop sends a request, it goes to the router, because router
is the connection to the outside network, right to Internet.
And router will then request that on the device's behalf
from Internet and the response will then be
sent back to the device. And that is a
very important concept and has two main advantages.
One of them is security and protection of devices on the land because
your IP address isn't directly exposed and no one can talk to
it directly. And the second one is that we can reuse
IP address ranges multiple times without conflicting
with each other. So two huge companies can
have the same IP address range within their own
local area network and they will basically not know about
each other. So there will be no conflict. And this is very efficient
because there are a limited number of IP
addresses you get from the IPV
four address range, which is as we saw, four zeros.
And sure there are lots
of combinations between them. However, there are also lots and
lots of devices in the world that need IP
addresses.
Now what if an outside device wants to talk to your lan directly?
Like you have a server that runs your application, so you want
to be able to accept requests from devices outside your
lan. Well, by default this kind of communication will not be allowed
because of a firewall. So what is a firewall?
Firewall is a set of rules that protect a network from
unauthorized access. And you can explicitly
define what kind of communication you want to allow to
your network using firewall rules.
So how does it work? You define which device on your network
with a specific IP address should be accessible.
You can also define which other devices or what
IP addresses specifically can access your
server. Or you can say, I allow any device on the Internet
to talk to my server. And this is usually the case when you're running a
web application because you want everyone to be able to
access your application. So for most servers that are running some
applications, you will need to configure firewall rules to
manage the access configuration.
Now there is one more important thing that you always define
in a firewall rule, and that is which
ports are accessible on the server or
generally on the device that you want to allow access to.
So what is a port?
Every device has a set of ports and ports are
like doors to the same building. You unlock
some doors so the guests or requests can enter and
you keep others locked so no one can enter there.
Or you unlock them only for specific guests,
like a specific IP address that can
enter that door, so to say. So with firewall configuration,
you define which doors of the building or your server.
In this case you want to unlock and for
which guests or for what request. And different applications
and programs that run on the server will start
or listen on different ports,
meaning you can access that application on the device
only on that specific port. And to keep this all
standardized, there are default or standard ports
for many applications. For example, most web
applications start on port 80,
so they are accessible on that port from the browser
when you request the application. That means when you type facebook.com
or google.com in the browser, by default,
this request goes to a machine where Facebook or Google application
is running on port 80. So on those machines,
the firewall was configured to unlock the port
80 to accept browser requests. Other applications,
like databases, also have standard ports. Like a MySQL
database is usually accessible on port 3306,
PostgreSql on port 5432, and so
on. So for every application you need a port to
communicate, and each port is unique on a device.
So you can't have two applications listening on the same
port. If you try to start the second application on the same port,
you will get an error which says port already in use.
So the firewall configuration allows a specific combination of
device, IP address and port to be accessed.
So firewall is like a guard that is standing in front of the building
and checks and verifies who can enter which door.
And that configuration is also called port forwarding
configuration.
Now there is some interesting information that we
see displayed here in the Kube system namespace,
as well as in the Kubectl get node output.
Here we see that we have one master node with a version
that we chose to install, and you see that its
status is not ready. So we have one node,
a master node in a cluster which runs some
of the pods. However, it is in the not ready status.
In addition to that, we also see that in the Kube system namespace
we have two pods that are in a pending
state. These are the core DNS pods.
Now there is actually the same reason behind those two
being in a pending state and master node being in
a not ready status. And the reason
for both of these issues is that we need to install what's
called a pod network in kubernetes.
So we've come to a very interesting topic, which is
what is a pod network and how does networking
actually work in Kubernetes? So in the next lectures
we're going to learn everything about networking in kubernetes.
And once we understand that we're going to install
a networking application or a networking layer
in kubernetes that will fix both
of these issues, I hope you're excited about it.
So let's dive in.
The core concept in networking of Kubernetes is
the networking of pods and containers some
of the questions we will answer is how are pods
created? How does pod networking actually look
like? How do pods communicate with each other on the same node
and how they talk to each other across different nodes in
the cluster. First let's see how networking works within the pods
and then we will see how networking works between the pods.
The smallest unit or component is a pod and not
a container. And considering that pod always contains one
main container, for example you might have a pod with postgres
container or elasticsearch container or your own application.
Some people may be asking why the need for abstracting
the container with a pod if there is anyways just one main
application running inside. So in this video I'm going to
explain to you why having a pod as an abstraction over
container is such an important concept in Kubernetes. I'm going to give you
a comparison between pod and container and I will
show you in which cases you would need to have multiple containers
inside one pod and how these containers then will communicate
with each other. At its core, Kubernetes networking has one
important fundamental concept, which is that every pod has
a unique IP address and that ip address is reachable
from all the other pods in the cluster. So that's the main concept.
Now why is it important and valuable to have this pod component with
its own ip address? You see, one main challenge on distributed infrastructure
with multiple servers is how to allocate ports to
services and applications running on servers without getting conflicts.
Since obviously you can only allocate one port once on a single
host with containers, you would soon face
this challenge because this is how container port mapping works.
Let's take for example a postgresql container where
inside the container the postgres application starts
at port 5432. Now when you start containers
directly on your machine, what you do is you bind your host
port to the application port in the container.
And to see that in practice we can start postgres docker container.
So this is the part where we map or we bind
the port on the host to the port of the application running
inside the docker container. So it doesn't have to be
the same port. I can also give it a completely different one. So let's write
5000 and if I execute this command postgres
container started and if we check here with docker ps,
I will see that port 5000 on the
host machine is mapped to this one here. So now
the application is reachable by the host port.
Now that I have one postgres already running,
I could start another postgres container that will
also run at the same port but bind it on a different port
on my host. So this will work
as well. So if I go here now and say docker
ps, I will see two postgres applications
bound to different ports on the host and
this is how containers work. The problem with this is when
you have hundreds of containers running on your servers,
how can you keep track of what ports are still free on the host
to bind them so soon enough? With this type of port
allocation, it will become difficult to have an overview
and the way Kubernetes solves this problem is by abstracting
the containers using pods where pod is like its
own small machine with its own IP address,
usually with one main container running inside.
For example, you might have a pod where postgres container
is running. When a pod is created on a node,
it gets its own network namespace and a virtual ethernet
connection to connect it to the underlying infrastructure
network. So a pod is a host just like your laptop.
Both have IP addresses and a range of ports they can allocate
to its containers. This means you don't have to worry about port
mappings on the server where pod is running and only
inside the pod itself. But since you anyways usually have just one main
container, or sometimes maybe maximum up to six containers
inside a pod, you won't get conflicts there because you have a pretty
good overview of what containers are running inside. This means
that on one server you can have, for example, ten microservice
applications that all run on port 80 80
inside ten different pods. And you won't have any conflicts
because they all run on self contained isolated
machines which are pods. Another reason why pod
abstraction over container is useful is that you
can easily replace the container runtime in Kubernetes. So for
example, if you replace docker runtime with another container runtime
Kubernetes configuration will stay the same because it's all
on the pod level. It means that Kubernetes isn't tied up to any
particular container runtime implementation. Now as
I mentioned at the beginning, sometimes pod might have
two or more containers inside. This is a case when you need to
run a helper or side application to your main application,
like for example for synchronizing when you
have multiple database pods, or for backing up your application
at certain intervals. So it would have this backup sidecar
container within your application container, or it could
be a scheduler or maybe authentication gateway.
So there are many use cases where you might end
up having more than one containers inside a pod.
Now the question is, how do these containers communicate
with each other inside the pod? Remember, pod is an isolated
virtual host with its own network namespace,
and containers inside all run in this network
namespace. This means that containers can talk to each
other via localhost and a port number,
just like when you're running multiple applications on your own laptop.
Also, have you noticed that in a Kubernetes cluster when you
run docker containers, there is this pause container,
always per each pod. These are called sandbox
containers, whose only job is to reserve and hold
the pod's network namespace that's shared by all the containers
in a pod. So post container makes it possible
for the containers to communicate with each other. And also if a container
dies and a new one gets created, pod will stay and
keep its IP address, but know that if the
pod itself dies, it gets recreated and a new pod will
get assigned a different IP address.
Learn how networking works within the pod, how containers
are created, et cetera. Now what about
interpod communication or basically a network where pods
can talk to each other? Well, Kubernetes does not come
with a built in solution for this. Instead, it expects
you to implement a networking solution for pod to
pod communication. And even though Kubernetes doesn't implement
that itself, it has a clear set of rules
of how pod networking should look like in the cluster.
And for the pod networking solution to
work in Kubernetes and to be pluggable to it, basically it has
to implement those definitions and rules.
And that set of rules is CNI
or container networking interface. This is the
same concept as we saw with the container runtime interface. You remember
when we learned that Kubernetes created an interface where
you can basically plug in any container runtime
as long as it implements that interface provided by
Kubernetes. Same way you can deploy and use a networking
plugin if it implements the container networking
interface. Now let's see, what are the requirements for
pod networking solution that network
plugin should implement. First of all,
Kubernetes expects every pod to get its own
unique IP address, and the IP address has to be
unique across the whole cluster, not just the node
where the pod is running. The second one is that pods on
the same node should be able to talk to each other using that
IP address. And the third one is that
pods on different nodes should be able to
also talk to each other using that IP address without
network address translation or net.
So basically, Kubernetes expects a network plugin
to implement a pod network for the
whole cluster on all the nodes talk to each other as
if they were on the same actual network. One thing
that Kubernetes doesn't define or doesn't care about is what
IP address range this network gets
or what IP addresses the pods will get. That's up to the
network plugin to decide. And this model of
how pod networking should look like is called Kubernetes networking
model. And there are many networking solutions out
there or network plugins which implement
this model and fulfill all these requirements,
and some of the most common and popular ones are flannel
psyllium, wavenet from weaveworks,
etc. So how does this all work in practice?
Or how do these networking solutions implement these
requirements? First of all, let's see how pods on the same
node are able to talk to each other directly with their
IP addresses. First of all, let's start with the nodes.
Each node in the cluster will have an IP address from the
IP address range and belong to the same private
network or land. In our case, this is
the VPC in our AWS account, and VPC has
a cider block or IP address range from which.