Nodes name. And this is the simplest way to define a specific node
to schedule the pod. So let's see an example of that.
First, let's see our nodes and their
names. We have master worker one and worker two. So I'm going
to create a pod definition file
to be scheduled on worker one
and it and this is the pod configuration
where inside the specification we're going to define
node name attributes on
the same level as containers and we basically just
give it name of the node and
create the pod. So now if I do get pod
nginx with
the white output, you will see that it was scheduled on the worker one
because we explicitly told the scheduler to do that.
But what if the node names in your cluster are dynamic so
you don't know exactly what the name is going to be beforehand?
This is actually very common in cloud environments where you get dynamically
provisioned cluster nodes. Or what if the node doesn't have enough
resources to run the pod? In that case, pod will
simply not be scheduled anywhere. So how can we specify
a node selector that allows more dynamic values?
For that we can use a node selector attribute which allows
specifying nodes using labels.
So you can label your nodes that are for development
environment. Maybe you can label nodes that have high cpu or
ram resources and schedule pods selectively on
them. Let's see an example of that as well.
So first I'm going to print all
the nodes with their labels and you see that
they have some auto generated labels already set on them.
However, we can give our own custom labels in addition to
that. And let's say worker two has a lot of cpu
resources and we want to schedule our pod, which is
cpu intensive on a node that has enough resources.
So to label a component in
kubernetes we can use Kubectl label command and let's see
help here. And as you see
we can label any component using Kubectl label and
the component name and
the label key value pair. So let's
change the values here. Kubectl label node because that's
what we want to label node. And let's say we want to
label node worker two and
let's give it a label. Type equals cpu.
Let's execute, check the labels again.
And there you go, type equals cpu. That's the label
we gave. And now let's create a pod definition
that will run on worker two.
And again, I'm going to just paste in a super simple
pod configuration and instead
of node name this time we have a node selector
attribute and
the value of node selector is a key value pair
of the label that a node has. In our case,
that's type cpu. That's what we labeled it.
And now if I apply this,
well, we get an error because we already have a pod
called Nginx in the cluster.
So let's try again and let's
print out nginx two
pod definition, and as you see it is running on
worker two, which we selected using
its unique label with node selector
attribute.
So the node selector attribute gives you a little bit more flexibility
over node name. But again,
if none of the nodes with a label have enough resources,
pod will not be scheduled at all. Also, let's say you want
to use more flexible expressions to select
the proper nodes. Again, this will be very useful in
cases where you have thousands of nodes in your cluster
and not just three, where they run in different regions,
different availability zones, they may have different operating
systems on them or have different tools installed.
Some of them may have specifically intel cpus,
etc. And it would make sense that you will
want to schedule pods on specific nodes for different
purposes. And that's where the third and last way of specifying
nodes in a pod definition comes in, which is
node affinity. The affinity language is
more expressive and allows you to match rules
more flexibly with logical operators,
not just the exact matches with node name or labels that
we saw. And not surprisingly, its syntax is
a bit more complex and looks like this. So inside the pod
definition we have affinity attribute instead of
node selector or node name. And inside the
affinity attribute we have the node affinity configuration.
And under node affinity you can define multiple rules
or expressions to select
a node where this pod will be scheduled on. First of
all, for each rule, like these two, for example,
you can indicate whether it is a soft
or a preferred rule, or it's rather a hard requirement,
as you see in the required and preferred
prefix. So this basically means that this rule,
whatever is defined here, has to absolutely match
for the pod to be scheduled on a node.
A preferred rule on the other hand, or a soft rule is try
to find a node that matches this expression.
But if you don't find such a node, then schedule
pod somewhere else. So this way we can allow fallback rule
so that pod still be scheduled somewhere. Now you don't have
to memorize the syntax here by heart, of course,
because if you need it, you can refer to the documentation.
However, it's important to understand what exactly you define here
and what this logic means. These node affinity rules
say that pod can only be placed on a
node with a label key equal to this
which has a value either e two
E-A-Z one or e two e az
two. So one of these values for this key, that's what the operator
in actually means. Among nodes that meet this
criteria, try to find nodes with a label,
another node label key which has a value,
another node label value. So among all the nodes that match
this criteria, those nodes should be preferred which
have this second label key value pair. So if
nodes with this preferred rule cannot be found or they
don't have enough resources, pod will be scheduled
somewhere else. And the node affinity syntax actually supports
a couple of different operators. One of them is in as we saw here
it also supports an operator exists, which means
we can say match all the nodes that have this
label. Doesn't matter what the value of that label is,
it should have that label. So in that case we would have operator exists.
We also have greater than or less than this
could be used for example to select nodes that have cpu or
memory greater than or less than a specific amount.
Now what if you have an application that you don't want to schedule on
specific nodes, but instead you want to avoid scheduling
it on certain nodes? So for example you don't care where
they go except not on nodes that have an Ubuntu
version 16.4.
Or let's say you don't want to schedule the pod on any node that has
one of the following labels. So we kind of need a negative
affinity, right? In that case you can use an operator
called not in or does not exist.
Again, not in will be to define nodes
and labels where the value is not
any of the defined here does not exist will be
nodes that do not have this specific label. And again,
let's see that in action.
First let's print out the nodes label values
again. And you see that worker one and
worker two have some of the same labels, right?
For example, the operating system is Linux on both
of them as well as the architecture is the same and
so on. So let's actually define using node affinity that
we want to schedule our pod on one of the nodes that has
Linux operating system. So if we had some other ones in the cluster
only the Linux nodes will be chosen. And among those Linux
nodes we would prefer to schedule our
pod on a node that has label
type ecpu. So let's see how we express
that with node affinity rule. So let's create
a third definition of the pod and let's call it node affinity.
So we don't know on which host it's going to be scheduled. Exactly.
And let's call our pod with node affinity and
this is the basic configuration. Now let's add
an affinity rule here. So first we
have the affinity, then we have node affinity
and under that we define all the rules or
all the expressions that should be used to
find a node to schedule this pod. So first we have
this required or hard rule, so to say
it's. And I'm just going to copy the whole expression here and
we're going to adjust the values. So first of all we have the node selector
terms match expressions and this is where
the values are defined. So we have the key and
values and the label that we want to use
is Kubernetes IO
Os. So I want the operating system to be Linux
let's define that here like this. And then we
have among those Linux servers we
want to define a soft rule again, I'm going to copy it here.
And in the soft rule we have another key value pair
of a label type equals
cpu or one of the values of the type is
cpu. And when these rules
get evaluated it should actually choose both of the worker nodes
because they have Linux operating system. And from those two
worker nodes it should then choose worker two because
that one has type cpu and because it's a soft
rule or preferred rule. If scheduler could
not find any node among those Linux nodes
that has this label or if it found one but it didn't have enough
resources to schedule the pod then it will be scheduled
on one of the other Linux nodes. And I'm going to
change this to an nginx image because busybox image
does not actually execute any process so
it's going to exit right away and
let's execute and let's check that
our pod with node affinity
was scheduled on worker two. And there you go.
We have seen a way to prevent pods from being
scheduled on specific nodes by configuring
pod itself. But what if we want to configure nodes
with such logic? So basically we want to tell
nodes which pods they should let be scheduled
on them and which not. For example, instead of
specifying that pod my app cannot be scheduled
on nodes with specific labels we can say nodes
worker one and worker two should not allow pods
with label app equals my app to be scheduled
on them. And these rules that we define on nodes to prevent
specific pods from being scheduled on them is
called a taint. And that's exactly the reason why
we can't schedule regular pods on master nodes because
they have taints that repel any pods
from being put there and we can see the taint on a master
node. If we do describe on
the master node, and right here you see the taints attribute which
says node role master, no schedule.
And we can also check taints
on all the nodes to
see that only master has that taint and not the worker
nodes. And there you go. So these are the three nodes that
we have in the cluster, and only master node has this taint,
the others don't have any. So who set or
defined that taint on a master node? Actually, well that's
done by Kubeadm when initiating the cluster.
So tainting the master node is one of the tasks
on the list of Kubeadm when bootstrapping the
cluster. So just like pods repel certain nodes,
nodes can also repel certain pods. But as you
also know, we actually have some pods
scheduled on the master node, like ECD,
kubeproxy, even the network plugin pod.
So they are all running on master. So how did the other
pods get scheduled there? This means there must be
a way to work around this taint so that some
pods get scheduled, right? Well that's done using what's called a
toleration. We can define in the pod configuration
a toleration for the taint, which is basically saying
we know that masternode has a taint that says no scheduling
of pods, but we want to configure pods to
tolerate that limitation, to still allow scheduling it
there by saying tolerate no schedule
taint. And we can see that in the configuration of
the masterpods.
So let's do describe pod.
So I'm going to do Kubectl describe on itScD
master pod. And right here you see
toleration for no execute taint.
And again we can check the toleration of all the pods kubectl
get with
JSON output first.
And right here we have the tolerations object which
has two values. The effect is the taint, the actual taint
set on the node which is called now execute and
the operator exists. So if this taint exists
on a node, we want to tolerate it. And we can also get
a list of all the tolerations for the pods in Kube system namespace
using a custom columns output
like this. So we have pod name and tolerations
columns which is in spec tolerations.
And if I execute, you see a bunch of output. Here we have
pod name and for each pod toleration.
And you see that the master pods actually
all have this no execute taint
toleration. And that's the reason why they were able
to still get scheduled on master node.
Now let's say we have a pod that we want to schedule on Masternode
specifically, and let's say it collects logs of all
control plane applications, so it has to be scheduled there.
We can configure our pod to tolerate the taint
of master node like this. So again,
let's create a pod definition and let's call it podwith
toleration and
paste in a simple pod configuration. And we're calling
this pod podwith toleration. And we're going to
make this pod tolerate the taint that master
node has. And it's actually super easy to configure. We have a tolerations
attribute, which is a list. So we can define multiple
tolerations here. And for each item we have
an effect, which is the actual taint that
a node has and its value, which for master node
is no execute, as we saw, and the
operator is exists. So if
this effect or this taint exists
on a node, we want to tolerate it for this pod.
Now our pod may tolerate the master taint,
but it doesn't mean that scheduler will actually put it there
because other nodes can run this pod as well.
Right? So now basically this pod tolerates all the nodes,
including the master. So schedule will just select between
all the nodes. So how to make sure that this
pod tolerates the master nodes taint
and also gets scheduled there? Well, for that we're going to
add a node selector or node name attribute
and let's actually go for an easier option and define node name
master. And the combination of these two will
now guarantee that the pod will be put on the master
node. And let's see that.
I'm going to apply.
And now if I do get pod podwidth
toleration with white output,
we should see that the pod is actually running on the master node.
And there you go, you see that it was actually
scheduled on the master.
Let's say we have a dynamic infrastructure, so nodes
get added and removed based on the application load.
And we want to schedule this pod that collects
master node application logs on up to
four additional master nodes that may be added to the cluster.
So we specify five replicas in total and
a node selector for all the master nodes.
However, the node selector only finds one master node.
So what will happen to the other four replicas we defined?
Well, they will all be scheduled on that one master node.
And this may be okay, but we actually want just one
application replica per master node. We don't want five of
them running on a single node. Plus, if new master nodes get
added, they won't get any pod replicas because they are all
scheduled on one node. So how should we solve that? For this
specific purpose? There is what's called an interpod
antiaffinity rule, which basically lets you
decide that your pod should only be scheduled
on nodes that do not have a specific pod
already running on them. Now where there is an antiaffinity
rule, there should be an affinity rule as well, right?
So what's an interpod affinity for? Well, let's say
our application that we want to run on the master nodes is configured
to work with an ECD application specifically.
And let's say Etsy replicate does not run on
every master node, it only runs on some of them. So we don't need to
run this application on those master nodes that don't have an ECD
pod. In other words, we only want to schedule our application pod
replica on those master nodes that have etcd
pod running on them. And that's where we can use the interpod
affinity rule. With a combination of these two rules,
interpod affinity and anti affinity rules. We can decide
to schedule our pods only on those nodes that
have itsdp pod running on them and which do
not have another replica of myApp
application already running on them. So let's see how the configuration
of that looks like again.
I'm going to create a pod definition file for interpod
affinity.
So first, let's paste in a basic configuration.
So we have five replicas defined in total. And also we
have a node selector which
defines a label, type master, or whatever
shared label all the master nodes have, basically so
that we can target master nodes and it also has a toleration
for master nodes. No execute taint.
So this is the same configuration as we saw before, but now
we have to add additional rules here to make sure
that myApp pod replicas
only run with the itsyb pod and no
two replicas of myApp end up on the same node.
And we're going to write pod affinity and anti affinity
rules for that. And note the comparison between
node affinity rules and pod affinity rules.
On the high level, we have the same affinity attribute. And instead
of node affinity, we're going to define pod affinity here.
And same way we have hard and soft rules
here. So this is a required rule. And this
basically means schedule this pod on those master
nodes that have a pod running on them with
a label app equals its CD. In addition
to that, we want to make sure. No two replicas of
myApp pod run on the same node, and we
do that using pod anti affinity rule, which is also required.
And this has the same exact label selector
that matches all the pods which have label app equals myApp,
like this one here. And since it's an
anti affinity, it will basically repel itself
from those nodes that have this pod running on them.
So combination of these two will actually give us
the desired outcome. And finally, the topology key
attribute here basically defines label
key for a unit that this
expression is meant for. And this could be a cluster node,
this could be an entire zone, this could be cloud provider's
region, et cetera. In our case, this is a cluster
node, which will be probably the most common value for the
topology key.
So to compare it with node affinity,
interpod affinity or antiaffinity works with
pod labels rather than node labels.
And also, just to note here, maybe you already noticed
that this is pretty similar to what a demon set actually
does, scheduling exactly one replica on each
worker node. And finally, I want to emphasize here that explicitly
defining where the pods should be scheduled should
not be used too often, because the main benefit of kubernetes
is the automatic scheduling, rescheduling, et cetera.
So we want to interfere as little as possible
with such constraints that
sometimes the pod starts but one of the containers inside
crashes and fails to run. However, they don't
actually notice that because the pod is in a running state
and everything looks fine, even though the container inside
and the application inside is not running, so it's not accessible
from other pods. Also, when pod crashes,
Kubernetes restarts the pod automatically.
But if container inside the pod crashes,
the developers have to manually restart it after
detecting the issue in the first place. So they
ask you whether it is possible to know right away
that the container is not running, even though pod is in
a running state, and maybe even have Kubernetes restart
the container automatically when the container stops,
just like it restarts the pods. So how can we fix that issue?
Again? You go and research how to implement this.
Generally we know that Kubernetes has an intelligent way of
managing all of its resources, like it knows the pod
status. So when the pod dies, it automatically restarts.
So we don't need to worry about that. But what about when the
application inside the pod dies, like the container
that is running inside the pod. So the pod is still running.
So Kubernetes thinks that everything is fine here, nothing to do.
But in reality that application is not accessible because the
container inside the pod crashed or maybe stuck
in a loop because of a bug so it can't accept
any traffic. How do we let Kubernetes know in this
case whether the application inside the pod
is running successfully, or maybe it crashed
or has some issue, even if the pod itself
is running and in a healthy state, so that Kubernetes
automatically restarts the application in it.
Well, we tell Kubernetes exactly that information
using liveness probe. With liveness probe defined,
Kubernetes will automatically restart the pod when the application
is crashing or is having an issue. So how
do we define a liveness probe in our container? It's actually
a very simple script or a tiny program that just
pings the application endpoint every 5 seconds
or 10 seconds to check that the application responds so
it's running successfully. And this can be defined in three different
ways. So this is the liveness probe attribute,
and inside that we configure the health check.
First, we have the check with a simple command execution.
This could be for example a command to run a simple script
that checks the application's health status. And of course
we need to define how often this check will be made with period
seconds attribute like execute the defined
liveness check every 5 seconds. Second, we have
a TCP socket attribute with the port where
the application is running. So with this configuration,
Kubelet will attempt to open the socket to
your container on the configured port. If it
succeeds to establish a connection on this port,
the container is considered to be healthy, so the application inside
is running and is reachable. If it cannot establish
a connection, the probe will fail. And finally we have
the third way, which is checking the application health on
the HTTP endpoint. For example, if the application itself
had an endpoint that exposes the health status of
the application, we could hit that endpoint to check whether
the application is healthy or not. It is configured
with an HTTP get attribute which defines the
path and the port of the application's health
endpoint. So this configuration will tell Kubelet
there is an HTTP endpoint in the application on
path health port 3000
where you can check whether the application is healthy or not.
We said that Kubernetes knows the pod state, but it doesn't
know the application state inside the pod. And we solve this problem
with a liveness probe. Right, but liveness probe helps
Kubernetes see that the application is running successfully only
after the application actually started. But what
about the starting up process itself of the application?
So pod was created and now the application inside
is actually starting up. How does Kubernetes know that the
application is fully initiated and started and ready
to receive the request? That's where readiness probe helps.
It lets Kubernetes know that the application is ready to receive traffic.
And this is important because if your application needs two minutes to
start without readiness probe, all the requests to
it will fail during those two minutes and you will have a bunch of
errors in your applications. So how do we
configure a readiness probe? Actually very similarly
to the liveness probe because they both basically check
the application availability. Readiness probe
does it during the application startup process while liveness probe does
it while the application is already running.
And again, to quickly see that in action,
let's create a pod definition with health probes.
So first let's paste in some basic configuration
of NgInX. Let's actually call the pod MyApp
health probes. And right here we're going to define the
health probes. So first of all, we want to check the readiness of the application
to make sure the application has actually started and
is running before sending any requests to it.
And as I said, you can have own endpoints in your applications
that give you some health data that expose the
health data of the application, whether it's available or not.
So in readiness or liveness probes, you can just hit that endpoint
or you can just use a simple command or
a TCP socket configuration to check
that the application is available at port 80. So in
our case, let's do simple TCP socket check on
port 80 because that's
where the container is running. And let's say we
know that our application, our web application takes
some time to start because there are some tasks that it executes on
a startup. So we are actually going to give it some time before
we execute a readiness probe check. So we're going
to do initial delay seconds
ten, and then once we start the readiness checks
we're going to do it every 5 seconds.
So period seconds is
going to be five. And this will take care of making
sure that the application is fully started before it receives
any requests. Now once the readiness probe is done
and we have made sure application is started,
then readiness probe's job is done, so to say.
And now the liveness probe can take over. So liveness
probe, and it is actually going to be the same
configuration where we just check that port 80 is
open and accessible and we can define
the same initial delay for
the liveness probe to take over. So let's say application
started. So after 5 seconds we start the
liveness probe and after the initial one we're going to do it every
15 seconds. So every 15 seconds this
will check whether the container is still running, whether the
application inside is still running and accessible on port
80. And if at some point it crashes and
liveness probe doesn't get an answer from the application,
it will notify Kubernetes and say this
container actually crashed so we need to restart it.
And if the application fails to run even after the
restart you will see the status directly.
When you do Kubectl get pod. So it's going to be more visible to you
that something is wrong with that pod. So let's save this configuration
and let's deploy our pod with health probes.
And if I do Kubectl get
pod, you will see that the readiness probe kicked in in
about 10 seconds. So the first 10 seconds we had
ready zero here and after that
readiness probe was successful and we have one container out
of one running. And now every 15 minutes
the liveness probe will actually check whether application is
still running or not. And if it isn't it will show
us the issue right away.
Have set up a pipeline to update their web application running
in a cluster. So whenever they release a new version
and build a new image, it should be deployed in Kubernetes.
They however aren't sure how the update works
in Kubernetes. So you have the old application version running
in the cluster. When you update the image version,
what happens to the deployment? Does it remove all the old pods
and restart new ones with a new image? In that case the application
will not be accessible for users while the old
pods get terminated and new ones are being created.
Right? So will there be an application downtime?
This could be a problem when they deploy the application in a production environment.
Also, what if the new image version has some issues?
How can they roll back the application to the previous image
version? Is there a proper way to do it with deployments
so they ask you for your input? And finally,
in addition to all of that, developers notice that when they
print all components in a default namespace
with Kubectl getall there is
a Kubernetes component called replica set on the list
and there are actually few of them with Nginx deployment
prefix with zero in the state.
So what is this component and what does it have to
do with deployments or pods?
Deployment. It creates what's called an application rollout
and for that it uses a component called replica set.
Replica set gets created automatically when we create a
deployment and is responsible for creating the replicas
and making sure the right number of pod replicas run
at all times. So to visualize the hierarchy we
work with deployment resources. We configure and
create them using Kubernetes configuration files.
And under the hood Kubernetes creates a replica set
for the deployment and replica set, then creates pods
so we don't have to directly interact with replica sets
or pods as long as we are working with deployments.
A deployment with new version of the container
image what happens is that a new replica set
gets created that is responsible for starting new
pods with the new image version while old replica
set remains and is responsible for removing pods with
the old image version. Now how does this update
actually happen? In which order do pods get removed
and new ones created? This is called a deployment
update strategy. The first strategy is pretty
simple. When deployment gets updated, Replica set removes
all the pods and the new replica set then
creates new pods. It's called a recreate strategy
and this one will result in an application downtime
because application will be unavailable between the removal of
old and creation of new pods. That's where the second
strategy comes in to prevent the application downtime.
So instead of removing all the pods at once and then creating new
ones, it deletes one old pod and creates
one new one, then removes the second old pod and creates a
second new one and so on until all old pods are gone
and new pods created. This strategy is called a
rolling update and it is actually the default strategy
configured for all the deployments in the cluster.
With both update strategies, the old replica set
will remain in the cluster with zero pods
in desired current and ready state and the new
replica set will be created with active pod replicas
as you see right here.
And that's why you see multiple replica sets of the
same application or the same deployment in the
cluster. And pods always belong to
one of the replica sets. If you look closely, the replica set
has a prefix of the deployment it belongs
to, plus its own unique hash at the end.
So by looking at the pod names, you know which pods belong
to the same replica set. Now as I said,
the rolling update is the default update strategy configured
for the deployments. So how can we check where
the update strategy is configured or how can we override that if we
want to? You can actually see that in the deployment configuration where
we have a rolling update strategy section.
So if I do Kubectl describe deployment
and name of the deployment.
Right here you see the strategy type which is set to rolling
update and then for the rolling update we have another attribute
called rolling update strategy that says 25%
max unavailable and 25% max search.
So what does this value actually mean? Well, in rolling update,
you can define how many pods you want to restart at
once. If you have 20 replicas, for example, you may not
want to wait for old pods to stop and new pods to
start one by one. So you can configure rolling update
to restart five pods at once.
So restart the first five pods, then the second five pods,
et cetera, until all 20 are running with the new version.
And you can define that in percentage, saying maximum
25% of pod replicas may be unavailable
at once at the same time and maximum 25%
more than defined replicas may be running at
once. And if we check the deployment updates events,
we will see how the update actually progressed. Here you
can see how the old replica set scaled down pods
and in parallel the new replica set scaled
up the new pods.
The updates in deployment creates what's called revisions.
So each time we roll out changes to a deployment,
a new revision gets created, which we can
check using Kubectl rollout history command.
And we want a rollout history for a deployment called NgINX
deployment. And right here,
you see we have three revisions, which means we
have rolled out this deployment three times.
So let's actually change the version in
our NginX deployment. And let's change the NginX image
version and let's set it to 121.
And let's roll out the change by applying the
new configuration. And let's see
the old pod being terminated and new ones running.
And you see the pod now belongs to a new replica and let's check that
as well. Kubectl get replica set. And as
you see now we have four replica sets where this
was just created 25 seconds ago as we rolled
out the changes. And if we describe
the pod image,
we should see image Nginx 121.
And also if
we check the revision using rollout history,
and we have a new revision on the list. So with these revisions,
we actually have a history of deployment
changes. And that means we can roll back to a previous
revision if we want to. And we can do that using a command Kubectl
rollout undo. And let's say in our case,
the new version broke something in the cluster. The application isn't
working anymore. So we want to undo that change and deploy the
previous version of the application, which was 120.
So let's do rollout undo for deployment Nginx deployment
and to check the status of a rollout,
we can do Kubectl rollout status.
And again we see that old pod gets terminated.
And now let's check the replica sets
again. And as you see, the previous replica set
has one active pod again, and the new one,
which was created three minutes ago, has no pods.
So this replica set removed all its pod replicas,
and the previous replica set recreated
its pod replicas. And again, if we describe
the pod and
check the container image, we should see it's back to 1.20.
So that's how we can do rollbacks in our deployments.
And again, checking the history,
we have reverted the changes in revision six and
now we are at revision eight point.
We have provided developers with access to the cluster for
them and for their CI CD pipeline. So everything is
running smoothly until an outage happens
and we lose all cluster configuration data. So all
the resources were deleted, which means we need to redeploy
all the components again. And that's really bad. We should
be prepared for such cases. So we need to back
up the cluster configuration data which is stored in
ECD,
as you've learned, is a key value pair store.
And just like we can and should backup any database,
we can backup, and should always backup etCD
store as well. Now what is exactly in the Etsy
store? All the Kubernetes components that we created
have configurations defined with Kubernetes manifest files,
right? And they also have the state.
State of deployment, for example, defines how many replicas
are running and available. A state of a service
is how many endpoints and which endpoints it has,
et cetera. Plus we saw for deployments we have revisions
or in other words, the history of changes of the
application deployment, which we can use to roll back
to the previous version. We also have all the config
map and secret data and so on. So all this data
is in the Etsyd store, which means if
we lost the Etsyd store data, we would lose all this information
and would not know the cluster state. Now,
it's also important to understand what is not in the Etsyd store,
and that is the application data itself. So the
storage we configure with persistent volumes for database or
any stateful applications is not in the Itsyd
store. It is stored either on the cluster nodes itself
or on a remote storage. So that's a separate
storage and needs to be managed in its own way.
Right now we are only talking about the Kubernetes configuration
data and state in the Etsy store.
An ECD backup. It's actually pretty easy because
we have an ECD control command line tool
which already has all the commands we need for backing up and
restoring the ECD data. So first we install
the Etsy control on the master node and then we
use this tool to create an ECD store
backup.
So let's see how that works. First of all, I'm on the master
node and if I do ECD control command it
is not installed, but I will get a suggestion of how to install
it and I'm going to use the EPT command for this and
install etsy client. And now we
have eTCD control installed. And now let's see how to
backup eTCD store data.
And for that you can also reference the Kubernetes official documentation
which has all these steps described in detail.
And you see that before the ETCD control commands we set
this environment variable to the API version
three. So ECD control underscore API and
then the ETCD control command. So I'm going to copy that first.
So let's put together our command. So we are setting the environment variable
Etsy control underscore API to three.
Then we have Etsy control command itself and then we have
snapshot subcommend which will take the snapshot of the
current state at this moment of the ETCD store.
And then we have save so we want to save the snapshot
and the location where we want to save it. And this could be a temporary
location. Let's call it Etsy backup db
because it is a key value database. Right.
But note that ECD control is
a client tool for connecting to the Etsyd store.
And of course because of security reasons the Etsyd service
is protected so we can't just execute this command without any
credentials. Right. We're going to get some authentication
or authorization error here. So basically this will
not work because we need some kind of authentication with
the Etsy server from the Etsy control client
and we do that using certificates. One way
to see how we can provide authentication to ETCD server
is to check how API server connects
to the ECD because API server is also a client
that talks to the ECD server. So we can basically use
its example to see how to authenticate
with it. And for that we can simply
output the configuration file of
the Kube API server. Because remember in the certificate section
we saw that components in kubernetes actually talk to each other,
right? So most of the components talk to the API server and
API server itself talks to the EtCD server
and we have to do it with pseudo command. And if
I scroll up you
will see how Kube API server actually authenticates
with the ECD server using these three
files where API server uses the API server
client certificates. Or we
could also check the ECD configuration itself which
also defines the certificates and way to communicate with the ETCD
server itself. So we have the certificate file which is
Etsy server certificate, the server key and
the ECD CA certificate. So we can use any
of these certificates to authenticate with
the ECD server. So I'm going to use the ones defined
here. So we need three of them. We need the CA certificate or
server key and the certificate file.
So let's actually print this out by
grabbing it like this and
let's pull up our command again and
we're going to specify the three credentials we need. So first
is going to be the CA certificate which
is located right here.
Then we have the certificate itself. This could be a server or a
client certificate. So I'm going to take this one and
then we have the key which is the key file.
And now let's execute the command again and
with pseudo because of the permission.
And as you see snapshot saved at
temp ECD backupdb. So if
we check that we have the file
that has been generated, we can also check the status of
the backup file and make sure it actually has some data in
it using
snapshot status command. And note that we don't need authentication
for that because it's just a local file. So here we're going
to do snapshot status and this
will give us some information. We can also display it in a table format with
a more readable output using write
out table.
And you see the total size. So we have
3.4 megabytes of data, we have 926
entries of data, these are the total keys and so on.
So now you as an administrator would
take care of saving this backup file of your ETCD
store, properly encrypting it for more safety and
basically storing it somewhere safe so that in case
such a disaster happens where the whole
cluster basically goes down because we have a power outage or all
the servers where the cluster is running basically just die and we
can't reuse them anymore and we have to recreate the cluster
on completely new servers, we could actually recover
the cluster state from that ECD store and
save us a lot of time and effort and headache.
Now I want to mention one thing about the certificates that
we passed here. Of course now because we're on the master
node, we have access to those certificates, right,
because they have been generated by the Kubeadm and they're all stored
in this PKI folder. However, if you
are executing Etsy control command from outside
the cluster you will have to explicitly copy
or make these certificates basically available there
to pass them as credentials. So on that other machine
you would have these certificates at their own location and you
would specify them when executing Etsy
control command from another machine.
You're probably wondering if Etsy store is
so important. Do we need to have maybe multiple replicas
of them or can we manage it separately
independent of the cluster? Because that's where all the important cluster
data is, right? And we also saw that DTD data physically
is also saved on the node and to remind
you of that, that was actually configured here as
a host path volume ETCD data. So that's
where the ETCD data physically gets stored, right on
the master node at this path
with pseudo. So that's where the data actually
leaves. And you would be absolutely right to ask whether
there's.