It. Let's use Nginx, maybe with a specific
version. We can also specify a port here as
you see in the usage. Again you can add ports and
everything inside the configuration file, but you can
also specify them right here so they end up in the configuration
file already configured. So let's set a port,
let's say it is 80 and replicas,
which I'm going to copy from here. And this will be
the main configuration of the deployment. And again
we are telling Kubernetes or Kubectl
do not actually execute this, we just want a preview in
YAmL format and we want to save it as a deployment file.
In my deployment yaml and with dry run
without a value we get a warning here
because I didn't specify the client value.
That's just the warning. We should have our deployment file
still created and let's actually check that.
And there you go, we have the blueprint of deployment and pod
configured with the image port, replica count
and everything else. Basically you can set yourself and this
could be super convenient if you don't want to go
to the documentation and search documentation,
but really quickly just want to generate a couple of configuration
files and let's actually see final and third example for
creating a configuration file for a pod. How do we
do that? The way we create pods
in the cluster, as you already saw, is not by Kubectl
create, because if we check Kubectl create
does not actually allow us to create pods,
but it allows us to create all these components. So you can generate
configuration files for all these resources here,
but for pod we use Kubectl run
command. So Kubectl run name of the pod,
let's call this my pod and let's actually do help to see
everything we can configure. So image which
is the required attributes.
Again let's use our well known Nginx
and again here you have usage of different
other options. So you can set ports here, you can add environment
variables, you can add labels.
So basically all this stuff that you see here
and let's actually add some labels to
the pod like
this and dry run
client Yaml outputs and let's save
this in my pod yaml file and
as you see we have a pod manifest with the
image name of the container is same as the pod
and we have the two labels that we specified on the command.
So that's the second pro tip for working efficiently
with kubernetes.
Great. At this point we have a cluster where an
application is running and accessible through its service.
However, that Nginx application is only accessible within
the cluster. However, if we deploy a web application, for example,
we want end users outside the cluster to have access
to it, right? It means we need to open our application to the
outside world. And in this section we're going to see
how to expose an application running inside a
Kubernetes cluster to external users using
three different ways. And the first one is
using an external service called node
port.
We have an internal service, Nginx service
with a cluster IP type. So cluster IP type
means actually an internal service. So instead
of an internal service, we're going to create an external
service. So what I'm going to do is I'm going to actually delete service
Nginx service from
the cluster and it's
gone. And I'm going to adjust the
configuration of our service to turn it
from an internal service to an external node port
service, which is actually pretty simple.
In the specification part of the service, we just
provide a type. So by default the
type attribute, if we do not specified in the configuration,
it is going to be cluster IP, which is an internal service.
However, we can override that default value and instead
of cluster IP, we can make type node
port. And there is one more thing we need to do here.
Node port services actually need a third port
in the port configuration of the service. So right here we
have two ports. One of them is where the service is
accessible at, and another one is where
the pods or endpoint pods of the service are
accessible. And Node port has a third port called
a node port.
So what is this node port and how does
Nodeport service actually work?
When we create an internal service for our pod,
that service is accessible from other pods in
the cluster at this specific IP address at the port
of the service. When we create a node port,
it actually creates an internal service, but in addition
to that, it also opens ports on
the nodes on each worker node in the cluster
to make the service accessible from outside.
And this port which gets opened on
the servers, the Kubernetes worker nodes
is called a node port. And there is actually a
dedicated port range for these node
ports. And you actually saw that range when we configured
our AWS security groups. So going back to
the security groups here in the worker nodes
security group, we configured a firewall rule
with the port range from 30,000 to 32,767.
And we said that any IP address
should be able to access this port on the worker nodes.
And that's the port range that we use
to open a node port on the worker nodes, when we
create a node port service, and that means that the
value of node port has to be within that range.
So I'm actually going to take 30,000, which is the first in
the range. You can also do 30,001, doesn't really matter,
and let's save it and apply
it. Nginx service created
so now if I do Kubectl get service,
you see that the type is not
cluster IP anymore, but rather a node
port. And you don't only have the service port
here, but also 30,000, which is a node
port. So the way it's going to work now is that the
service, the node port service is actually now accessible
from outside the cluster for end users on
the IP address of the node, of the server itself and
the node port. Right. So combination of these two is
going to be the URL to access the service from outside
and internally when the request comes in into one of
those worker nodes. So this could be any one of them.
The request will then be forwarded to the internal service
IP address. So let's actually test that this works.
I'm going to choose one of the worker nodes. It doesn't matter which one because
the service is accessible on all the worker nodes. I'm going
to copy the public IP address of the worker node
and port 30,000. And there
you go. We have a welcome to NgINx page,
which means we were able to access the NgINx application
or NgINx pods through the node port service
externally from outside the cluster, again using
the IP address of any of the worker nodes, it doesn't matter
which one. And the node port or port that we
opened on each one of the worker nodes by specifying
that as a port in the service.
Cool. So now our application is accessible externally,
but we can't ask users to access the
application on this kind of port and have
to type in the IP address of the application,
because this is not very user friendly. Also imagine if we had lots
of applications that we exposed like this using
a node port service. This would open up lots
of ports on our worker nodes.
And this is actually very insecure and also very
messy because we will have to keep track of the node ports that we
assign to the services. So there must be
a better way of exposing our applications
than using a node port service. So this is fine for
testing, but there should be a better way of exposing
our applications to the end users. Well,
as a better alternative, we have another service type called
a load balancer. Now let's see how load balancer service actually
works. Going back to the cluster, I'm going to again
delete the NgINx service
in the cluster and go ahead and modify
the Nginx service yaml file. And instead
of type node port we're going to write
here load balancer type.
That's it. Everything else can actually stay the same.
We have port of the service, target port and
even the node port. So let's actually try to create this by
applying and
let's get the service. First of all, we have a type load balancer
instead of node port here, and we also have an
external ip which is pending and
the same port mapping here as for the node port. So how
does load balancer actually work? So the way
the load balancer service actually works is that on top
of the internal service that listens on the
service port like 80, 80 here,
and the node port service which opens the
node port on the worker nodes, it creates a
load balancer in front of the cluster nodes which
will accept the request from outside and then load
balance it to one of the worker nodes on the node
port, which will then forward the request to the internal
service IP address. So as you see, node port and load balancer do
not replace the internal service type,
but rather it builds on top of each other. So with load balancer we actually
have all three types in one, which works
in this hierarchical way. Now I said that load balancer
gets created outside the cluster and is accessible
at its own IP address and its own port.
So the load balancer IP address or service
itself is not created inside the cluster,
it just gives you a service of that type. But the load balancer
is actually a component outside the cluster, which means
this external IP address does not come from the Kubernetes
itself. This should actually be set by whoever
creates a load balancer that sits in front of
the cluster. So who is responsible for creating a load balancer
and assigning it an IP address? Load balancer
is actually created by cloud platforms that
offer kubernetes as a managed service.
And that is a limitation of a load balancer, because if we
are creating a cluster on bare metal servers
or just on empty self managed servers
and basically install it from scratch instead of using a managed
service of cloud platform, you don't
have a load balancer or you don't get a load balancer out of the
box. You would actually have to create your own.
In this case because we installed the cluster from
scratch on bare servers. And this will be the same for installation
on on premise servers without any cloud platform,
we will have to create a load balancer for each service
that we want to expose. So that means if I go to my
AWS account and search for a load
balancer which is actually in the EC two service,
if you scroll all the way down, you have load balancers section
here which currently is empty.
So when you're using a managed Kubernetes service like eks
for example on AWS, the cloud native
load balancer will be created for you
automatically when you create a load balancer service.
And you would see that right here. In our case,
however, load balancer does not get created automatically, but we
could create it manually and see how that works.
Which means you would have to create your own load balancer, whether it's
on premise solution or here on AWS
itself. So just to demonstrate that,
I'm actually going to create a load balancer for our load balancer
service.
So let's do create load balancer and this is going to be a simple application
load balancer for HTP, which is our Nginx service.
Let's do create, let's just give it a name.
Test load balancer service.
It has to be Internet facing because we are testing access
from the browser and we
have to select a zone and we
actually have to select the zone where our nodes
are. Again, remember, load balancer will sit outside
the cluster in front of it and will get all the requests
and then forward it, or load balance it to one
of the worker nodes on the node port, which will
then forward it to the internal service, which means we want
our load balancer in the same zone as the worker nodes.
So let's choose one b but because it's a load balancer
we have to select at least two subnets.
Now this is very specific to AWS, so you don't have to 100%
understand how this works, especially if you're deploying Kubernetes
cluster on a different platform. But just know
that here we have to select at least two subnets
of the VPC and one of them where the worker nodes
are running and click next
we have a warning about security settings. Then we
just choose a default security group here and configure
routing. So this is the part where we decide where
does load balancer forward the request that
it gets. Again one of the worker nodes on port
30,000 which is the node port here,
right? So this is the port which is already
open on all the worker nodes because we deployed load
balancer type of service. And we can check
that again if I reload this. You see that NgInx
is still accessible using the worker node ip address
and 30,000. So on the EC two instances,
port 30,000 and let's give this
target group or routing group a name.
Let's also call this test routing.
And that's it. So this will basically say to instance
types on port 30,000.
And now we have to say which instances these
are exactly. In our case, these are the worker nodes, only the
worker nodes, not the master on port 30,000.
And we do add to registered.
So now we have a setup where we put
a load balancer in front of the cluster as part
of AWS. And this load balancer gets
the request from the users and it will forward it to one of
the two worker nodes on port 30,000.
And with this configuration we do review
and create load balancer.
Provisioning will take some time because it needs to get an IP address,
it needs to connect to those instances,
need to basically configure everything in the background and
after a couple of minutes it will go from provisioning state
to active state.
Once the load balancer is in an active state, it means that we
can access the service in our cluster with
this load balancer. Now how do we access the
load balancer? Our load balancer has an IP address,
but it also has a domain name, which is
this one right here. So if we copy
the name of the load balancer and
paste it here on default port 80,
that's where load balancer is accessible. And enter.
There you go. We have welcome to NginX page
because in the background the load balancer
got the request and it then forwarded the request
to one of its registered targets,
worker node one on port 30,000
or worker node two on port 30,000
on their IP addresses. And you can actually ignore the health
status here because we don't expose health information in the EC
two instances and that's why it says unhealthy.
So everything works and our load balancer is
correctly load balancing the request
to the node port all the way to internal
service.
Now as I said, when you're configuring a self
managed kubernetes cluster, you would have to create the load balancer
yourself. On a cloud platform like AWS you
can provision a load balancer just like we did or
on premise servers. You would have to implement or deploy
some load balancer application. However, even if
we were using a managed kubernetes cluster that
automatically created load balancers for us,
whenever we create a load balancer service, it would still have a
disadvantage that we would end up with
bunch of load balancers that each become an entry point
to the cluster. So if we had hundreds of applications
with hundreds of services, we would basically end up with bunch
of load balancers that also need to be configured
and mapped to our actual application's domain name,
right? Because eventually people want to access our application
on a proper domain name like myapp.com
and not the domain name of the load balancer or IP address
of the load balancer. So with hundreds of load balancers,
how do we map each load balancer IP address to
a proper domain name? And also each load balancer will
expose a new node port on the server. So we
have multiple issues here. With multiple
node ports being exposed on all
the worker nodes, it means we need to keep track of those
ports. We also have multiple load balancers, which on a
cloud platform would translate to a very high bill because each
load balancer service will cost some money. And on top of
that, we don't have one domain that will let us access all
those load balancer services. So basically we would need
a load balancer that will get all the traffic for myapp.com
domain, and then based on a subdomain
or a path in the URL, we'll redirect that
request to one of the load balancers.
And finally, you also need a way to secure
access to your applications, right? So you need this htps
configuration to access applications inside your cluster.
So if you're installing and managing cluster on bare
metal servers, you would have to manage all of these outside the cluster.
So wouldn't it be great if we had a simple solution
to all of this stuff as a part
of the Kubernetes cluster itself, which means we
would be able to configure the secure connection
to the application as well as load balancing
to all the different services in our cluster using
solution as part of the cluster. That would be a
much more elegant solution than having to create this load
balancer components and then configure routing
and all this stuff yourself. Well, the solution for all of this is
actually ingress, which is part of the Kubernetes
itself, and it lets you configure
routing to different services and applications in
your cluster using simple Kubernetes native
components, as well as configure secure connection to
any of your applications. This means that for our
NgINX service application, we would simply
need an ingress component in the cluster
that will take the request and route that to the
NgINX service. However, as we said, ingress is
deployed and available inside the Kubernetes cluster.
So to make it externally accessible we would still
have to expose it either through a node port
service or a load balancer. However, this would be much
easier to do because we would just need one single node
port or load balancer. That would be the single entry
point to the cluster, which will then direct
the traffic directly to ingress. And ingress will
then manage all types of routing of the request
within the cluster. So let's see how Ingress actually works
and how it manages all this routing in an
elegant and easy way so that we don't have to do any
of this route configuration ourselves.
So let's go through the syntax of Ingress.
Basically you have a kind ingress instead of a service,
and in a specification where the whole configuration happens
you have so called rules or routing rules,
and this basically defines that the main address or all
the requests to that host must be forwarded
to an internal service. So this is the
host that user will enter in the browser. And in
ingress users define a mapping. So what happens when that
request to that host gets issued? You redirect
it internally to a service. The path here basically means the URL
path, so everything after the domain name,
so slash whatever path comes after that. You can define those
rules here and we'll see some different examples
of the path configuration later. And as you see here in this configuration
we have an HTTP protocol. So later
in this video I'm going to show you how to configure htps
connection using ingress component.
So right now in the specification we don't have anything configured for
the secure connection, it's just HTP. And one thing to note
here is that this HTTP attribute here does not correspond
to this one here. This is a protocol that the
incoming request gets forwarded to to the internal
service. So this is actually the second step and not
to confuse it with this one. And now let's see how
the internal service to that ingress will look like.
So basically backend is the target where
the request, the incoming request will be redirected and the
service name should correspond the internal service name like this,
and the port should be the internal service port.
And as you see here, the only difference between the external and
internal services is that here in internal service I don't
have the third port which is the node port starting from
30,000. We now have that attribute here, and the
type is a default type, not a load balancer, but internal
service type, which is cluster IP. So this should be a
valid domain address. So you can just write anything here.
It has to be first of all valid. And you should map that
domain name to IP address of the
node that represents an entry point to your Kubernetes
cluster. If you configure a server outside of the Kubernetes cluster,
that will become the entry point to your Kubernetes cluster.
Then you should map this host name to the ip address
of that server. So now that we saw what Kubernetes
ingress components looks like, let's see how to actually configure
ingress in the cluster. So basically you have a pod
service and corresponding ingress. Now if you
create that ingress component alone,
that won't be enough for ingress routing
rules to work. What you need in addition is an implementation
for ingress, and that implementation is called ingress controller.
So the step one will be to install an ingress controller which
is basically another pod or another set
of pods that run on your node in your Kubernetes
cluster and does evaluation and processing of ingress
rules. So the YamL file that I showed you with the ingress
component is basically this part right here,
and this has to be additionally installed in Kubernetes
cluster. So what is ingress controller exactly?
The function of ingress controller is to
evaluate all the rules that you have defined in your cluster and this
way to manage all the redirections. So basically this
will be the entry point in the cluster for all the
requests to that domain or subdomain rules that
you've configured. And this will evaluate all the
rules because you may have 50 rules or 50 ingress
components created in your cluster, it will evaluate
all the rules and decide based on that which forwarding
rule applies for that specific request.
So in order to install this implementation of ingress in
your cluster, you have to decide which one of
many different third party implementations you want to choose from.
There is one from Kubernetes itself, which is Kubernetes NgInx
Ingress controller, but there are others as well. So once you install ingress
controller in your cluster, you're good to go create
Ingress roles and the whole configuration is going to work.
So now that I've shown you how Ingress can be used in a Kubernetes
cluster, there is one thing that I think is important
to understand in terms of setting up the whole
cluster to be able to receive external requests.
Now first of all, you have to consider
the environment where your Kubernetes cluster is running. If you are
using some cloud service provider like Amazon
web services, Google Cloud, Linode. There are a couple more that
have out of the box Kubernetes solutions or
they have their own virtualized load balancer etc.
Your cluster configuration would look something like this.
So you would have a cloud load balancer that is specifically
implemented by that cloud provider and external
requests coming from the browser will first hit the load
balancer and that load balancer then will redirect
the request to ingress controller. Now this is
not the only way to do it even in cloud environment.
You can do it in a couple of different ways, but this is one of
the most common strategies. An advantage
of using cloud provider for that is that you
don't have to implement a load balancer yourself.
So with minimal effort, probably on most
cloud providers, you will have the load balancer up and running and
ready to receive those requests and forward those requests into your
Kubernetes cluster. So very easy setup. Now if you're deploying
your Kubernetes cluster on a bare metal environment, then you would
have to do that part yourself. So basically you would have to configure
some kind of entry point to your Kubernetes cluster yourself, either inside of
a cluster or outside. As a separate server
you will have to provide an entry point and one of those types
is an external proxy server which can be a
software or hardware solution that
will take a role of that load balancer in an entry
point to your cluster. So basically what this would
mean is that you will have a separate server and
you would give this a public ip address and you would open the ports
in order for the requests to be accepted.
And this proxy server then will act as an entry
point to your cluster. So this will be the only one
accessible externally. So none of the servers in your Kubernetes cluster
will have publicly accessible IP address, which is obviously
a very good security practice. So all the requests
will enter the proxy server and that will then redirect the request to
ingress controller and ingress controller will then decide
which ingress rule applies to that specific request
and the whole internal request forwarding will happen.
In the next section we're going to go through more use cases
of how you can define more fine granular routing
for applications inside Kubernetes cluster. So the first
thing is defining multiple path of
the same host. So consider following use case.
Google has one domain but has many services that
it offers. So for example if you have a Google account, you can use
its analytics, you can use its shopping, you have a calendar,
you have a Gmail, et cetera. So all of these are separate applications
that are accessible with the same domain.
So consider you have an application that does something similar.
So you offer two separate applications that are
part of the same ecosystem, but you still want to have them
on separate URLs. So what you can do is that in rules
you can define the host, which is myapp.com,
and in the path section you can define multiple path. So if
user wants to access your analytics application,
then they have to enter myapp.com analytics
and that will forward the request to internal
analytics service and the pod. Or if they want
to access the shopping application, then the URL
for that would be myapp.com shopping.
So this way you can do forwarding with one ingress
of the same host to multiple applications using multiple
path. Another use case is when instead
of using URLs to make
different applications accessible, some companies use
subdomains. So instead of having myapp.com analytics,
they create a subdomain analytics myapp.com.
So if you have your application configured that way, your configuration
will look like this. So instead of having one host like in the previous example,
and multiple path here inside, now you have
multiple hosts where each host represents a subdomain
and inside you just have one path that again redirects
that request to analytics service. Pretty straightforward.
So now in the same request setting you have analytics service and
a pod behind it. Now the request will look like
this using a subdomain instead of path.
And one final topic that I mentioned that we'll cover
here is configuring TLS certificate.
Till now we've only seen ingress configuration for HTP
requests, but it's super easy to configure HTTPs
forwarding in Ingress. So the only thing that you need to do is
define attribute called TLS above the rules
section with host which is the same host as right
here, and the secret name which is a reference
of a secret that you have to create in a cluster that holds that
TLS certificate. So the secret configuration would look
like this. So the name is
the reference right here, and the data or
the actual contents contain TLS certificate and
TLS key. You probably notice the type additional
type attribute here. In Kubernetes there is a specific
type of a secret called TLS, so we'll have to use that
type when you create a TLS secret. And there are
three small notes to be made here. One is that
the keys of this data have to be named exactly
like that. The values are the actual
file contents of the certificate or key contents and not
the file path or location. So you have to put the
whole content here, base 64 encoded. And the third
one is that you have to create the secret in the same namespace
as the ingress component for it to be able to use that.
Otherwise you can't reference a secret from another namespace.
And these four lines is all you need to
configure mapping of an HTTPs request
to that host to internal service.
We know what Ingress is, how it works, and how we
can configure ingress in our cluster. Let's actually
go ahead and set it up. As you learned,
the first step to using ingress and configuring it is to
actually install the ingress controller application,
the application that actually does routing
in the cluster. And then after we've installed the Ingress
controller, we're going to create ingress components in Kubernetes using
Kubernetes native manifest files to
configure our ingress controller application with
the logic of how to route different application
requests. So as a first step, let's install ingress
controller in our cluster and we're going to install it using
Helm. Helm is basically a package manager for Kubernetes
that lets us install different applications with
all the needed components inside. So it basically makes
it easier for us to install applications in Kubernetes.
If you don't know what Helm is and how it works, you can watch the
prerequisite video about Helm and then continue with the
lecture where we install ingress controller manager with helm.
In this video I'm going to explain all the main concepts of helm
so that you are able to use it in your own projects. So understanding
the basic common principles and more importantly its
use cases to when and why we use Helm
will make it easier for you to use it in practice, no matter which
version you choose. So the topics I'm going to go through in
this video are Helm and helm charts, what they are,
how to use them, and in which scenarios they're used.
So what is Helm? Helm has a couple of main features
that it's used for. The first one is as a package
manager for Kubernetes, so you can think of it as
apt Yum or homebrew for Kubernetes.
So it's a convenient way for packaging collections of
Kubernetes YaML files and distributing them in public and
private registry. Now these definitions may sound a
bit abstract, so let's break them down with specific examples.
So let's say you have deployed your application in
Kubernetes cluster and you want to deploy elasticsearch
additionally in your cluster that your application will use
to collect its logs. In order to
deploy Elasticstack in your Kubernetes cluster,
you would need a couple of Kubernetes components. So you would need a
stateful set which is for stateful applications like
databases, you would need a config map with external configuration
you would need a secret where some credentials and secret
data are stored. You would need to create the Kubernetes user with its
respective permissions and also create a couple of
services. Now if you were to create
all of these files manually by searching for each
one of them separately on Internet, be a tedious job
and until you have all these YAML files collected and tested
and try it out, it might take some time. And since elasticstack
deployment is pretty much the standard across all
clusters, other people will probably have to go through the
same. So it made perfect sense that someone created
these YaMl files once and packaged them up and made
it available somewhere so that other people who
also use the same kind of deployment could use them in their kubernetes
cluster. And that bundle of YAML files is
called Helm chart. So using helm you can create
your own helm charts or bundles of those
YAMl files and push them to some
helm repository to make it available for others.
Or you can consume so you can download and use
existing helm charts that other people pushed and made
available in different repositories. So commonly used
deployments like database applications, elasticsearch,
MongoDB, MySQL, or monitoring applications
like Prometheus that all have this kind
of complex setup, all have charts
available in some helm repository. So using
a simple helm install chart name command,
you can reuse the configuration that someone else has already made
without additional effort. And sometimes that someone is even
the company that created the application and this functionality of
sharing charts that became pretty widely used
actually was one of the contributors to why Helm
became so popular compared to its alternative
tools. So now if you have a cluster
and you need some kind of deployment that you think
should be available out there, you can actually look it up, either using
command line so you can do helm search with a keyword,
or you can go to either Helm's own public
repository, helm hub, or on helm charts
pages or other repositories that are available now.
Apart from those public registries for Helm
charts, they're also private registries. Because when companies
started creating those charts, they also started distributing them
among or internally in the organization. So it made perfect
sense to create registries to share those
charts within the organization and not publicly.
So there are a couple of tools out there that are used as helm
chart private repositories as well. Another functionality
of helm is that it's a templating engine.
So what does that actually mean? Imagine you have an
application that is made up of multiple microservices
and you're deploying all of them in your Kubernetes cluster.
And deployment and service of each of those microservices
are pretty much the same, with the only difference that
the application name and version are different or
the docker image name and version tags are different.
So without helm you would write separate
YAML files, configuration files for each of those microservices.
So you would have multiple deployment service
files where each one has its own application
name and version defined. But since the only difference
between those YAML files are just couple of lines
or a couple of values using helm, what you can do is that
you can define a common blueprint for all the microservices
and the values that are dynamic, or the values that are going to
change replace by placeholders.
And that would be a template file. So the template file would
look something like this. You would have a template file which is standard
YAml, but instead of values in some places you would have the
syntax, which means that you're taking a value from
external configuration and that external configuration.
If you see the syntax here values, that external configuration
comes from an additional YAMl file which is called
values Yaml. And here you can define all
those values that you're going to use in
that template file. So for example here those four values are defined
in an values YAMl file and what
dot values is. It's an object that is being created
based on the values that are supplied via values YAMl file
and also through command line using
set flag. So whichever way you define those
additional values, they're combined and put together in
values object that you can then use in those template files to
get the values out. So now instead of having YAML
files for each microservice, you just have one and you
can simply replace those values dynamically.
And this is especially practical when you're using continuous
delivery, continuous integration for your application, because what you can
do is that in your build pipeline you can use those template
YAMl files and replace the values on
the fly before deploying them. Another use case where
you can use the helm features of
package manager and templating engine is when you
deploy the same set of applications across different Kubernetes
clusters. So consider a use case where you have your
microservice application that you want to deploy
on development, staging and production clusters.
So instead of deploying the individual YAML files separately in
each cluster, you can package them up to make your
own application chart that will have all the
necessary YAML files that that particular
deployment needs, and then you can use them to
redeploy the same application in different Kubernetes
cluster environments using one command, which can also
make the whole deployment process easier. So now that you
know what helm charts are used for it, let's actually look
at an example helm chart structure to have
a better understanding. So typically chart is made
up of such a directory structure. So the top
level will be the name of the chart and inside the directory you
would have following. So chart Yaml
is basically a file that contains all the matter information about the chart
could be name and version, maybe list of dependencies et cetera.
Values Yaml that I mentioned before is place
where all the values are configured for
the template files, and this will actually be the
default values that you can override later.
The charts directory will have chart dependencies
inside, meaning that if this chart depends on
other charts, then those chart dependencies will be
stored here and templates folder is basically where the
template files are stored. So when you execute
helm install command to actually deploy those yaml
files into kubernetes, the template files
from here will be filled with the values from values
Yaml, producing valid kubernetes manifests
that can then be deployed into kubernetes.
And optionally you can have some other files in this folder
like readme or license file et cetera.
So to have a better understanding of how values are injected
into helm templates, consider that in values
Yaml, which is a default value configuration, you have following
three values, image name, port and version.
And as I mentioned, the default values that are defined
here can be overridden in a couple of different ways.
One way is that when executing helm install
command, you can provide an alternative values
yaml file using values flag. So for
example, if values yaml file will have following
three values which are image name, port and version, you can define your
own values yaml file called myvalues
Yaml and you can override one of those values,
or you can even add some new attributes there and
those two will be merged which will result
into a dot values object that will look like this.
So we'd have image name and port from values Yaml and the one
that you overwrote with your own values file.
Alternatively, you can also provide additional individual
values using set flag where you
can define the values directly on the command line. But of course it's
more organized and better manageable to
have files where you store all those values instead of just providing
them on the command line.
Now that you know what helm is and that we're going to use it in
the cluster to install applications,
let's actually install helm itself so that we have helm
command available. Right now we don't have it. And to install helm
we can just check out their official documentation about installing Helm.
Let's search for Ubuntu because that's the server
operating system we're working on and we have two ways
of installing it with apt package manager and snap.
Let's actually go with the apt. I'm going to copy all of these
commands and execute it right here.
And apt get install helm. Let's execute.
And if I do helm now you see that we have the command
available with a version
three six three. Awesome. So we already
have helm installed on the master node,
which means we can use it to install Nginx Ingress
controller in our cluster. There is one thing I want to note about helm,
which is we don't have to explicitly connect helm
command to the cluster. We can simply go ahead and
start executing helm install commands. So you may
be wondering how does helm then know in which cluster
it should install applications inside or how to even connect
to any cluster? Well, in the background helm will
actually use the kubeconfig file that is configured
by default for Kubectl. So the config file in
the Linux user's home directory Kubefolder,
which Kubectl uses to connect to the cluster is also
used by helm command to connect to the cluster.
So whatever Kubectl command is pointing to
will be cluster which helm will connect to. And that is
very convenient because we don't have to do any extra work here.
Awesome. So how do we install a package or application using
helm? Well, we find a helm church that we need. In our
case, this is the ingress Nginx controller that
we want to install and it is actually in the
Kubernetes repository itself. And right here we
have the commands for installing it. So I'm just going to copy
this. Helm Repo Ed will basically just add
a repository where the chart is located and then
it will update the repository. And now we
can install the chart which again we have command for it
right here.
Let's call it Ingress Nginx.
That's the name that you can come up with and give your chart
installation. And this is the repository
name and chart name. So execute.
And we have a nice output that says
chart deployed as well as an example ingress
configuration file right here. So for creating the
first ingress component, you could just copy this
here and get started with it. If I do helm
ls, I will see the chart information namespace
in which the application and all the components
related to it were created, as well as the
chart version and the application version.
And that means we should have new pods running
in a cluster in default namespace. So if I do
kubectl get pod, you see that we have ingress
Nginx controller pod, one replica of
it running in our cluster.
And if I do get service, you see that we
have two services in the cluster. One of them is internal
service and another one is load balancer.
Remember when I mentioned that Ingress application
also needs to be exposed in some way to
the external traffic, either using a node port service
or a load balancer service. And this is exactly the load balancer
service that ingress controller
needs to be accessible from external applications.
And as we learned in a setup like this, load balancer
does not automatically get created by the platform.
So we would have to actually configure it just like we configured
a load balancer for our Nginx service. So the way it's
going to work is we're going to create a load balancer that
will forward the requests to ingress controller
on whatever node port it's available on.
And right here you see the port or node port on
which ingress Nginx controller application is
available. On each of the worker nodes,
there are actually two node ports where the controller
is available. One of them is for HTTP traffic,
that's port 80. Another one is for HTPS
traffic, which is four, four, three. That means
we're going to configure a load balancer with this information.
And this is going to be easy since you have already configured a load
balancer for another service. So let's go ahead and do
that as a next step.
So we can actually get rid of this load balancer here and
create a new one for HTP HTPS traffic.
And let's call it Ingress NginX
controller load balancer. Again, Internet facing,
and this is the load balancer port. So load balancer itself
will be accessible on port 80, which is the default one.
So users don't have to explicitly type it, which is fine.
We're going to leave it at that. And again choose two subnets,
one of them where our work nodes are running.
Next, choose the default security group
and create a new target group. Let's call
it Ingress target group, instance type and
port for HTP traffic,
which as we saw here is 32,675.
And
let's register the two worker nodes that we
have and
create the load balancer.
In our case, again, because this is not an AWS
specific setup, we're just going to do a simple configuration
just for the HTP traffic. So our load balancer
is active, which means using the load balancer's
IP address or the domain name right here,
we can now access the cluster.
So right now, because we don't have anything configured, if I just
type it in the browser and execute, we're going to get a
gateway timeout error, which means we were able
to access the ingress controller. However,
the ingress controller doesn't know what to do with that request
because we haven't configured anything. So it just gives us a
gateway timeout error. But that means we're connecting to
the cluster through NginX controller. And as
a next step we're going to configure ingress controller with
logic of how to route different requests to
our applications. And for that we're going to create an ingress
component.
So think of ingress components as
a configuration piece that we
basically pass on to the ingress NginX controller
application. Telling here is what to do when this
kind of request comes in. So with every ingress component
we create in the cluster, we basically hand over a
new configuration logic to our
ingress controller application. So that's a Kubernetes
native way, by configuring routing logic
in the ingress controller application. So what do we want that routing
logic to be in our case? Well, we want Ingress to
forward any request coming inside the
cluster to NgInX service internal service.
That's what we want. So that's the rule that we're going to configure in
our ingress controller application using the ingress
component. So before that I'm actually going to delete the NgInx
service load balancer and
adjust our service configuration file to
be a cluster IP type,
which means this is only accessible internally and
let's apply it again.
And now we have an internal NgINX service
and basically all the services from now on will
be internal because we have an entry point in the
cluster which is Ingress controller, and all the traffic will
be first accepted by Ingress controller. And Ingress
controller will then decide based on the logic, we configure
which internal service it's going to send that request to.
So forwarding a traffic received on HTP port to
NgInx service, that's what we want to configure. So let's create an
ingress configuration file.
For that, I'm actually going to use the create
Ingress imperative command and then using
dry run option.