Do we have to label other components as well other than pods
like services, deployments, config maps, et cetera.
And does Kubernetes add some of its own labels
to the components? Well, let's see. First of all, as I explained,
we use labels to identify and target any Kubernetes
component. So we can give labels to deployments,
services, config maps, secrets, et cetera, and of
course pods. And even though it's optional
for many components, it's actually one of the Kubernetes
best practices to label all the components.
We can also add more than one label to a
component. Now let's go ahead and label our service.
I'm going to make adjustment directly in the service configuration
file and
in the metadata section where we have name and the labels.
I'm going to add the labels list and add some
labels to our service. Again, when you're labeling services
and deployments together with the pods, it is
a best practice or a standard approach to give
them the same labels. So we could give the
service as well. App Nginx label
and let's add another label just as a test.
Let's do this is service test Nginx
and let's save it. Now, very important to understand
here, we just edited the YAML file,
the configuration file that we have just lying around
on our node. So changing a
YAML file for deployment or service or
whatever component doesn't actually update the service in
the cluster. For that to happen, we have to explicitly
apply that change to the existing service. So Kubectl
apply and providing the configuration
file. And let's see what happens. As you see now,
it says service NgInx, service configured.
So Kubectl apply command is smart enough to
know that we already have a component defined
in this YAML file running in the cluster or existing
in the cluster. So instead of creating a new one, it basically
configures or adjusts its configuration.
If it doesn't find a component defined in this
configuration file, it will create a new one. So instead
of configured it will say service NgINX service created.
And the simple way it can find whether the component exists
or not is using the name of the component.
So this right here, the name will be used to see
whether this component already exists or not.
That means you cannot have two services in
the same namespace with the same
name or two deployments with the same name.
And this applies to all other components.
So now that we applied the configuration changes to our
service, our engineering service should have those
two labels added to that now how do we check
labels of any component? Again, using a
Kubectl describe command that
shows us details of a component will
also show us its labels right here.
And we can check this on any component like
deployments, pods, et cetera. So you can do Kubectl
describe deployment, Nginx deployment.
And this will again give you a bunch of information. And one of them
is labels. Now this may be too much information just
to check the labels for a component.
So as an alternative, what you can do is
you can do Kubectl get deployment for all
the deployments in the default namespace. And you can
add show labels option here.
And this will basically add labels column
here with the list of labels in the same
way you can do it for services.
Another useful usage of labels is that you
can actually select components using the label
instead of its name. So we can do Kubectl get
service and instead of providing the name of the service you
can actually give me all the services that have
this specific label.
Now this may be less interesting if you have just one service
with that label. However, it becomes very useful if
you're selecting pods. So if I had 100
pods in my default namespace and ten of
them were replicas of the same application, if I
wanted to display those ten replicas, I could use
the label that they share because their names will
be different. So again to
check the labels, you see app Enginex.
And again, if I had pods from other applications here and I
just wanted to select app Nginx pod replicas,
I could simply do that using the
label. Another cool usage of labels with
multiple pod replicas is if we want to check logs
of the application for a certain request,
but we don't know which pod replica actually handled
that request. So instead of logging each pod
individually using the pod name, we can show logs
of all pod replicas using their label.
So Kubectl logs and again,
instead of specifying the pod name, we're going to do
label and this will give us
logs of both pods in one output.
Again, this will be especially useful in a more crowded
cluster where we have hundreds of pods and maybe
tens of replicas of the same application. And we wanted
to address all the pod replicas of the same application
in one command.
So we've seen that we can assign labels to the components,
but Kubernetes applications like master and
work processes themselves use labels to
target and identify other components in the cluster. And for that,
Kubernetes actually assigns some of the components
labels automatically. To see that, let's actually check
the pods in Kube system namespace
which is running master and worker processes and do
show labels here. And as you see these
are pods that Kubernetes components that were deployed
by kubernetes. And all of them have labels
here which are used to group multiple pod replicas
together as well as identify specific applications
or pods from other components. In the same way,
our cluster nodes also have
labels. So these are our three nodes.
And in the labels section you see that the master
node has a bunch of labels assigned to it as well as
the worker nodes. And one of these labels is Kubernetes
iohostname that basically identifies
the name of the node as worker one,
worker two, and master as well as an empty label right
here that basically says that this node here,
the master node, has a role of a control plane
component. And we're going to see usage of the
node labels in one of the future lectures.
Now let's say we decide we want to scale our NgInX
application to four replicas instead of two.
Maybe because we want to test something or maybe we want to make the
application more available. One way to do it is to
adjust the replica count in
the deployment configuration file right here. But maybe we
just want to test something without actually changing
the main deployment file. So how can we scale our applications
up or scale them down directly using
Kubectl commands? Well for that there is a Kubectl
scale subcomment that
will help us do that. And if I do Kubectl scale
help, this will give us all the options and usage
of the scale command, which is actually pretty easy.
First of all we can use scale on deployments or
stateful sets. And with replicas attribute
we can set the number of replicas. So I'm going to copy that
and let's say we want to scale deployment called
NgInx deployment to four
replicas and let's execute that. We see it output deployment
scaled. So we should actually see two more pods running
and we know which ones are the newly created pods
by looking at their age. So these two started 6 seconds
ago. These two have been running for some time now.
And the same way we can scale it down
to three replicas.
And you see one pod is being terminated. So that's a way
to quickly scale your application if you want to test
something. Now if
you remember in one of the previous lectures I explained
that making changes to components using
Kubectl subcommands like create,
delete, or in this case scale
is an imperative way and the disadvantage of
it compared to working with Kubernetes manifest files
is that your team cannot review those
changes and you don't have a history of what
you did in the cluster or basically what changes were
made using the Kubectl subcommands
that resulted in the state that we have now in
the cluster. So we don't have a history of those changes.
So in this case no one knows how the current replica count
came to be, but we can overcome that issue
with the imperative commands and add an audit
trail to our changes using
a record option so we can record all the changes that
we make using these imperative commands. And if I
do scale help again,
I see one of the options here which says record
which is set to false by default, and we can basically
turn it on on the scale command to
record the change. The same goes for Kubectl
create command. For example, if you see here, we also
have the same record option.
So this option can be used with almost all Kubectl
subcommands and even the Kubectl apply command
can be recorded with this option.
So what adding this option will do is basically add
an annotation attribute called Kubernetes
IO change cause to
the component with the change cause being the command
you executed. So let's see that in action. I'm going to bring
up the scale command again and let's say
I want to scale it to five replicas now, but I want to
record the change using record
option which we can either specify like this or we can explicitly
set it to true. It's going to be the same.
So let's execute and let's do another
scaling. Let's scale it down to three again and record
that one too and execute. And let's
see that we have three pods that are running now.
How can we check that those two commands were
recorded? Or where is this history of changes?
We can check that using a subcommand called
rollout. Again, if we do help here,
we will see Kubectl rollout options right
here and one of them is a history. So let's
do Kubectl rollout history.
And again let's
see the usage and we have it right
here. So we can see a history of changes
of a specific deployment. We can see a history of changes of
a demon set or a stateful set. So changes
to these three components can be recorded as
a history using this record option.
So I'm going to copy
the command here and we're going to check
the history for our NgInX deployment.
Let's see. And the last command that was recorded is
recorded here as the cause of the change.
Now you understand how deployment can be scaled and also learn
a few useful Kubectl commands along the way and also
how to record Kubectl commands. As a next step,
let's actually test that NgInX application is really accessible
through its service and see how we can talk to it.
For that we're going to deploy another pod in the cluster and we're
going to do a simple curl to our Nginx
applications service. So this is going to be basically a test
pod that we're just going to deploy temporarily. In order
to test that, accessing Nginx application
through its service actually works. So we're going to do a simple curl
command from inside the pod. And this means we
don't need a deployment configuration file for it. We just want to quickly
create a pod, test it, and then we can remove it up to that.
So we're going to create that pod using an imperative kubectl
run commit. So let's do Kubectl run and
let's call this pod test Nginx
service. And we are going to need
an image which is a required attribute because each
pod has to have at least one container based on
some image. And we can actually use the same Nginx image
because Nginx image has curl preinstalled and
that's what we need. And let's execute. So this
should actually start a pod called test Nginx
service. And remember this doesn't have a deployment behind it,
it's purely a pod on its own. Now the pod
is running, but how do we execute commands from
inside the pod? Because that's what we want, right?
We don't want to execute a curl command from the node. We want
to enter the terminal of the pod or environment
of the pod because pod is part of the
pod network in the cluster. And the Nginx service that
we have can only be accessed from within the cluster.
So how do we get into the pod's terminal?
Well, there is an own command for that, which is Kubectl
exec command. And this lets us execute
commands inside the pod. And one option we have to specify
here is it, which stands for interactive
terminal. So we're getting an interactive terminal of the pod
with the name test Nginx service.
And then we have to pass that exit command,
a Linux command for the pod which is
going to be bash. So we are executing a bash command
inside this pod, which will give us an interactive terminal of
that pod. So if I execute this, you see it changed
to the pods environment. So I'm no longer on the
master node anymore. I am inside the test
NginX service pod as a root user,
as you see right here. And I'm seeing the
virtual file system of the pod. And this is actually a great way
to debug your applications by entering
the pod and accessing its file system. Maybe if
you want to check some configurations or execute
commands, et cetera. And if you want to leave the
pod environment and move back to the node, you can
simply do exit, and that's going to be it. So in this case,
we want to again enter the pod, test Nginx
service, and execute curl command to the Nginx
applications service. So first of all, let's do Kubectl
get service. This will give us the name of the service and its ip address,
and let's curl that from
within the pod. So first, what I'm going to do is I'm going
to use the IP address. So let's do HTTP
the IP address. And remember, we configured
the service to be accessible on port 80 80. So I'm
going to copy that and execute. And as you see,
the service is accessible at its IP address at the port.
And we get welcome to NginX.
And now let's check that the service is also accessible using
its name. Again,
copy the name of the service, execute.
And there you go. So we got the same
welcome to NgINX response when we
connected to Nginx using the service name.
And that means that the name of the service was
resolved to its IP address. Now how does that
actually work? So how does the pod know
that whenever it tries to connect to
this service, basically with this name, it should connect
to this IP address. So how does this resolution actually
work in kubernetes? And that's going to be the topic of
our next lecture.
You notice that the request to service is not resolving.
So pod is making a request to a service,
NgINX service, but it gets a message that the service with
the name Nginx service cannot be found.
So you check the cluster to troubleshoot this issue.
You see that service is there with the name.
The pods are running as service endpoints, so everything looks
fine and you don't know what's going on. This means you need to dig
in a little bit and really understand how services work
and how service names are resolved to their IP
addresses. And let's say you enter one of the pods
to debug or troubleshoot this issue a little bit,
just like we did in the previous lecture. And you
test that the service IP address is accessible
and gives you the right results. But when you try to
curl or access the service name, it tells you
that Nginx service could not be resolved. And that
means we have a DNS issue in the cluster,
which means the poll cannot find the IP address
of the service called Nginx service. Now let's
understand what that means and why
it's a DNS issue. To understand DNS in kubernetes,
we first need to understand DNS in general.
So let's start there.
Basically the thing that the whole networking relies on.
So let's see exactly what a DNS is. We know that every computer
on the network is uniquely identified by
its IP address. And we saw that every device
can talk to any other device using its IP address.
But when you visit Facebook application, do you type in
the IP address in the browser? Or when you visit any
other website? You never just type an IP address,
right? Why is that? Because facebook.com
application runs on many computers
which each have their own IP address. A website of
your favorite local restaurant is available on a specific
computer with an IP address. So every single
application that is running on a machine is accessible
by an IP address. So why do we use names
of the application instead of the IP addresses? Simply because
we're not computers. Humans remember words and names better
than IP addresses and numbers. So to make using
the web easier for humans, the concept of mapping
the IP addresses to names was introduced.
So we access every application by typing the name.
But the network, as we saw, doesn't understand the names,
it understands numbers and IP addresses. So under the
hood, that name gets translated into the
actual IP address where that application is
running, which then your computer can send the request to.
And the service that does this translation is DNS.
So using DNS, we can give a unique name
to any IP address. So you can think of a DNS
as an address book or yellow pages of Internet at the
beginning, before the Internet became so popular and so
many websites were created, the DNS entries or
name to IP address mappings were defined
locally on each computer in the etchosts
file. And even today, that's the first location where DNS
service would look to find the IP address of the requested
name. However, as Internet usage grew,
it was not possible to manage all the DNS entries locally
on each computer and a more centralized and scalable
solution was needed. So, considering there are so
many websites and applications in the world and new ones being
added daily. And so many servers in this world connected
to the Internet. How does DNS manage so many addresses
and their names? DNS uses a simple policy of dividing
all these names into different domains or groups. Domain names
follow a hierarchical structure. There are around 13
root domains across the globe, with names from
a to m. And under each root domain you have
a hierarchy of what's called top level domains,
or tlds. There are six original and most common
top level domains, and each domain has a specific
purpose. We have MIl, which is
for military applications. Then we have.
Or this is for educational institutions
and their websites. Then we have, which is more
general purpose and usually used for businesses because
stands for commercial. Then we have,
which is for nonprofit organizations. Usually the next
one is net, originally for
networking technologies like Internet service providers or
any other infrastructure provider companies. But today it's more
general purpose and can be used by all types of businesses.
And finally we have gov, which is for government.
Apart from these original top level domains,
there are geographical domains which were added later.
These are domains for each country. This is used to also
regulate domain names for companies that are registered in that
country. Examples would be de for
Germany, US for uS, UK,
fr for France, et cetera. This makes sense if your
website is in the local language and your visitors
are local from that country, like local restaurants,
shops, et cetera. And finally, a bunch of other domains
were also added, like bees int
dev, et cetera. So basically, whenever someone creates a website,
they can buy a domain name that belongs to one of these domains,
like mywebsite.com or mywebsite Uk.
And you may buy it for a year, and if you don't need it anymore,
someone else can buy the domain name later. Now,
who actually manages these names? Or who can sell those domain
names to you or keep track of which ones are already taken
and which ones are still available? Or who decides
how these domains are grouped or divided? Well, this is all
regulated by a dedicated organization called the Internet
Corporation for assigned names and numbers,
ICANN, which basically
manages all these domain name spaces. And it
also authorized domain name registrars through
which domain names may be registered and reassigned.
And obviously you don't have to remember this organization's name, but I
think it's interesting information to know that there is actually a
dedicated organization that manages all these domain names.
So, as I said, every domain name actually belongs to this root
and one of its top level domains or
geographic domains. Now suppose I want to create my own
website and let people visit it like tech World with Nana
website. First I select the top level domain that I want for
it in my case and create a domain
for techworldwithna.com. Now let's say I have three
servers with three different applications which all belong to my company,
so they are in the techrobena.com domain. I can
assign each one its own domain name using a concept called
subdomains like bootcamp techrobina.com
or workshops techrobina.com and then courses
techrobina.com. And many companies and many organizations
actually use these subdomains for different
applications that all belong to that organization. So each application
may run on its own dedicated server
and each server that has its own ip address will now have a
full domain name with which you can access it.
There's also a fully qualified domain name which will be
courses techworldwin.com where dot at
the end is for root domain, but we don't use the
fully qualified domain names. It works without dot at the end as well.
Great, so we understand what DNS is, but how does your computer
actually use the DNS service to map the domain name
to an IP address? Every computer has a DNS client preinstalled,
so when you open a browser and type in facebook.com,
your operating system will make a DNS query asking
DNS to resolve that facebook.com address or find
the IP address that maps to facebook.com.
The DNS request first goes to the recursive name
server, which is typically operated by your Internet service
provider, and your recursive name server might have the ip address
already stored, but if it doesn't, it will go to
one of the 13 root servers which manage
requests for top level domains. These root
servers are redundantly available all over the world so
that you get your response quickly. The root server will
then look at the address and see and
it sends a response back to the resolver saying, I don't know
what the address of facebook.com is, but here's the address
of the. Coms domain server which you can ask.
The resolver then asks the server
hey, can you give me the IP address of facebook.com?
The server sends a response I don't know the IP
address of facebook.com but here is a list of
the IP addresses of the authoritative name servers
for domain they will know Facebook Com's
IP address. So finally, resolver chooses
the IP address of one of the authoritative name servers
from the list, asking for Facebook. Com's IP
address, and this time the name server responds with the actual
IP address of facebook.com. So now your computer can send
the request to Facebook's IP address. Now imagine
this process happens every time you visit a website for the first
time. But to save time in the future and make things more efficient,
both the recursive name server and your computer
will cache the DNS entries for a while
so that the next time you want to visit the same address,
it won't have to go through this whole process.
Imagine we have two pods and two services with
their IP addresses, and we tell MyApp
pod to talk to MyDB service using the
service name. Applications can only send a request to an IP
address. So how do we tell the pod myapp
what the IP address of the service named MyDb
is? The simplest way would be to write it in its etc
hosts file. As you learned in the DNS prerequisites video,
this is the first place to look for a domain name
to IP address mapping. The same way when myDB pod
wants to talk to myApp service, we can tell it which
IP address myApp service has by
adding the mapping in mydbods etc
hosts file. Now of course, if we have hundreds
of services and all the pods are talking to
all the services, this will be a lot of DNS mappings to
manage per pod. So instead it makes
much more sense to have all these mappings of service domain
names to their ip addresses in a centralized
place instead of each pod having its own huge list
of them. And that centralized place is the DNS
server. So now instead of listing all the mappings in each pod
in the etc hosts file,
you can simply point the pods to
the name server which has all the records. You can
do that by specifying the address of the domain name
server in the etc resolve
confile in each pod. So we have a name server
in the cluster that keeps track of and manages
the list of all the service names and their ip addresses in the
cluster, and all the pods point to it to
resolve service names whenever they want to make requests
to them. And the DNS server in Kubernetes cluster is
core DNS. Remember when we installed the cluster
with kubeadm init command? We saw that two add
ons were deployed in the cluster in addition to the master
and worker processes. There was one of the last phases
of the Kubeadm init command execution, and one
of these addons was core DNS application. And note
that the DNS server used in Kubernetes before
version one point twelve was actually Kubedns
starting from Kubernetes version 112, it was
replaced by core DNS as a recommended DNS
server. And as you probably also remember,
core DNS is running inside the Kube system namespace
and we have two replicas of it. And that is necessary for
redundancy because as you just learned, it is an important
service. And if core DNS application crashed
and it was not available, pods will not be able to resolve
service names and the whole communication in the cluster between the
applications will be broken. So in a production cluster,
you should have minimum of two core
DNS pod replicas, preferably even more.
And this also means that when developers come to you
saying that service name doesn't resolve, you could
first check that the core DNS pods are running and accessible.
And as one way of debugging, you can also check the logs of
the core DNS pods. In fact, let's actually go ahead and check
the logs of core DNS pods. And we actually want to log
both pods at once. So for that let's use the labels
as we learned. Right? So both core DNS pods
have a shared label, this one right here. So we're
going to do kubectl logs in a Kube system
namespace and label of core
DNS doesn't say much right here, but you could check the logs
in case of some issues to troubleshoot the
DNS resolution in your cluster. So the way it works
is that whenever we create a service in the cluster,
core DNS creates a record for that service.
The record maps the name of the service to its IP address.
So using this record, any pod within the cluster can now
reach the service using its name, which we already saw in
the Nginx pod, where we curled the Nginx service
from a test pod. So now as a final step,
let's also check the etcresolve
confile in the pod. We still have the
test pod running in the cluster, and same
way as before, let's actually enter the pod environment using Kubectl
exec command. And inside that we have the virtual
file system of the pod. So let's check etc
resolveconf, which is a file so
we can print the contents. And as you see right here,
it says name server pointing to our
core DNS's ip address. Now let's clarify two
things right here. First of all, how is this
entry configured here? So who tells pod,
basically that the name server in the cluster is
core DNS. The first one is that
this IP address is not a pod IP address of core DNS.
This is actually an IP address of core DNS's service.
So if I exit the pod and
let's check kubectl, get service in
Kubesystem namespace and let's filter it on
DNS using
gorep. And this is a core DNS
service which is actually called kubedns and not core
DNS. That's the name of the service. And this is the
IP address that is specified right here. So we
have one mapping that tells the pod if you want to
resolve any domain name then go and talk to
the name server at this IP address, which is cord
DNS as we learned. So that's the first thing. The second one
is how is this actually configured? So who tells
pod that this is the name server that they
should use to resolve domain names?
That's actually Kubelet's job. So whenever Kubelet
schedules a pod, it automatically generates
this file inside with these contents. And we can
also check that in Kubelet's configuration
which is located in varleep Kubelet
and config yaml file.
And we need pseudo permission here. And right here you see cluster
DNS and the IP address
of the Kubedns,
the same IP address as configured here. So Kubelet actually has
this information and inserts that
into every pod and that is configured right here.
So that's how resolving service names to their IP addresses
is configured in kubernetes.
Now what happens if I create a test
pod in a different namespace than the Nginx
application and its service? Can I still access the
service by using its name? Well, let's try.
Right now we have our test service running in
the same namespace, which is the default namespace
as the Nginx deployment pods as well as Nginx
service. So what we're going to do is we're going to create the
same test pod in a different namespace
and then we'll try to access Nginx service from
there. Right now let's get all the
namespaces that we have right here
and I'm simply going to create a new one using
Kubectl. Create namespace and let's just
call it test namespace. And then I'm
going to create a pod called test
Nginx service. So the pod with the same
name but in a different namespace.
So namespace will be test ns
and not a default. And of course we need the image which is Nginx.
Now remember we were not allowed to create a
pod with the same name in the same namespace, but we
can create pod with the same name in a different namespace.
So let's run this and let's
check that our pod is running. And now
let's actually enter this pod right here and
try to access the service again.
Remember Kubectl exec command
that lets us get an interactive terminal
of any pod. And when
we are working with a non default namespace, remember we always
have to specify the namespace option here
with every command. So this
will let us enter the test Nginx service
running in the test namespace. And let's connect to
the service. First I'm going to use the IP address of
the service and port 80 80
to connect. And let's see we get a reply
back, right, so IP address and port, not a problem.
Now let's use the service name
instead. Nginx service,
which is the name of the service and port.
And as you see, after a couple of seconds we got
a response here that says could not resolve host,
so it's not able to find a service with this
specific name. So why is that? What's happening
here? For each namespace, a DNS server,
which is core DNS in Kubernetes, as we've
learned. So core DNS creates a subdomain.
So all the pods and services are grouped together in
the subdomain of the namespace. So the services
in default namespace actually have
an address of nginxservice default.
In addition to that, all the services of all the namespaces
are grouped together in another subdomain
called service or SVC. So each
service can actually be addressed with service
name namespacename SvC
and finally, Kubernetes DNS created a root
domain for the cluster, which is cluster local.
So the full name of any service in a cluster would be
servicename, the namespace name in
which the service was created, SVC cluster
local, and that's also called a
fully qualified domain name of any service or
FQDN. But conveniently, as you saw,
we don't have to specify the fully qualified domain
name for services when we connect to them.
That's why we were able to connect to the service
from this pod right here, just using the
name of the service. However, if the service is
in a different namespace, we can't just address
it with only a name. We actually need the service name
and namespace name. So the way it works is that when a pod
tries to connect to a service using the name of the service,
Kubernetes will actually try to resolve this and
it will try to find NgInX service in the same
namespace as the pod that is trying to send a request to
it. So in the test NS namespace there is
no NgINX service, and that's why we get could not
resolve host. So if we want to access
services from another namespace, we have to explicitly
tell the domain server the subdomain
of namespace name as well. So instead
of NgInX service, we're going to do nginxservice default
and let's try again. And there you go.
So again, whenever we're talking to services in
the same namespace, we can use just the name of the service.
Whenever we want to talk to services from other namespaces,
we have to specify the name of that namespace as well,
and that's going to be the domain name of the service.
So this is still a short form of a fully qualified
domain name of the service, which would be NginxService
default SBC cluster
local. So if we execute this,
this should work as well. And as you see, it does.
Now why is that? That we don't have to specify the
whole name and we can actually just use a shortcut which
is either service name and namespace name
or just the service name. So how does that
resolve to the services fully
qualified name? Well, that's because of an
entry in the resolve confile right here which
says search and then a list of subdomains
in which a domain name will be searched,
basically. So this means whenever pod sends a request to a
service name, the domain name server will try to resolve
the service name in one of those domains. And that's the
reason why we don't have to specify the whole path, because that will
be automatically appended, so to say, whenever you do
a search. So if the NgInX service was in the same namespace as
the pod, we would not have to specify the namespace
because the core DNS will then search for this service in
test NS domain. So in this domain right
here, it will find one and it will give us a result.
And that's why when the service is not in the same namespace,
it's not going to be found here, and we need to
specify a namespace name so it can
be found in the next domain. So that's
basically how it works.
So if I enter the test NginX
service in the default namespace and print
the resolve contents you see instead of test namespace
here, one of the domains in the search is default
namespace. So as a troubleshooting tip, if you have an
issue where accessing a service using just the
name and the namespace does not work,
but specifying a fully qualified name does work.
It means your cluster has an issue resolving the
service names and you would know where to debug that service
names are mapped to service's ip address
and how it's resolved in the cluster.
So where do these IP addresses of the services come from?
Because this is not same as the pod IP
addresses which we can see right here.
This is in the completely different range. So where is it
defined and can we change it if we wanted to?
Well, let's see. As you see, the Kubernetes services here
have a type of cluster IP. So they get a
cluster internal IP address which
makes them accessible to the applications and pods running
inside the cluster. And this IP address range
is defined in the Kube API server configuration.
If you remember, the Kube API server which is one of
the control plane processes has a static pod
manifest that Kubeadm generates, right?
And they are located in manifests
folder. So if I check the Kube API
server manifest file
and we have lots of different options here when starting up the
Kube API server application and one of them
is service cluster IP range.
So this is actually a parameter that is passed on
to the API server and this is the cider
block of the service IP addresses.
Again, remember these are internal service IP addresses that
only the applications in the cluster can use to access the services.
And as you see it is in the range of 10960
zero, which is exactly the range
from which we have these two IP addresses.
So that's where the service cider block
is defined. But as we know KubeadM provisions
and creates the Kube API server configuration.
So how does KubeaDm actually get that? Well, if we look
at the KubeadM init command and
its options, one of the options that we
see here is service cider. So this is where
you can actually specify an alternative
IP address of service virtual IP addresses.
And the cider block that we saw is actually a default that
is used when you do not specify a different one,
which is again a range from 10960 zero.
Alternatively, you can also check
the KubeaDM default configuration values
by printing Kubeadm config emit
command defaults.
And I misspelled the print and there you go. This actually
gives you a nice list of all the default values
that Kubeadm will initialize your
cluster with. One of them, as you see is the DNS type which is
set to core DNS, the ETCD data directory.
And you have the networking configuration here which defines
the DNS, the roots domain of Kubernetes cluster which
is cluster local and the service subnet again
which we saw is the default service IP range.
So if you needed to change that value you could specify
it on init command as
a parameter service cider. But what if you wanted
to change the service cider block after you have
initialized the cluster? Well for that you
can actually adjust the Kube API server manifest
file and specify a different cider block there.
And let's actually do that. So one thing to note about
static pods is that whenever I make a change in
the manifests folder to one of the existing files
or I create a new file, a new pod manifest file,
Kubelet will actually automatically detect the change and reload
all the pods that got updated or basically all the configuration
that got changed. So going inside let's
actually adjust the service cluster IP range and let's
set it to 20960
and let's save the change. And now if
I do Kubectl pod in the Kube system
namespace, you see that the connection refused.
Why? Because we just changed the API server configuration.
So API server is actually restarting so we can't
connect to the cluster. This is going to take some time till
the API server is fully restarted and
after that we can try to connect again. And there you go.
After a couple of seconds we're connected to the cluster and Kube
API server got restarted.
Right age is 11 seconds. So it was just
started. Now the question is what happens
to the services that have been created in the
cluster before we made the update? Let's actually check that.
I'm going to do Kubectl get service and as you
see they have the same IP addresses as
before. Nothing changed here. So the new cider block
actually applies to the services that get created after
we made the change. So all the previous services will keep their
old IP addresses. So to test a new cider block for
the services, let's actually create a new service.
And again when we want to test something quickly
we can do that using Kubectl's imperative commands.
So let's see how we can create a service
using Kubectl create service command. Let's get
help here. And as you see the
first thing we need to specify is the type of the service which
is the cluster IP. That's an internal service.
You see the type right here. Again, let's get help. And we see
usage here. Cluster IP, we need
the name of the service. Let's call these test
new cider and we're going to have to specify
at least one port. So let's do 80.
80 service was created,
let's do Kubectl get service again. And as you
see the new service got an IP address from
the updated service IP range with
kubernetes and specifically with Kubectl command,
much more efficient.
As you see, we work a lot with Kubectl command for configuring
the cluster, creating components, debugging, troubleshooting and
so on. So we're using this command a lot and it could be
annoying to type Kubectl command all the time.
So as a quick optimization, I suggest you use
an alias for that command that is much
simpler and faster to type. So one common alias for
Kubectl could be K. So we said Kubectl
command alias to K and this will create an alias in
your current session. So it's not going to change it in the
whole system. This will be just temporary for that active
session that you're in. So it doesn't make this change
permanent. And if I execute this, I can now use K
instead of kubectl to interact with the
cluster, right? So kgetpod and
so on. And this small optimization can actually make your
work more efficient. So that's the first quick
tip. A second one is related to creating Kubernetes
manifest files in an efficient way. We said that when testing and
creating pods or services to just try something out,
we use imperative commands. However, if you want to create
permanent components that will stay in the cluster,
we prefer configuration files for that,
especially because we want to have a history of what
components we created with what configuration, and they
may end up in a git repository that the whole team
can work on. So one way that I
showed you to create configuration files was going
to the Kubernetes documentation and basically grabbing a
service example or deployment example and
so on. Now this may be time consuming and
you may not want to scroll through the Kubernetes documentation
every time you want to find an example of one of
the components. Plus you may not want to have to copy and
paste the contents from here to your
terminal session, et cetera. So a more efficient way of creating
Kubernetes configuration files for different components is
actually using Kubectl command. So let's see how
that works. What I'm going to do is I'm going to bring up one
of the previous commands where we created a service of
cluster IP type called Testnew cider
with this configuration in the cluster.
And this is an imperative way of creating a service. And it just gave
us a service in the cluster. That's it. Now instead of creating
a service with this command, we can actually forward
the results into a configuration file.
So we can actually generate a Kubernetes configuration file
from the imperative commands. And the way we do that
is we tell kubernetes do not actually execute this.
And we do that by using dry run
option. And it has a couple of values. One of them is a client.
So we are saying do not create a service. We are just
trying to do a preview here. So that's one option.
The second one is the preview that we're getting
by not actually executing the command. We want
that preview in a yaml output. So give
me a yaml output of this command's preview and
I want to save that yaml file into a file called
my service yaml.
So let's see what happens. First of all, kubernetes did not try
to create service because we already have a service
with this name in a cluster and if it did we would
have gotten an error. Instead we don't get any output because
everything was forwarded or redirected
to this file here. So if I do ls I have
my service yaml and let's actually see
what's inside. And there you go. We have an
example service file that we just generated by
using an imperative Kubectl command. And once
you have that blueprint, so to say you can then go ahead and
set and change all those values. You have a couple
of redundant attributes that get generated that you
can actually get rid of them, like creation, timestamp,
maybe labels and status which
gets generated and edited by kubernetes. So actually you
don't need that. So you can get rid of them as well. So you can
clean up all this stuff and then set the values that you want.
And by the way, in vim editor, if you want to
delete lines instead of characters one by one,
you can go from insert mode or from edit mode to command
mode by hitting escape and then
two times the key d. So DD
will remove one line from the file and
back to the insert mode. As I said, you can
change all the values here and the port that we set, port and target
port are already set here. So you have that already
configured. Let's actually try to do the same for a deployment
file. So I'm going to exit
here and let's do Kubectl create
deployment again? Let's use
help to navigate here so we have deployment
name of the deployment let's call this my deployment
image of the pod in the deployment.