Values. So for example, if we have deployed
attributes, you can say true or false.
And in yaml you can also express boolean expressions
with yes or no. So let's say deployed yes and
also with on and off. So all these three pairs of
values are expressions of boolean values.
And you also see the syntax highlighting is different.
So this is a list and these are the items of the
list. And I can add second item
app, let's say shopping cart,
whatever.
Let's say port is 9002. Then we have version,
which is 1.9.
And this way you can define lists of objects,
but you can also define lists of simple values. So for example,
if you had a list of just the microservice names,
you could do like this and
it, and that would be fine as well. And you can also use lists inside
of a list item. So for example, if you have multiple versions
of shopping cart, for example, that you want to list here for some
reason, I don't know, you can actually list them
here. So I can do versions. Let's say you have 2.0
and then you have 2.1, et cetera.
And I'm going to copy that also in the
validator. And here you see that the dash
position, you can actually use different indentations for
that. So I have an indentation here but I don't have here, so that's
fine as well. I could do like this, or I can align
it on the parent attribute. So don't be confused.
If you see different alignments of the lists,
both work because Yaml recognizes that
it's a list item. What will not work is if you don't align
the list items using indentations. So for
example, if it was one space off,
then the validator will be red.
So some small details there also know that if you
have primitive items in the list, like this one for example,
so not the object items but the primitive ones, you can also express
it in a different way. And this is how with the different syntax,
you have square brackets and you can put those values
inside like a list, which makes it actually more
readable if you have just simple data types and not objects.
Let's validate that as well, to make sure you can have
strings here as well, or a mix of them.
Doesn't matter. Now this is really some of the basics of
Yaml syntax, so to make it more
practical and realistic, let's actually look at a real Kubernetes
Yaml example to see how this basic syntax is
expressed there. So I'm going to clean this up and let's
look at a pod configuration. So this is basically the
main part where the metadata and kind,
et cetera, is defined as you see, these are super simple
key value pairs. And then you have these objects
that we just saw with hierarchy, with indentations. So you
have a metadata object and inside that you have another
labels object. And here you have the specification
and containers. Maybe you are familiar with this already.
And in containers is a list.
So each container item,
so to say, has to start with dash and indentation.
And there we have the name of the container,
have the image. Let's use Nginx.
Then you have ports, which is another list.
So again we start with dash to
list the ports. And then you have the attribute
which is container port value.
There inside container you also can have volume
mounts, which is another list.
So here you list all your volumes and this is a list of
objects, again, where you have key value pairs. Let's use,
I don't know, Nginx volume and
mount path.
And this is how a pod configuration will
look like. So you have again basic building blocks,
key value pairs, objects and lists, and then lists
inside of that list item. And since containers
is also a list, you can have multiple
containers inside. And for example, if I were to
define a sidecar container, I would have another
item expression. And here I would say this
is my sidecar container.
And again image some image, et cetera.
Also another example that I also showed in one
of my videos is where we deployed a curl
image as a sidecar. And inside
of that container configuration we also had these two lines.
I'm actually going to copy them. And here you see that
this is this alternative syntax of defining lists.
So arguments is a list and we use it like this.
And then we have the two items here,
one and two. So knowing how YAml syntax works
should make it easier to understand the Kubernetes
configuration file structure better. Another important
concept of YAml syntax is when you have
multiline strings. So for example,
file contents, multiline string,
let's call it the attribute. And instead of writing
this multiline string here with the carriage,
I can write it actually on multiple lines like
this. So I don't need that thing anymore.
So this is a
multiline string and this
is the next line, et cetera,
right? And the way I can do that is using the
pipe symbol. So Yaml will see that character and
will interpret everything here as a multi line text. So these line breaks
will actually stay. Another case could be if you
have this super long string, which has to be on a single
line. So for example this is a single line
string that should be all on
one line. And some
other stuff, let's put dots here.
And in that case obviously you don't want the line carriages here,
but you also don't want to write this all out on one line because it's
just not very readable and that's
why you want to, for readability you still want to display
that here in the Yaml file itself, but you want Yaml
to interpret it as a single line. In this case instead
of pipe you actually replace it with a greater than
sign or with this angle bracket and this
will be interpreted as single line. Now this is just some
random example. So let's actually see some real
use cases. I have a config file Yaml here
from kubernetes which I have used in one of my tutorial videos.
And here you see the basic key value stuff
and here you have the name of the attribute, you can call it
whatever you want. And here we use that pipe and
these are actually the contents of the file. This is going to be displayed exactly
like this with line carriages because this has to be each one on
its own line. And this way you can actually write
configuration files for different applications. Like this
one is for mosquito. You also have maybe fluenty and
they have their own different formats and you can write the whole thing as
a file represented by multiline string
in Yaml. Another example of using this multiline
string that you may actually encounter in Kubernetes configuration
files is this one right here. So this
is part of configuration of a pod. So you have this command attribute and
here you see the familiar list.
And here again you have this pipe that is followed
by multiline string. And this is an example of kibana that I found.
So basically what it does is that it executes a shell command
and this is a shell script. So you can actually put the whole contents of
a shell script as you would have that as a shell script file.
After that pipe symbol as a multiline text and
this will execute as a shell script. Basically one
thing that I've also needed to use in Yaml was
environmental variables. So for example you have a pod that has
environmental variables defined inside and you have to
use one of those inside the pod configuration. You can
actually access them using a dollar sign inside
your Yaml configuration. So this is an example of a
Mysql pod and here the same thing that I
showed you before. So you have the command and here in
this line we're executing a Mysql command and I am accessing
the environmental variable that is available inside
the pod using the name of the environmental variable and
the dollar sign before that, which if you need
that might come in handy because I believe this specific concept of
using environmental variables in Yaml isn't very well documented.
Yaml also has a concept of placeholders.
One of its use cases is in helm, for example, and this
is how it looks like. So basically, instead of directly writing the
values inside, you define placeholders and the syntax
for using placeholders is double curly braces around
that placeholder and this value gets replaced using
template generator. And I believe the same concept
is used in ansible as well. So again, if you use helm
or ansible for example, and you see the syntax, you should know what
it stands for. And lastly,
inside one yaml file you can actually define multiple
components and you can separate these components using
three dashes like this. So for example, if I
have a yAml file where I want to put all my configurations, I can
separate them using these three dashes and
this will be a valid yaml. And this can be very handy in kubernetes,
especially where you have multiple components, maybe for one service,
and you want to group them in a single Yaml file. So for that
use case, this is the way to go.
You have learned theoretically what Kubernetes is
its architecture and components, as well as how
to create these components. But to see that all in action,
we first need to create a Kubernetes cluster. So let's
see what options we have for creating a Kubernetes
cluster and how the process of moving to Kubernetes
for it teams actually looks like.
Here is our background story.
Your team has decided to move their application to
Kubernetes cluster. So you all gather in a
meeting room to consider different options you have available.
You discuss whether to use managed Kubernetes solution from
one of the clouds or go for a self managed Kubernetes
cluster. Finally, you decide to go for a self managed Kubernetes
cluster because of more control and flexibility.
So now your task is to
set up Kubernetes cluster from scratch on bare servers.
Cool. As a next step, you also go through
cluster size and configuration options.
You decide to start with one master and two worker nodes
to set up the development environment where you can start deploying
your applications. Once that setup is completed,
your plan is to then replicate the
cluster for test and production environments with more master
nodes and worker nodes for high availability.
So this is your chance to test around and learn all the
things without any fear of destroying something. You also
decide that you will install Kubernetes cluster on Ubuntu servers.
Now what about the size of the servers? How much
cpu or ram should each server have
so that we can use them as Kubernetes cluster nodes?
You check out the Kubernetes documentation page and see
the minimum requirement of server resources is at least
2gb of ram and two cpus per
node. So that's going to be the minimum size of your
servers. Once you have defined all these criteria,
you ask your IT operations team to make these servers available
for your project so you can get started. It team
gives you three Ubuntu servers with the requested
resource sizes together with the list of their
public IP addresses. Plus your users access
to the servers is already configured so you can ssh
into them and get started right away.
Now of course, for this course, since we don't have an IT
operations team, we're going to spin up these servers with
the right resource requirements ourselves very
easily on AWS platform. And I want to make
two notes here. First, this exact setup
of creating a self managed Kubernetes cluster from scratch on
AWS instances is very common and many companies
and projects actually use it, so you might actually encounter
this in practice very often. And second,
this course is not AWS specific. So if
you have Ubuntu machines already or want to use virtual
machines from another platform, that's absolutely fine too.
So setting up those virtual machines is going to be our first task.
So let's go ahead and do it.
Who will set up the cluster on AWS servers?
Like I show you in the demo, you will need to open
an AWS account and also understand some really
basic concepts of AWS and how to configure
servers on it. So in this video we will cover all the basics
that you need to get started on AWS. If you
are already familiar with AWS, or if you
will be installing the cluster somewhere else, you can skip
this video.
In order to create an account, you basically just have to fill out some forms,
including your address information, credit card information and
so on. Because AWS wants to make sure that
people who are creating accounts are verified and
are registering with valid data. And I will put a link below
for a guide of how to create an account that you can follow.
And once you have an account, you get a
free tier offer from AWS. So what does that actually
mean? On AWS documentation
you have this free tier page that basically lists all the
components, all the services of AWS that you
can use for free for one year after registering
an account. And some of them or some of the most important ones are
the EC two instance, which is the virtual server which
we are going to be creating on AWS as well as
some storage and so on. So you can take advantage
of that free tier account on AWS.
Now by default when you create an account on AWS,
you have a root user. This user gets
created automatically and this user has access
to all the services and all the features.
So it has unlimited privileges to do whatever you want
in your account, including the billing part,
account settings and so on. So the first thing we want to do
when the account is registered is create an
admin user that has less privileges than root
user, but it will have all the privileges that we need
to create EC two instance, deploy some applications on that.
And this is the first thing that AWS also advises
to do for security reasons. So if you
go inside the IAM service, you will see
the configuration dashboard. So we can create users
groups and permissions here and manage all
the stuff here. Now admin user can also have
permission to create users,
assign roles to them and so on. So you can have one admin user
to manage and administer the whole AWS account,
but it will still have less privileges than the root user.
For example, it will not be able to access the billing and
credit card information. And then using that admin
user you can actually create other users and give them other
permissions for team members. For example,
if you have a DevOps team that all use AWS
and configure stuff on there, obviously you need to give them
all permissions and access to EC two
and maybe some other services. So the admin user can
be the one that administers all of this.
So now let's create a user admin
that has admin privileges to do stuff
on AWS services. We don't need a group for that because
it's just going to be one user and the only one with admin access.
So let's create it. So here we have an add user button,
let's call it admin. And we can give a
user two types of access. It could be either access
through the console in the UI. So basically you can
log in on the UI and then do stuff
through the UI, like configure stuff, change stuff and so on.
And you can also have a programmatic access.
This is when you can execute different tasks
from your command line, and this can be either through AWS
command line interface or in our case, we're going to use
terraform commands to access AWS. So we need programmatic
access for the admin user to execute terraform
commands. And you can decide whether a user
has one of those access types
or maybe both. In this case we can give admin both types
of access because we want to be able to access the
UI console with it. So we want to be able to log in with
this user, but also execute things from
command line. And as you see, the management console access
displays some other options. Because if we
are going to log in with this user, we need a password
for the user as well and we can let it auto generate a
password. And with this option we can
force the user, the admin user on the first login
to reset their password. So the UI access
will basically be through username and password username here
password auto generated and the programmatic
access will be the keys. So from the command
line we're gonna need access keys or secret
access key to log into AWS and then execute
some commands. Let's go to next.
Now here we can create a group that the user can be
part of. It is actually the best practice to have all the users
in a group and then to assign the permissions to
the group rather than directly to user. But the admin
user is going to be the only one in the group. So we can actually
skip creation of group. So we can assign a
permission to the user directly. And for that we are going to
go to attach existing policies directly.
And this is a list of all the permissions or all
the policies that we can choose from.
And this is a pretty long list because you have
granular permission policies in AWS.
So you can basically decide
for each single service what type of access
you want to grant a user. And this actually is
good because it supports the best practice of
giving the user the least privilege they need. So if a user needs
the read only permission for a service, you can give a user
read only permission rather than full access. So admin
user is going to get administrator access,
which basically includes all the policies
and all the permissions that are needed
for administering your AWS account.
So we're going to choose administrator access policy and
go to the next page.
You can also add tags to the user,
which is basically additional information like metadata
about the user. If these are individual team members in
your organization, this could be an email address description
or job title, name, surname, et cetera.
It's optional though. And we're going to skip this for admin user.
And next. And this is our summary page.
So we have created an admin user. We're giving it
access to login through a web console. The password
will be generated as well as programmatic access
from the command line interface.
And it has administrator access privileges,
so all the permissions it needs to administer the
AWS account. Let's create the user.
And here you have all the information, all the secret information
as well for the user. So password,
you're going to need this one to log in to the console.
And these two are the keys to access
the AWS account and the services from
admin user from your command line. So save all this information
and those keys securely.
So download this file and we're going to reference that later.
And as a next step, we're going to log into Ui using this password
and change the password because we have configured it this way.
So let's sign out as a root user and log in with the
admin user. Again,
log back in, and in the sign in page you
have selection between root user and IAM user.
Let's choose this one. The id or account id of
your user is also in this downloaded file. If you
open it in the console login link, you have this
id here, you can use a link directly to go to the
login page like this.
And this id is going to be filled automatically. So this is the
account id. And here you have the username,
we called it admin and the password which is also in this
file.
And since we've configured it, we have to change the password.
And as you see, we are logged in as admin user
and we can configure services and do stuff now with admin
user.
Now whenever you create an account in each region,
you will have something called a VPC.
So VPC actually stands for virtual private
cloud. So if you go through the services here, all services
list in the networking and
content delivery part, we have this VPC service.
And right now I'm in the Frankfurt region.
And here you see I have a VPC, a default one that
gets created with some other configuration as
well. And if I switch to another
region, for example Europe, Paris,
here I also see a VPC. So I haven't created any of
this. This is out of the box by default in each
region. So VPC in AWS is
basically your private network, right? When you
create resources, virtual servers and so on,
on AWS, you obviously don't want other AWS users
or other AWS accounts to have access to
your resources, right? You want to protect them and you want
only you to have access to them. So because of that you can create
this virtual private cloud on AWS infrastructure
that only you have access to, and you create this VPC
in a specific AWS region. So again,
region is basically one of
those regions in a list. So for example in Paris
region in EUS three, I can create as
many vpcs as I want. However,
region in AWS consists of multiple
availability zones. Availability zone,
in very simple words, is basically a data center of
AWS with all those servers that runs
the whole infrastructure. So the virtual machines
that you spin up in your AWS will actually run in
one of those AZ because these are the actual
physical locations where the servers will run. So VPC
will actually span all the availability zones in
that specific region. So here you see Paris
has three zones and VPC actually spends all
these three zones. So in each region,
basically VPC isolates a space where you are
creating your virtual instances, your servers,
maybe database instance, some other components from different
services, because obviously this is a data center
where others also rent virtual servers,
create components. So they might actually be running on the same physical
machine, same computer, but they will be
isolated in private networks
with vpcs.
And for bigger corporations that have
much more complex application setups, they can
actually use multiple vpcs and manage multiple of
these private networks in different regions.
Now what does this VPC include?
Here you see we are in the VPC dashboard
and we have a bunch of other stuff in here.
It is basically a virtual representation of
network infrastructure. When you have servers physically in your
company, which was a traditional way of hosting
servers and applications before cloud, you have Sys administrators
that set up, configure and manage this whole network. They set
up the router, they do all the network configuration,
configure, firewall and so on. So all of this
physical network infrastructure is basically now
moved in cloud, and VPC is the representation of
this. And the reason why you have this
default VPC in each region is that whenever you create an
EC two instance, it has to run inside a VPC
or whatever component you're launching. It has to run, it has to start
inside a VPC. Another thing you see here
is subnets. So we have three
subnets, and subnets are
subnetworks. So VPC is the whole private network, and subnets are
basically components or subnetworks of
the VPC. While VPC spans the whole region,
all the availability zones,
subnets span individual availability
zones. So for each three zones you'll have
their own subnet. So it's like a private network inside
a network. Another interesting thing
in the VPC part is that
obviously whenever you create a virtual server,
it has to get an IP address. And in
VPC you have a range of private or internal
IP addresses. And that range is actually also
defined by default and you can even change it.
So if I go inside VPC, here you have
a range of IP addresses. So whenever you
create a new instance, a new EC two instance,
an IP address will be assigned to it from this
range. So internal or private IP address
is not for Internet traffic, but rather
for traffic inside the VPC. So when you have
multiple servers, multiple components inside
the VPC, they need to communicate with each other, right? So you have
an instance with web application, another instance with database
application, maybe a third one with some other service,
they all need to communicate. So private IP address is
what allows them to talk to each other.
So the IP address range is defined on a VPC
level and then each subnet then gets its own
IP address range. The private IP address range
from that total range, right, gets like a sub range.
So to say here you see those sub ranges defined.
Now obviously when we deploy our web application
on EC two instance, we want it to be accessible from Internet,
right, from outside. And for that, in addition to private
IP address, we need to assign it a public IP
address. And this is also configured
in VPC service. So when we create
an EC two instance, it will get a private IP address
from the range of the subnet inside which that
instance will start. And it will also get a
public IP address, internal one for internal communication
inside the VPC and a public IP address
for accessing it through the browser. For allowing
Internet connectivity with your VPC,
you also have an Internet gateway component.
So this basically connects VPC to
Internet to the outside world so that you can get traffic
inside your VPC to your web servers, for example. And then
you can also send traffic outside if
you want to download some stuff from Internet on
your components, et cetera. Now obviously in
addition to all of this network configuration,
you need to secure your components, right? So for
example, you want to control what traffic
enters your VPC or what traffic reaches individual
instances and components in your VPC or in
your subnets, and you want to control what traffic goes out, right? So this is
a firewall configuration basically for your VPC and
for individual instances. Now you can configure that security
control on multiple levels in VPC
and AWS makes it actually pretty flexible
and granular of how you can configure all
of this stuff, not just security, but the IP address ranges,
the route tables and so on. And that's why you
have this pretty big list of things that you can configure.
However, in many cases you will not need some
advanced network configuration. Most of this stuff is
configured by default as you see here because you have these
components already created and configured with some default configuration.
And in most simple applications you will not need
to do any crazy configurations here.
And since this whole network is private and
by default closed to the outside world so no
access from Internet. Of course for your web applications you
want to configure some Internet access, right? As well as you want
to ssh into your servers from your laptop.
So you want to configure some kind of external
access. And for that you have components
inside that VPC service called network acls
which are basically firewalls or firewall rules
for subnets so you can configure this per subnet
and in addition to that you have security
groups which are again firewall rules but on a
virtual machine level. So inside the VPC
we have the subnet and inside subnets we're going to have
EC two instances which are basically the virtual servers
and we can configure firewall rules on that
virtual server level using security groups.
So you create both of these components on a VPC level and
then you assign the necklace to individual subnets
and assign security groups to individual instances or
components inside that VPC.
We're going to provision infrastructure where
we will install and set up a Kubernetes cluster.
And as I said, we're going to go through a simple process of provisioning instances.
So basic virtual machines on AWS platform,
one server for a master node and two servers for
two worker nodes. So what I'm going to do is I'm going
to go to EC two service. So these are the instances
I'm in the region which is closest to me. So you
should actually choose a region which is closest to your physical location.
And then basically we're going to create instances for
our cluster. So launch instances and we
are going to go with Ubuntu and I'm going to choose the latest version which
is 2004. Select this one.
And now we have to choose the size. And as
we saw in the Kubernetes documentation, the cluster nodes have
a minimum resource requirement so it has to be minimum
of 2gb of ram and two cpus. So that's the
criteria we're going to use to choose server.
So right here I have a virtual machine with two cpus
and 4gb of ram. So this looks like a
good fit for cluster node. So I'm going to choose t
two medium. And also as I explained
in the video about Kubernetes architecture, master nodes
usually need less resources than worker nodes,
which is logical because worker nodes are the ones where
the actual applications, our microservices
or databases or whatever services we need are going to
be running. Master nodes will only have the control plane
applications running on them, which is just a handful of applications.
So what we're going to do is we're going to choose the smaller one which
is t two medium with the minimum requirement
for a master node. And for the two worker nodes
we're going to use servers which are a bit larger,
which is going to be t two large. If you want for
this course specifically you can actually select t two medium for all
three nodes. But just so you know, this is going to be a more realistic
setup where you have one smaller master node and the work
nodes will be larger. So once that's selected I'm
going to click on next and here you have a bunch of
configuration which we don't actually care about right now. And we have
one instance, right, so we are launching one master node with this
size. So it's going to be one here. And actually
I'm not going to change any of the default configurations. So I'm going to click
review and launch directly without
going through all the steps. And this will give us a
review of our instance which is the operating system image. We're using
the instance type security group which by default
has ssh port enabled so we can access it from
anywhere. And some other stuff I'm going to do launch
and this will prompt me to create a key pair or
ssh key pair for the server.
And this basically means that using this ssh key I'm
going to be able to ssh into the server from
my machine. So we're going to create a new key pair
and we're going to call this Kubernetes node and very important
to download this key pair, right. We need this
key locally on our laptop so that we can use it
when connecting to the server through
ssh. So I'm going to download this key pair.
There you go. So key pair was created on
AWS and I got a copy of that key,
the private key on my laptop, so I can use that key
to connect to the server, which means anybody who does not have this
key will not be able to connect to the server.
And we're going to launch the instance.
This is the instance id that has been launched and is being
initiated. So if I click on it, you see it's
in a running state and still initializing. So that's
one server that we just provisioned with t two,
medium size and this is going to be our master node
and we can actually call this master node
in the name and now we can provision the
two worker nodes again. Launch instances,
same operating system ubuntu as
I said, I'm going to choose t two large, you can actually choose medium
because we're not going to be deploying so many applications on the
worker nodes, but this will actually be the
realistic setup. So with t two large I'm
going to click on next because we need two instances
of this server, not just one for
two worker nodes. Again I'm going to leave everything at
defaults and do review and launch same default
configuration and launch. Now I can
create new ssh key pair for these two
servers or I can reuse the one that I created for the
master node which means I would be able to connect all three servers
with the same key, which is going to be practical. So that's what we're going
to do. Choose an existing key pair and I'm going to choose Kubernetes
node and click on this acknowledgment.
And obviously I don't have to download this because I already have that
locally and launch instance and
now two instances are being launched. Let's click on one of those.
I'm going to remove the filter and there you go.
And we can actually call them worker nodes.
The name doesn't have to be unique or for more differentiation we
can also do worker node one,
worker node two,
and after a couple of minutes all the servers are fully
initialized and ready to go. So basically we just
created or provisioned infrastructure of three
servers, three Ubuntu servers that we're going to
use to install and create cluster from scratch.
Now these are just bare servers. There is nothing on them that
related to Kubernetes. So we're going to have to install
everything needed step by step. Node that we're going to work
with is going to be master node. So in a Kubernetes cluster we
first have to set up and configure a master node which
will give us a Kubernetes cluster and then we can connect or
join any additional nodes to that configured
cluster. So we have these three servers which are
all empty. There is nothing Kubernetes related on them and
we just name them master node, worker node,
because we're going to turn this instance into a master node
and these two instances into worker nodes.
So as a final step of our infrastructure setup we're
going to test connecting to one of the servers. Let's actually
choose the masternode server and connect to it
with this key that we downloaded from AWS.
So I'm going to go to the terminal, the key has been downloaded
in downloads folder and
kubernetes node. And what
I'm going to do first is I'm going to move that file into
my SSH folder
because that's where the private ssh keys
should be located by standard.
And once I have moved it there one more thing
I need to do is I need to restrict
permissions on that key. So right now
if I do ls minus l, you see
that I have a read write permission as an owner and
it has read permission for other groups. And if I
try to use this key to connect to the server on aws
I'll get a warning that the file is not protected
because it has two broad permissions.
So we have to restrict that and we're going to do that using
change mod command and we're going to set the permission to 400
which will translate to read permission for
the owner, zero permissions. So basically no
permissions here for the group and no
permissions for anybody else.
It and let's execute. And let's see again.
There you go. So now I will be allowed to use this
private key to connect to the server. How do we
connect to the server? Very easy actually we go and grab the public
key of the server first of all because we need that to connect
to it. And right here we have the public IP
address. You can also see that in the list view right here you
have the public IP addresses of all the servers.
So I'm going to copy it and
we're going to do ssh the
public IP address of the server. And before the
server we need to specify a user.
If I leave it like this by default Linux will
attach my current user as a username and
will try to connect like this. But obviously there
is no this user on the server right.
So I have to specify the user which AWS
actually creates on that instance when it's provisioned.
And on Ubuntu instances the default user
is ubuntu and I know that from the documentation.
So for each instance you can actually find out what the default user is
that you connect with. So we're connecting to the server
with a default user which already exists on the server
and obviously we are going to need the private
key to connect to it, which is this
one right here. So basically we're connecting to this server with
credentials which is username and
the private ssh key. So if I execute this command
on the very first connection we get this authenticity check
that we need to confirm. That basically means that we're going
to save this server with this IP address as a known
host on our laptop, on our local machine saying
we can actually trust this server. And as you see,
we have connected to the AWS
instance. We are inside the terminal with Ubuntu user
and this is basically the private, the internal IP address of
that instance, which you can also see in the UI. So it starts
with 172 and going back
here, right here you see the private IP address
172, et cetera. And since we are going to be
administering all these servers, obviously we're going
to need root privileges, right? To install different packages,
to install different applications and binaries for kubernetes,
like kubernetes, binaries, the container runtime, et cetera. We're going to
need root privileges. So for those commands we can actually
execute them using pseudo because our ubuntu, the default
Ubuntu user, has permission to
execute pseudo commands like this.
Or you can actually switch to the root user
inside the terminal and then basically work as a root
user. And we can do that by pseudo.
I if I enter.
There you go. Now we are actually logged in
as a root user to the server. So you can administer the
server as a root user. So the servers
are set up, we check the connectivity. Now let's actually
log out from root user, then log out as
Ubuntu user back to our terminal. And in the
next lectures we're going to set up and configure
a master node.
This lecture you will learn the basics of TLS certificates
so that you're able to understand how certificates in kubernetes
work. So how do certificates work in general?
Now at the very basic level, TLS certificate is
a way to establish trust and enable
secure communication between client and server or
user and the application to get the terms right.
In any communication one party is always
initiating the request, so the user or client
is the one that initiates the communication. And on
the other side there is a server or an application or
some kind of service that gets that request and replies to
it. An Internet is used to exchange
all kinds of data, like user accessing their banking application and
their bank details, or a web application requesting
credit card information from a payment service, et cetera.
So anytime personal and sensitive data is exchanged,
this communication has to be secure. Now, what does secure
communication actually mean? Well, let's say an example of a
user accessing their online banking website.
To access their account, the user must first log into the account,
right. Without unencrypted communication,
users login credentials will be sent to the server
in plain text. If a hacker intercepts the traffic,
they will simply see the credentials in plain text and
be able to use it to log in to the user's account.
So, first step for securing
the communication between client and the server is to
encrypt the data so that hackers can
see that in plain text. And encryption is a
concept that has been around for thousands of years.
And at its core, you basically just take a random
string and use it to change the plain text into an
encrypted, non human readable text. And that
random string is called an encryption key. Encryption is
its own subject in computer security, so we won't go
into too much detail of how that works exactly,
but it's enough to know that a randomly generated encryption key
is used to encrypt plaintext data so that hackers
cannot read it. And that same key is then used to
decrypt the encrypted data as well. This kind of encryption,
when you use the same key to encrypt and decrypt the data,
is called asymmetric encryption. Now, when a user logs
into their account, the credentials are sent to
the server, encrypted, so that hacker that is sniffing
the traffic cannot actually read it. The problem is,
though, the server cannot read it either,
because it can't decrypt the data without the
key of the client. So the client needs to send the
encryption key to the server as well. The problem is
that the hacker can also get the copy of that key sent
to the server, and that's where an asymmetric
encryption comes into play.
So instead of having the same key to encrypt and
decrypt the data, we have separate encryption and
decryption keys, also called a key pair.
So you encrypt the data with one key, and you can only
decrypt it with its pair key. So let's see how
this is used to solve the issue of hackers stealing the
client's symmetric key and decrypting the
data. We use asymmetric encryption to securely send
the client's symmetric key to the server.
So the client has a symmetric key for encrypting
its data when sending it to the server. Right on
the other side, we generate an asymmetric key
pair on the server. The server sends one
key to the client. Hackers sniffing the traffic will
also get that key. Client then encrypts
its own symmetric key with the key that server
sent it and sends its own encrypted symmetric
key to the server. Server will then use the other key
to decrypt the data that client sent and extract
the client's symmetric key. Again, Hacker also gets
the client's key, but it can't decrypt it because it
doesn't have the other key that the server has. This way
client was able to send its key to the server securely
and after the exchange the further communication can be encrypted with
a client's symmetric key without hacker being able
to read any of the traffic. And the key that server sends all the
clients and which hacker will be able to get
is also called the public key because it is for public
access. Even hackers can obtain it without any security issues.
And the key that server only leaves for itself to
decrypt the client's data and is not
shared with any client or anyone outside the server
is called a private key because it must stay private and
protected on the server. So the asymmetric key
pair is also called private and public key pair.
Now the hacker is not able to see the data between client and server
and is not able to impersonate the client.
So the only option they have to get your personal data
like login credentials or credit card information
is impersonating the server. So when you
visit your social media page or your banking account
to log in, the hacker manages to route
your request to their own website or application, which looks
exactly the way as the valid website and has a
secure protocol, htps for communication.
So just by looking at the website you don't know whether
it's a fake or a real website. And this way
hacker will act as the real server. It will have
its own asymmetric key pair generated. It will then send
client its public key. Client will encrypt its
symmetric key with Hacker's public key
and send it back, establishing a secure connection
with the hacker's server and any data user
enters like credentials, personal data will end up
on the hacker's computer. So what is a way to avoid
that? Or how can a client validate
that? The public key which server sent it really belongs
to its online banking website or its social media website,
and not a fake hacker website. That's where certificates
come in. The admins of the real website can
get the public key signed and certified by
what's called a certificate authority, or also called
CA is an entity that gives website owners
a digital certificate that certifies the ownership
of that specific website and its domain. So basically,
the owner of the real website and its domain asks an
authorized party to sign their certificate as a proof
that their public key is really for the website,
mybank.com or facebook.com etc.
And this authorized party or certificate authority will
issue a certificate which has a public key embedded
and includes the name of the real website and its domain,
and a signature of the CA. So it has to be
signed by the certificate authority. If the website has
subdomains or any other domains, including the language domains for their
website, all of them should be included in their certificate
for a client to validate them. So when you access
the real website in your browser, the browser which is the client
will check the certificate, make sure the certificate
is valid and issued for this domain name,
and that the signature is from a valid
or authorized ca.
The same way, servers need to also protect themselves from
the hackers, just like clients. So the server can also request
a certificate from the client to verify that it's
talking to the legit client and not a hacker. These are the
client certificates which work pretty much the same way they get
signed by trusted CA, which server can
validate. Now you may be thinking you have never generated
a client certificate for connecting to websites, right?
Well, it actually happens in the background so you don't have to do
it yourself. Otherwise it will be very inconvenient for the website
users if they had to somehow do this themselves.
However, we will see how to generate client certificate
to connect to the Kubernetes API server in
the following lectures.
Now I mentioned that when a server gets a certificate
signed by CA, client will validate and see
that the signature is valid. But how
does the browser know that the CA that signed the certificate
is a legitimate one? Because the hacker could have
created their own CA and issued the certificate for
their public key. So how is client able to validate
that the signature is valid? Well,
there is actually an official list of all authorized
and acknowledged cas, and these cas are trusted
organizations that issue digital certificates,
and each modern operating system has a list of
such cas already packaged inside. That's where browsers can
verify whether the CA is trusted or
not. So when you see the hacker's website, it will have
a certificate that certifies the ownership of the website,
but it won't be signed by the trusted CA.
And when the browser sees that most browsers will
give you a warning saying insecure certificate, meaning it was
not signed by a known or trusted CA one of
the CAS on that official list. It was signed by an unknown source,
which can be hacker's own CA that hacker
generated and used to issue the certificate. This is
also called a self signed certificate. Now, how do we
actually create this key for the server for our
application and get a certificate from a CA?
Well, there are actually simple command line tools such as openssl
a that give you commands to do it. Using this tool we can
generate a private key, and then using that key, we can generate
a certificate signing request with a public key
inside, which we will then send to the CA for signing.