Kubernetes is one of the most popular tools in
cloud computing and is becoming more and more popular
every day. All the projects are migrating to Kubernetes
and it is already becoming the standard in most companies
as a result. Of course, the need for IT professionals
who know Kubernetes is higher than ever and is increasing
every year. But the demand for Kubernetes professionals is
way higher than the number of people who actually know Kubernetes.
This means if you invest time in learning Kubernetes
and getting certified as a Kubernetes administrator,
you'll have an incredible advantage and a head start in your IT
career. Now, Kubernetes is not the easiest tool
to learn, set up and manage, so if you want to become
a Kubernetes administrator you will need to learn a bunch
of stuff. I have taught hundreds of thousands of people
Kubernetes through my videos and now I have created this
full course to teach you everything necessary to get started
with kubernetes from zero and become an expert in
it. You will be prepared to handle any issues in the cluster.
You will know exactly how Kubernetes works and be able
to support teams in your company to use kubernetes properly
after completing this course. This course is mostly demo
led projects where you work hands on along
with me, to practically apply all the concepts you learn,
but also understand the use cases of each concept and
really know why and how to use it. And to make
understanding the theoretical concepts easier. We have
animated videos and real world examples to understand how
it all applies in the real world projects. Now you
also know how important it is to prove your knowledge in
the it world and a certification is a great way to
show your skills and this course prepares you completely
for the CKA exam so that you can become a certified
Kubernetes administrator. So let's go through the course contents
and see what you will learn from our Kubernetes administrator
course. We will start with the main Kubernetes concepts
and understand how Kubernetes architecture works,
what Kubernetes resources are, learn about Kubernetes configuration
files and generally how to work with Kubernetes.
We will then install a Kubernetes cluster from
scratch on virtual machines. For that we will use a
Kubeadm tool and learn and understand all the
concepts about control plane processes, how they work,
how they get configured and so on. You will also learn about
container runtime interface in Kubernetes and how is
it possible to use different container runtime technologies with
Kubernetes. We will also look at a very interesting topic which
is networking in Kubernetes and container
networking interface. We will learn about how pod
networking works and how it is configured, as well as install a
networking plugin to create a networking layer in our Kubernetes
cluster. We will also learn how DNS works in Kubernetes
and learn about core DNS which is the DNS service
in Kubernetes. We will also take a look at how
certificates work in Kubernetes, what certificates get
automatically created, and how you as a Kubernetes administrator
can manage that. In the same section we will also learn
about very important Kubernetes concepts like namespaces,
how to work with Kubectl which is a Kubernetes command line
tool. You will learn about Kubeconfig file and
how to use that to connect to the cluster, as well as how to
configure and modify that and also using Kubeadm
tool you will learn how to join any worker nodes to
the cluster. Once you have installed and configured the cluster,
of course you want to start deploying your applications in it
and make it accessible externally. So we will learn how to deploy
applications inside the cluster using deployments
and how to make them accessible with services.
You will also learn about different types of services in kubernetes,
how to use each one, and more importantly, how they
compare to each other. One of the common ways of configuring external
access to our applications running in Kubernetes is
ingress. So you will learn what ingress controller is and
how to create ingress resources to configure
routing in a cluster. And since we will be installing
the ingress controller application using Helm, you will also learn
what helm is, how it works, and how to use it to
easily install different applications in Kubernetes.
Now of course, you won't be the only one working with the cluster because
developer teams and other people will also need access.