So we have the private and public key pair, but we want the public
key to be certified by a trusted
CA so that clients will accept it. CA will then
actually certify the details of your website,
company, domain name, ownership, etc. All the data that
you entered and if everything is fine they
will issue a signed certificate and send it back to you. So if
the hack try to get the certificate signed by the CA they
will fail in the information validation stage and won't
get the certificate from the CA. So that's how the whole process
works. And this whole infrastructure with the process of
issuing, validating, maintaining certificates as well as
all the CAS involved servers, keys, et cetera is called
a public key infrastructure or PKI.
Now that we have the infrastructure ready, it's time to get started and set
up a Kubernetes cluster from scratch, which is super exciting.
But how does it all work? What applications do
you need to install and how do you install them?
In this section we will go through the whole setup and how everything
works in detail. First we need to deploy
a container runtime on every node so that
containers can be scheduled on them. After that we
need to install Kubelet application also on every node
which will basically run as a regular Linux process
just like the container runtime. So they will both
be installed from a package repository just like we install any
application on Linux servers.
And again these two need to run on each server
whether it's a master node or worker node.
And with these two in place we can now deploy pods for
all the other Kubernetes components on the
control plane node. We need to now deploy pods
which run the master applications. So API,
server, scheduler, controller, manager and eTCD
applications will all be deployed as pods
on the master node. Plus we shouldn't forget
about the kubeproxy application which again will be deployed on
each node because worker nodes also need
them and kubeproxy application will also run
as a pod. Now there are two things
we need in order to deploy these applications.
The first one is that since all these applications are pods,
we need the Kubernetes manifest file for
each application. And the second thing is that we
need to make sure these applications are also deployed securely.
This means unauthorized users shouldn't be
able to access these applications and also the applications
should talk to each other securely in an encrypted way.
So let's see both of these points in more detail.
First of all, as I mentioned, all master components will be
deployed as pods. But as you already know,
we need the master components in order to deploy the
pods, because when deploying a pod, we need
to send a request to the API server. The scheduler
component will then decide where the pod should be scheduled
and also the pod data will be written
into and updated in itSCD storage.
So as you see, when scheduling one pod,
all the master components are involved. So how do
we schedule these components without
having them in the cluster? So we have this chicken
and the egg problem. Well, for that specifically,
we have what's called static pods.
Static pods are basically just like any other pod, but they
are directly scheduled by the Kubelet without
the need for API server or itsyd or
scheduler. So the request for scheduling that
pod doesn't go through the API server, it goes directly
to Kubelet. So once we have the container runtime and Kubelet
running, we can actually schedule these
static pods. So generally with
all the regular pods, as you already learned,
API server will get the request first to schedule
a pod. So scheduler will decide which node it
should be scheduled on and then API server will contact the
kubelet on that selected node
that scheduler selected and tell Kubelet
on that node to schedule the pod. So that's a way of scheduling
regular pods. But in addition to getting these commands from
the API server, Kubelet can actually schedule
pods on its own. How does it happen?
Well, Kubelet continuously watches a
specific location on the node where
it's running. And that location is etcmanifests
and it watches that folder for any Kubernetes manifest
files. And if it finds a pod manifest there,
it will schedule it as a static pod. No master
processes required. Now why is it called
a static pod and how is it different from the regular
pods deployed through the API server?
Well, there are a couple of differences. First of all,
even though static pods are visible on the API server,
they cannot be controlled from there. So it's a responsibility of
Kubelet. So controller manager, for example, doesn't manage
that pod. So if it crashes or doesn't work
anymore, it's Kubelet's responsibility to
pick that up and reschedule it again. And also
you can easily identify the static pods
by their names because at the end of their
name they get a suffix of the node
name they are running on. So this all means that
when installing a Kubernetes cluster, we would need to generate
the static pod manifests for the API server,
controller, manager, scheduler and eTCD applications
and put these manifest files into manifest
folder where Kubelet will find them and schedule
them when
deploying these applications, we need to ensure that they
will run securely. So the question is
how do they talk to each other securely? How can each
component identify the other component
in the communication process and also establish a mutual
TLS connection so that the communication between
them is encrypted? Well, we need certificates
for that. Now let's see exactly who talks to
who in Kubernetes cluster and what certificates we need
for them. Well, the API server is in the center
of all the things and all the communication.
So almost every other component will talk to the API
server and that means every component that wants to
talk to the API server will need to provide a certificate to
be able to authenticate itself with the API server.
So the way it works is we need to first generate a self signed
CA certificate for kubernetes which we will then
use to sign all the client and server certificates for
each component in the cluster. And we can store these certificates
in PKI
folder. So API server will have a
server certificate and scheduler and controller manager
will both have their client certificates to talk to the
API server. Same way API server talks to
ETCD and Kubelet applications,
which means ECD and Kubelet will need their own server certificates.
And since in this case API server is the client,
it will need its own client certificate to talk
to the ETCD and Kubelet applications so
that it can authenticate itself with them. For that
it can use its existing server certificate.
Or alternatively we should create new client
certificates specifically for talking to
iTSCD and Kubelet applications. Kubelet also talks
back to the API server, so it can also use
a separate client certificate for that. So basically
the idea is that whenever an application talks
to the API server, for example,
API server doesn't know whether that application is
a legitimate application, whether the request is coming
from a hacker or an unauthorized source or whatever. So for
API server, any application connecting to it
is basically just a regular client.
And for every such client, API server
needs to make sure that this client
is authorized. And the same goes for
ETCD when API server connects to it. Right.
ETCD has to decide is this client authorized
to talk to me? And to ensure proper identification,
each component will get a certificate
signed by the same certificate authority.
So now when scheduler connects to API server it
will say this is my certificate which is a proof that
I am part of the same cluster as you are.
Therefore I should be allowed to talk to you.
So that's how the whole setup,
public key infrastructure PKI should
work in Kubernetes. So all these components talk
to each other to do their jobs.
But there is one more client that we need to
give certificate or access to the cluster to
and that is ourselves as administrators
of the cluster. Right, because we as admins also need to
talk to the API server to administer it because as
you learned, all the queries and updates in the cluster
go through the API server. And this means we also
need our own client certificate for the admin user
to authenticate with the API server. And of course
to be valid and accepted by API server. This certificate
also needs to be signed by the CA that we created
in Kubernetes. So when preparing the installation
of the cluster, all these certificates need to be created first
the self signed CA certificate for the whole cluster and
then all the server and client certificates which will be
signed by the CA certificate that we created.
So these are the main things that we need
to prepare for the cluster. Plus there are a couple of minor things
and configuration details we also need to provide
to install Kubernetes cluster. So as you
see, all of this is pretty complex and it
would be really difficult to set all this up manually
like generating all these certificates
and making them available for each pod, creating those manifest
files and configurations for the applications
and so on. Well, thankfully there is a command line tool
called Kubeadm or Kubeadmin which
will bootstrap all of this and do all this stuff and
generate all the necessary configurations and certificates
and everything in the background. And Kubeadm
is created and maintained by Kubernetes itself.
So in the Kubernetes official documentation, Kubeadm is
used as one way of installing the cluster and you have all
the documentation of Kubeadm and its commands here and
that's the tool we're going to use to create our cluster.
Great, so now we know what we need to do to install the
cluster, so let's actually go ahead and do it. So you go
ahead and open the Kubernetes documentation to work through it
and use it as a guide. So once infrastructure is
provisioned, we need to check our prerequisites and configure a
couple of things on those servers so that Kubernetes
can work properly on them after installation.
And these are our prerequisites. We already checked this before
creating the infrastructure to make sure we have the required
resources on our servers. And we have a couple of more prerequisite
things here. The first two are already satisfied. We have unique
host names on our AWS infrastructure as
well as our servers are in the same
private network in the VPC. So that
should be fine, but we need to disable the swap and
also open some ports on our machines.
So let's go ahead and do those two things. The first
one is pretty easy to disable swap on our server.
We execute swap of
a command and we need to do that on each of
the servers, so we're going to do that on worker nodes as well later.
And the second thing is about opening ports
on our machine. So if I click here, these are basically a
list of ports that we need to configure on control
plane nodes and on worker nodes. Now what are
all these ports and why do we have to configure them right now?
If we check our AWS infrastructure and
security, for example, you see that we only allow
incoming traffic to our servers on port
22. So that's the only port that is open on our
server. And this is same for all the nodes.
So every node has the same security configuration where
we just allow incoming traffic on port 22
so that we are able to ssh into those servers.
And that's a default config on AWS infrastructure.
This means all the other components that are running on
those servers but on different ports are not accessible
from another instance when we install the cluster.
However, the applications on master nodes and worker
nodes like API server,
scheduler, etCD, Kubelet and so on
need to be able to talk to each other on different ports because
as we learned, these applications communicate with each other to
execute certain tasks like API server
talks to Kubelet and HCD and all other services
talk to the Kube API. And without opening those
ports we wouldn't even be able to join worker
nodes to the cluster or add more master nodes.
So let's configure all this on our AWS,
which is actually pretty easy because we can do this on
the UI using the security groups of our
servers. So again, in the security part of my server I
see which security group it is using and if I click
inside I can actually edit the incoming traffic
or inbound traffic rules of that
security group that will then apply to the server.
So let's click on it and use this security group to configure
rules for the control plane node. So let's go
ahead and open those ports. The first port we have is 6443,
which is the port where by default
Kubernetes API server is running.
And all the clients, whether they are inside the
cluster or outside the cluster, need to be able to connect
to it. So the source is basically every IP address.
So let's copy this port. Let's add the rule that's the port
number. And as I said, every IP address
should be able to access it because API server is
the entry point to the cluster and when we execute Kubectl commands
we want to be able to connect to it from outside the cluster.
So that's one rule. Let's check out other ones. The second
one is a range, a port range from
2379 to 80. So these
two ports are used by itSCD server and we need
to open them as well. However, Etsy server doesn't
need to be accessible from outside the cluster because only
the Kube API server or the ECD itself is connecting
to it. So we don't want to open access to this port
from everywhere, but only from inside
the cluster. So how do we know what is the IP address range
of the instances which are part of this cluster,
so only they need access to it. And remember, in security there
is a best practice that says that you always give the minimum permission
required to do the task. So we only want
these ports to be accessible from within this
private network. And to find the IP address range
of the private network, as you already learned in the prerequisite lecture of
AWS, we go to the VPC where all our servers
are running. So that's the VPC and our VPC
has this IP address range.
So basically that means that any instance which is created
inside that VPC, any server will have an IP
address from this range and we want those
instances to be able to access this port,
so only accessible within that private network. And the
same will be true for these three ports
here, 10,200 and 5251 52,
which are respectively used by Kubelet
application, the scheduler and controller manager. So let's
actually copy the first one and let's make it a range as
well. So 250 to 252,
that's the range. And again, we only allow it
within that VPC private network that
basically configures the ports and access
to these ports on
any server which uses this security group.
And to make it more visible for us, the launch
wizard two. This is the security group that we
just edited. Let's actually give it a name as well.
And let's call it Master security Group.
And going back in the master node and
security,
we see the adjusted security rules or firewall
rules that are configured for the master
node. So master node port configuration is done.
Let's now go and configure the same for worker nodes.
And clicking on worker node one, you see that it uses
a different security group, which worker node
two and one both share. So they use the same security group,
which we're going to now adjust and configure with
new rules. So let's open that edit
inbound rules. And the first rule is
again, Kubelet, which is running on master
and worker nodes. And Kubelet needs to be open because
Kube API server from master Node will talk
to the Kubelet on each worker node. So that's why we
need to make it accessible. So let's copy that port
is 10,250 and
again, only from inside the VPC
because no external connection to
Kubelet is required. So we don't have to give anyone else permission
to talk to it. And the second rule, port range,
which is for node port type
services. So basically whenever we configure, create a
node port service, it will make the application accessible
on one of these ports. And obviously to access the
application on this port, the port needs to be open.
So we're going to copy that and edit
as a range and as a source. We're going to choose
everyone because these ports are basically where
applications will run. So it should be accessible
from browser. So any external client will
be able to access it. And let's save this
again, I'm going to copy the name and
filter it here. And let's call it workersg.
So we have the master security group and worker security group
with different port
configurations. And again, just to make sure,
let's go to worker node one. And there you
go. We have the new rules here. And worker
node two. There you go. So this takes care of the
last prerequisite for opening the required ports
so the cluster can function properly.
And one last thing we're going to do in order to just
optimize our cluster is give our
hosts or our servers a more human readable name. So instead
of the private ip address as a name of the
host, we're going to call master node, master host,
worker one and worker two. So right
now I'm on the master node, so I'm going to connect to
the worker nodes as well,
and the
second worker node.
And there you go. So I'm connected to the master node,
worker one, worker two. However, just from the names
here, I don't know in my terminal
which node is master, which is worker one, and so on. So when
working and administering your cluster,
it's actually very helpful to have that name, the host name appear
right here so that you don't have to go back here and
check basically which node you're on. Right. So that's
what we're going to optimize now. We're going to give these hosts proper names
and that's actually very easy to do. Let's clear this up. We're going
to create entries for the host names in etc
hosts folder and we're going to do that using pseudo.
And at the end of the
file we're going to add an entry or mapping
for IP address, the internal private IP address of
each node and to the name that we want to give it.
So going back again the private IP address
of the node, not the public one because that's how
the instances or the servers talk to each other
within VPC using the private IP address. So copy
that. And this is
going to be the master because that's how we decided.
Then we have worker node one,
let's call it worker one.
And then we have worker two like
this. And we need these three entries
on each node inside this etc
hosts file beam
and it.
So basically what these entries will do on each node
is that whenever the master node wants to talk to
one of these worker nodes, or vice versa, they can
use the names instead of using the ip
address to communicate with each other. So if master
node says let me talk to worker one,
we'll be able to get the ip address behind that worker
one to connect to it. So those host
name to ip address mapping is present on
all the machines. What we also need to do is assign the
host names to those servers. So we
do that using pseudo host name
control. It's a command set hostname
and whatever hostname we want to give it, we're calling it
master. There you go.
We're calling this one worker one and
this one worker two.
And we don't see any changes here. And that's because
we need to log out from the server and then log in again
so that it will take effect. So we're going to do exit and
connect again. And as you see we have master here
and let's do the same here. Reconnect worker
one, exit, reconnect and
worker two. So now it's way easier for us
to administer the cluster because we know immediately which
server or which node we are on provisioned
and configured. And we also made
sure that all the prerequisites for installing the
cluster are fulfilled. So we are ready to start installing
the applications necessary to set up a
cluster. And the first one is a container
runtime. That's the first application that we're going to install
and container runtime is not a Kubernetes
component. It's basically a separate application that kubernetes
will then use to schedule the containers.
However, before we actually install a container runtime, let's actually
understand what a container runtime is.
What options do we have here, as well as
what a container runtime interface actually means.
As you learned in the lecture about Kubernetes architecture,
on every Kubernetes node there needs to be a container runtime
because the applications in Kubernetes run as containers.
Now, important to note here is that not only our own
applications or databases and other services will
run as containers in Kubernetes, but also Kubernetes
processes themselves, such as API server,
scheduler or controller manager, etCD and so on.
All these are applications, right? And they also run as
containers in Kubernetes. So that means
we need a container runtime on both master
and worker nodes. Now, how do we choose a container
runtime? And how is it that kubernetes doesn't care which runtime
we choose and gives us this flexibility to basically plug
in any container runtime we want? Well,
at the beginning, Kubernetes didn't have this flexibility and
it supported Docker runtime as the first container runtime
by having the code to talk to Docker directly into
the Kubelet code. Remember, Kubelet runs on
every node, master and worker nodes, and talks to Docker
to make it schedule containers, so that
code for talking to Docker was inside the Kubelet
code. However, as more container runtimes were emerging,
Kubernetes wanted to make it more flexible and allow
any container runtime usage with Kubernetes. But integrating
code to talk to all these different runtimes would have been
time consuming and increased the code maintenance effort for
Kubernetes developers because you would need to have separate
code for each container runtime.
Instead, Kubernetes decided to create a single generic
interface where any container runtime who implemented
that interface could be plugged into. And this
plugin interface is what's called the container
runtime interface. So container runtime interface,
or CRI, is basically a set of rules
that defines what a container runtime technology
must implement and how it should implement it in order
for it to be pluggable to Kubernetes as a container runtime.
And through this interface, Kubelet will be able
to talk to it to schedule containers, pull images,
et cetera. Now, Docker, which was the
first container runtime, did not implement CRI
rules, so Kubernetes developers needed to now reintegrate
Docker with Kubelet using the CRi.
How did they do that? Well, they created a Cri
compatible layer in their code for Docker
specifically, which is called Docker shim.
And shim basically means a bridge or connection
between two things. So Docker Shim is part of Kubernetes
code, which lets Kubelet talk to Docker using
the container runtime interface API.
Now, as I mentioned, Docker was the first, most popular
container runtime and important one to be supported.
But it's more than just a container runtime.
Docker is also used to build the images.
So whenever you write an application that needs to be deployed as a
container, you build a Docker image out
of it. It also has its own command line interface and
user interface, so container runtime is
just one part of the Docker technology.
But Kubernetes only needs the container runtime
part of Docker. It doesn't actually need any other parts. And with
the time more lightweight and more fitting container runtimes
emerged that didn't have all these extra
components that Kubernetes didn't actually need. And two of
the most popular container runtimes that emerged
are container D and cry O.
So Docker was not the number one runtime option anymore.
And also Kubernetes team had to continue maintaining the
Docker sheam code to keep Docker support, even though
it doesn't implement the CRI standard like other runtimes.
So Kubernetes recently decided to deprecate and stop
maintaining the Docker shim in version 120
and then completely remove it in version 1.22,
which would mean Kubernetes will not directly support Docker
runtime anymore. Now, does that mean you can't use
Docker in kubernetes from version 122?
No, because if Docker itself or some other company decided
to maintain the Docker shim code or create a service
similar to that, you can deploy that service with
Docker and it will still work. However, it's better to
use more lightweight container runtimes instead of Docker,
especially because you can still pull and run docker
images with other container runtimes. So you can be
creating a bunch of docker images for your applications and running
them in Kubernetes cluster that uses a container D runtime
and that will work just fine. So there is really no reason
to use Docker as a container runtime anymore, and that's what
all cloud platforms are doing. Aws,
Google Cloud, Azure cloud, et cetera all use container
D as a container runtime in their managed Kubernetes clusters.
And that's also what we're going to do. We're going to install and
use container D as a runtime in our cluster,
which is just as easy to install as Docker. So there should be no
big difference there. The only thing would be that we
won't be able to execute Docker commands on Kubernetes nodes
to check and troubleshoot the containers. But again,
in most cases that shouldn't be necessary since we're going
to be working on a Kubernetes level using Kubernetes tools
to troubleshoot applications.
Interface is and also we decided to
install container D runtime on our cluster.
So how do we install it again? You as a
Kubernetes administrator, you are trying to work through the
documentation. So you click on container runtimes link
here and you see those three runtimes are listed.
Click on container D and you have the installation guide for container
D for your cluster right here.
So this is exactly what we're going to do and we're going
to execute these commands one by one. So going back to my master
node, execute the first command which basically
creates this container D configuration file with the list
of necessary modules that need to be loaded for container
D. And after that we execute these two commands which
will then actually load those container
D modules. You don't have to understand these in detail. That's why you
have these installation guides usually wherever you need
them, so you can just copy and paste them. So let's grab
the next one which again creates a
configuration file for Kubernetes
cri config, which very simply explain
just sets these three
parameters that we need for container D. And finally
to apply those parameters we are going to execute this
command. And there you go, you see also an output here applying
the config file that we created with those kernel
parameters. So this will take care of configuring
the prerequisites for container D before we install
that. And after that we are going to actually install container
D and apply the configuration with these steps.
So first of all, install the container d package
and we can do that very simply by simply using
our Aptget package manager on ubuntu. So let's
clear this up and let's do pseudo aptget
update to first update the repositories.
And after that we're going to do pseudo
aptget install container
D and let's execute confirm
and this will install container d application as
a next step, we're creating a containerd configuration folder
in etc. And then inside that folder we're
creating this default configuration containerd
config default. This gives us default configuration for containerd
and we are saving that into that file. So let's
execute those two.
And finally we restart the
running container D with the updated configuration.
And now container D actually should be running on our node
and of course we would like to check that. So for that
I'm going to do service container d status
and this will give us the status of container d, which is
active in a running state. And you also see
some of the logs on startup, no errors here,
everything looks fine. Alternatively, you can also check the status
of a running process on the server using system control
command,
system control status and then the service name which
is again container d and you get basically the same output
here. So both commands work the same way.
And as you already know, container d process needs to be
installed on every single node in the cluster.
So we are going to install that on worker one and worker two
as well. But to make our work a little bit easier, instead of going
through these commands one by one, again we're just going
to create a script basically that will just execute in
one step so we don't have to type out the commands.
So I'm going to copy this first and let's create an install
sh. I'm going to
paste the whole thing in there. After setting
these prerequisites and configuration, we then
installed the container d using package
manager. So we did pseudo aptget
update pseudo aptget
install container d and
there you go. And finally we can also print out the
status of container d at
the end of the script execution. And there is one thing we need to do
in an automated script which is manually confirm
the installation of a package. So basically
we need to add this y option here
so that it gets automatically confirmed and the script will continue.
And basically that's our container D installation script.
We're going to save this install sh file
by default is not executable because it
doesn't have an execute or x permission here.
So to make it executable we're going
to add an execute permission and
we are going to edit only for our user.
And let's see now we can execute that
script. Also have color coding for executable files
and now we can do install sh.
Everything got successfully executed and we see the active
status of container D started. Container D container
runtime. Awesome. To exit from here we can
just click letter q and it will
quit the output. So basically we have a container
D running here as well. Let's copy
the install sh contents for
worker node two as well.
Let's paste them in there, save it,
do the same thing, make it executable,
and execute the
script. Cool. So the first step
of cluster installation is done. We have a container
runtime container D running on every
single cluster node to
install the Kubernetes processes on
master and worker nodes. And as I mentioned in
one of the previous lectures, we will use the Kubeadm
tool to deploy those processes. So how does Kubeadm
actually work? First, we install Kubeadm tool on each
of the nodes, just like we installed the container runtime.
Once it's available on the servers, we can execute different
commands with it. The very first command we execute
with Kubeadm is Kubeadm init command,
and this command will be executed only once on
one of the master nodes. Remember, master node at the beginning
is just an empty server, and we turn it into
a control plane or master node by executing
Kubeadm init on it. This command will basically
orchestrate the whole cluster setup. It will
generate etc folder
and inside that will put all the generated certificates,
all the Kubernetes manifest files for Kubernetes applications.
It will also create all the necessary configurations for these
applications like API server, kubelet,
etcd and so on. When the manifest files get
generated and put into the etC Kubernetes
manifests folder, Kubelet, which looks for any
static pod manifests in that location, will detect them and
start those static pods with the suffix
of the hostname. Kubelet will ask container d
runtime to fetch all the images for
the applications in those manifests and to
eventually schedule them as containers. So at the end
we will have all the processes up and running and Kubernetes
cluster will have been initialized with just one
node. So we're going to have a one node cluster,
basically. So we need to install Kubeadm on our server now.
But an important point here is that Kubeadm
does not install and manage Kubelet,
which means before we initialize the cluster,
we need to install Kubelet as well. And finally,
when we create the cluster, we need to interact with
it to administer it, right? So we're going to install
the third application, which is a Kubernetes client
command line tool called Kubectl. So again, for comparison
here, if you got confused by those similar
names of the three applications, Kubelet is
a process that we need to run pods on master
and worker nodes equally. Kubeadm is a command line tool
that we use to initiate or create the
Cluster and Kubectl is a command line tool
that we use to work with the cluster once it has been
created. So we're going to use Kubeadm only once
at the beginning to initiate the cluster. And after
that Kubectl is going to be our main Kubernetes
tool that we will be working with to create Kubernetes components,
get information about these components, etc.
And all these three tools or applications are
maintained by kubernetes and have the same release
versions. So let's install them again. If we
go back to the documentation after installing runtime,
that's the next step to install these packages,
Kubeadm, Kubelet and Kubectl. And installing them is
also very straightforward. We just need to follow the instructions here.
Choose the instructions for our operating system.
This one is for debian based distributions like Ubuntu.
So that's the guide we use.
So the first step is before we install Kubelet,
Kubeadm and Kubectl to basically configure
the Kubernetes repository that holds those packages.
So we need to connect the apt package manager on Ubuntu to Kubernetes
apt repository so that we can then
install packages from it. So the first one here
basically just installs packages needed to
set up the Kubernetes repository. So let's copy
them and execute them again starting with master pseudoept
get update and installing those
three packages.
The second step which downloads
Google Cloud public signing key. This is what our package manager
will need to connect to the repository. And finally
we add the repository to our
package manager's repository list. And there
you go again, Aptget update and
this command will actually install Kubelet,
Kubeadm and Kubectl commands.
And since we're not specifying versions here,
this will just download the latest stable versions of
each component. As I said, these three components actually
have the same release cycle so it will be the
same version. But what if you want to install a specific
Kubernetes version? First of all, how do you look up what
versions you have available? And second, how do you then specify
that? Well, let's actually delete that and list
all the versions that we have available for Kubeadm.
For example apt cache
using this command. If I execute this,
you will see all the versions available and
the latest one is this right here. So this will be installed by default
if we don't specify a version. And let's say we don't want the latest
version, we want this specific version right here,
1.210.
So let's copy that.
So that's our version. Let's just execute it, comment it out. So we
have it there. And I'm going to copy the installation
command again. And let's specify that version for
each package. Again, they have the same versioning,
so each one will get the same version and this will install
Kubernetes version 1.210.
And let's execute.
And finally, the last command,
which is EPTM mark hold for each of
the packages. What this basically does is it prevents
these packages from being automatically upgraded or
removed. So it basically fixates the version to
whatever is installed. And this is good
if you want to keep your cluster stable and prevent,
for example, accidental upgrades of any of these packages.
So let's execute that as well. And that's
basically it. We have now Kubelet installed,
which is running as a service. And we can also check that using
service Kubelet status. And you will
see that Kubelet is actually not in a
running state. It says activating and a
failure status, which is actually expected at this stage because
Kubelet doesn't have anything to do at this moment. So basically,
Kubelet is just waiting for Kubeadm to
initialize the cluster and tell Kubelet
what pods to schedule and basically what to do. So once we initiate
and create the cluster, Kubelet will be in a running state.
So we say that Kubelet is installed. We also have Kubeadm
command and
the version that we installed, which is 1.210,
as well as Kubectl version, which is the same.
And note that at this point, we don't have the cluster up
and running. We haven't initiated the cluster, we haven't executed
Kubeadm init command. We have just installed all the
tools that we need for setting up the cluster.
And these are exactly the same tools that we need on worker nodes
as well. So let's go ahead and do the same installation
process on each of the worker nodes.
And I'm going to do it the same way as for container deal.
And let's call this install Kubernetes components
sh and
basically just copy paste those commands.
And here, do not forget the version
because each node of course, needs to have
the same versions. So let's
specify that as well.
And that's it. That's our script for installing Kubernetes
components. Let's also make it executable and
execute.
Everything looks fine. Let's check that Kubelet is
present on the machine as well as
cube, Adm and Kubectl.
Everything looks fine. Let's copy
the installation, script it
and there you go.
Check the kubelet and
its version and it seems like everything was installed successfully
and now we actually have the same exact state on all
our nodes. So we have container
d running on each node. We have Kubelet running and
waiting for Kubeadm to basically give it some commands
to schedule pods. And we have Kubeadm and Kubectl
command line tools installed on each of the nodes.
So everything is present on the machines to
create a cluster. And now it's actually time to turn
this server into a master node using
kubeadm init command.
Execute pseudo kubeadm
init command. And we need pseudo here because Kubeadm
will actually write the generated configuration files
into etcubernetes folder which
is accessible only for root user. So we
need the root permission to execute the init command.
So let's do that. And now Kubeadm is actually
doing everything that we went through in the
installation overview lecture and basically bootstrapping
the whole cluster in the background.
Awesome. We just initialized a Kubernetes cluster and
created a master node and there are a bunch of things that
happened in the background that we also see in the output.
So let's check out some of the interesting stuff here.
First of all we have this pre flight stage.
So Kubeadm executes everything in different stages
in pre flight stage. Basically all the checks will
be made to ensure that our servers are in
the proper state so that Kubernetes cluster can be installed
on it. Another thing that is done in preflight mode is
downloading or pulling all the images that are needed
to start the Kubernetes components and to set
up the cluster. The next phase as you see is
certificates or certs stage and this is where
generating all the necessary certificates takes
place. The first step is creating this
etcuberpki
folder. This is where all the generated certificates will
be put and we can actually check that folder.
As you see we have a bunch of certificates here. We have
the central component which is API server has the
server certificate and private key which is used for others
or clients to connect and authenticate. API server
the API server also has client certificates
to talk to HCD and Kubelet services.
And you also see that CA certificates were
generated. So this is a self signed CA
of Kubernetes which basically signs all the other
certificates and inside that you also see Etsy
folder. So ECD basically has its own certificate
authority and it has its own server certificates
because ETCD doesn't actually talk to anyone other than itself
or its peers. If we have multiple ETCD replicas,
it only has the server certificate so that API server
can talk to it. So as you see, ETCD has its
own CA to sign its server certificates and
API server has its own CA to sign its server
certificates. So that's the certs phase. Then we
have Kubeconfig generation phase where basically
for every client that needs to talk to API
server, Kubeconfig files get created. Again, we can see
that in Kubernetes folder,
so we were in the PKI folder, but inside
this Kubernetes folder we have all these
Kubeconfig files for each of the clients that
are connecting to the API server controller manager,
Kubelet scheduler and admin user
which we can use to connect to the cluster and administer
it. Another important thing that Kubeadm does
in the background is configuring the Kubelet environment.
So you remember that Kubelet was in a state of basically
activating and waiting for Kubeadm to give
it instructions of what to do.